<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description>Aut tace aut loquere meliora silentio</description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 17:18:52 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Beyond</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/beyond/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1639479657l/58849383._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Stephen Walker
	  (2021)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      The space race from the American perspective is well-known: this book presents the same race from the Soviet perspective.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The differences are profound, of course, mainly driven by the Soviet programme occurring in complete secrecy to duck the risks that failure would have on the programme's image. The American programme by contrast was conducted in the open at least as far as the actual "shots" were concerned – and their public failures did indeed endanger their ability to continue, at least in part because neither public nor politicians understood the process of engineering or just how &lt;i&gt;hard&lt;/i&gt; each shot was. The deep irony is that the Soviet successes appeared so sudden and dramatic they led directly to the deepening of the American programme and commitment or more money and effort than the Soviets seemed able to maintain to capitalise on their early lead.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There are plenty of revelations even for those with a detailed interest in space history. I remember hearing all through the 1970s that the Soviet spacecraft landed on land, but it turns out that in many cases the cosmonauts were bailing-out and parachuting to earth instead, with this being intensively covered-up even to the extent of falsifying reports to the international organisation responsible for certifying "firsts" in space.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;While the achievements of both programmes were profound, they were perhaps doomed in the long term by a lack of vision for what they were actually &lt;i&gt;for&lt;/i&gt;. The benefits of space technology are now obvious; those of exploration perhaps less so, although it doesn't (in my opinion) require much suspension of disbelief to feel that science-driven activities lead almost inevitably to enormously valuable spin-offs. The fact that we can't quantify these &lt;i&gt;a priori&lt;/i&gt; shouldn't (in my opinion, again) stop us keeping the faith in the value of experiments that advance our science &lt;i&gt;and&lt;/i&gt; engineering in ways that wouldn't otherwise happen.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	5/5.
	  Finished Sunday 21 April, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6395477584?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/beyond/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Emergence of Numerical Weather Prediction: Richardson's Dream</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-emergence-of-numerical-weather-prediction-richardsons-dream/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1348662620l/275229._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Peter   Lynch
	  (2006)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A very technical examination of the world's first numerical weather "prediction" – although in fact it was really a "postdiction", taking detailed data and using it to compute a scenario that could be compared against a known ground truth. It was an incredible achievement anyway, performing manually and at low resolution the calculations now routinely performed by computers.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Richardson was the person who saw that this would be possible, realising that the physics and mathematics could be solved even though the computational capabilities didn't exist. In this he foresaw the emergence of the modern power of data, where the existence of more and better data transforms both the way we do science and the sciene that we do. It's something that should put him alongside Turing and Von Neumann as visionaries of what computation could achieve.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Sunday 21 April, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6326779093?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-emergence-of-numerical-weather-prediction-richardsons-dream/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>TIL: Cognitohazards</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2024/04/12/til-cognitohazards/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orga506648" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orga506648"&gt;TIL: Cognitohazards&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orga506648"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Could social media posts be actively damaging to our mental health?
– literally, not just figuratively? That's the premise of &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2024/apr/09/techscape-deepfakes-cognitohazards-science-fiction"&gt;a
TechScape article in The Guardian&lt;/a&gt;, that draws on both science
fiction and psychological research.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In Neal Stephenson's "Snow crash" there is a plot device of an image
in a metaverse that, when viewed, crashes the viewer's brain. We
haven't seen this in social media (yet), but there's an increasing
concern about deepfake images and other forms of misinformation.
Research suggests that such images are damaging &lt;i&gt;even if viewers
know that they're fakes&lt;/i&gt;, which suggests that techniques like
content-labelling images as AI-generated are insufficient to remove
their harm. Other examples include massively engaging artificial
images such as the "pong wars" animation of two simultaneous
"Breakout" games going on between two algorithms: something that
shouldn't be as engaging as it is (as I can attest to myself).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Social media attention grabbing at an industrial scale might
therefore constitute a &lt;i&gt;cognitohazard&lt;/i&gt;, a way of hacking people's
brains simply by being viewed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>internet</category><category>social media</category><category>til</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2024/04/12/til-cognitohazards/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 11:18:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Great Post Office Scandal: The fight to expose a multimillion pound IT disaster which put innocent people in jail</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-great-post-office-scandal-the-fight-to-expose-a-multimillion-pound-it-disaster-which-put-innocent-people-in-jail/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1636495053l/59581993._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Nick Wallis
	  (2021)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      The history of what is still as I write this an ongoing scandal: perhaps the greatest miscarriage of justice in UK history, when the Post Office turned on and prosecuted its own operators for fraud on the basis of flawed evidence from its Horizon IT system.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The scandal came from a series of interlocking arrangements. The Post Office could mount prosecutions in its own right (something that its management now claims to have been unaware of), with its own investigators able to interview under caution but seemingly not required to record interviews or allow legal representation. The contracts under which postmasters operated were mis-represented to turn any discrepancies into the postmasters' fault, while simultaneously denying them the data they'd need to investigate themselves unless they were exceptionally careful and persistent – and the few who &lt;i&gt;were&lt;/i&gt; were prosecuted and driven out anyway. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As a computer scientist I have to say that the most ridiculous part of the story is the presumption in law that a computer system works properly absent explicit to the contrary, that – when coupled with an asymmetry of who can access to software and its logs – makes it impossible to fight against computer-generated evidence. No system of this size &lt;i&gt;ever&lt;/i&gt; works flawlessly, and a careful designer would add features on that assumption, such as paper-trails or detailed logs that can then be forensically analysed. Equally, no such system would ever be constructed without remote access to terminal endpoints to allow problems to be remotely fixed, and again a careful designer would ensure that such interventions were logged so as to be auditable. This is so self-evident that I find it hard to believe that Horizon &lt;i&gt;wasn't&lt;/i&gt; designed that way, which makes the repeated denials even more suspicious.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But there's a social commentary here too. The justice system, juries, and the communities of the prosecuted postmasters were almost eager to believe their guilt. Part of that was the lack of proper media scrutiny to bring the extent of prosecutions into the public eye, and part due to obfuscation by the Post Office itself – but it surely there should be systemic oversight of such things, given the massive consequences. And surely communities should have been less ready to believe accusations made against their own members that went against the evidence of their own eyes.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Sunday 7 April, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5897614552?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-great-post-office-scandal-the-fight-to-expose-a-multimillion-pound-it-disaster-which-put-innocent-people-in-jail/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Loving Common Lisp, or the savvy programmer's secret weapon</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2024/04/02/loving-common-lisp-or-the-savvy-programmers-secret-weapon/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org237bc98" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org237bc98"&gt;Loving Common Lisp, or the savvy programmer's secret weapon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org237bc98"&gt;
&lt;p class="floater"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://simondobson.org/attachments/7a/bd1498-3024-4f11-91a7-97f3e99084d7/screenshot.png" alt="nil"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mark Watson.  &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://leanpub.com/lovinglisp"&gt;Loving Common Lisp, or the Savvy Programmer’s Secret
Weapon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. Leanpub. 2023.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While pitched as a way of sharing the author's enthusiasm for Lisp
(which really shines through), this book is really a deep
demonstration in using Lisp in modern applications – from web
APIs and the semantic web to deep learning, large language models,
and chatbots.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In some ways, like many other Lisp books, it's really two books in
one. The first chapters are introductory – and to be perfectly
honest could be dispensed with, as they're inadequate as a proper
introduction and there are far better introductions out there. The
later chapters focus on applications, and provide the real value.
One could criticise them as often tying-together tools in other
languages, with the Lisp code basically being glue; but that's a
very effective way of leveraging all the code and services out
there, and is an important technique for Lisp programmers too.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>applications</category><category>lisp</category><category>project:lisp-bibliography</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2024/04/02/loving-common-lisp-or-the-savvy-programmers-secret-weapon/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 15:57:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Lisp in space</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2024/04/02/lisp-in-space/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org9238410" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org9238410"&gt;Lisp in space&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org9238410"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://corecursive.com/lisp-in-space-with-ron-garret/"&gt;Lisp in space&lt;/a&gt; (podcast, 38 minutes)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
An interview on the Corecursive podcast with Ron Garret.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In 1988 (when, for context, I was in the second year of my BSc)
Garret started working on autonomous navigation software for
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sojourner_(rover)"&gt;Sojourner&lt;/a&gt;, NASA's first Mars rover, which flew in 1997. He used Lisp
to do planning, essentially developing an entire domain-specific
language for autonomous vehicles. The project was never flown, as
NASA opted for a far less ambitious approach to driving to rovers –
a decision that Garret now considers to have been the correct one.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But that isn't the end of the story, because Garret then went on
to develop an autonomous Remote Agent controller for the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deep_Space_1"&gt;Deep
Space 1&lt;/a&gt; technology demonstration mission that performed asteroid
and comet fly-bys. Without spoiling to story, the spacecraft flies
with a full Lisp system onboard, and Garret gets to interact with
its REPL at a distance of 30 light-minutes &lt;i&gt;via&lt;/i&gt; the Deep Space
Network – surely the longest latency of any REPL session ever!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's an fascinating insight into both the potentials of Lisp and
the political difficulties that using a non-standard development
language can engender.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>applications</category><category>lisp</category><category>project:lisp-bibliography</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2024/04/02/lisp-in-space/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 15:32:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Red Memory: The Afterlives of China's Cultural Revolution</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/red-memory-the-afterlives-of-chinas-cultural-revolution/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1701695268l/174927273._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Tania Branigan
	  (2023)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      It's unusual to read a book that probably couldn't have been written before &lt;i&gt;or&lt;/i&gt; after it actually was: the political environment of China thawed just enough to give people confidence to speak to a foreign author about the events of the Cultural Revolution.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The horrors shine through, in the memories of the young Red Guards and their victims. But so too do the current sensitivities, not least in the rather farcical museums and monuments that can be found across China – but that can't be visited, because the custodians race to close them up "for maintenance" as soon as a visitor arrives. It's a different approach to that described in &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/50215644.Between_Two_Fires_Truth__Ambition__and_Compromise_in_Putin_s_Russia" title="Between Two Fires Truth, Ambition, and Compromise in Putin's Russia by Joshua Yaffa" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Between Two Fires: Truth, Ambition, and Compromise in Putin's Russia&lt;/a&gt;, where museums are re-assigned to new curators who subtly change their message, but it reinforces the fears that authoritarian regimes have of their own histories and those who might actually remember them.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;China has never had a public reckoning with the Cultural Revolution – and it doesn't look that it will have one for a long time. The message of this book is that this hiding of the past continues to do damage to the present, not least because it provides a vague and unexamined fear of disorder that can be used to justify repression "in case it happens again". But the fact is that it didn't just "happen": it was commanded, by a regime that's the linear predecessor of the current leadership who seem to want to both disown it &lt;i&gt;and&lt;/i&gt; levarage it for their own ends.&lt;br&gt;
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Saturday 30 March, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6326777750?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/red-memory-the-afterlives-of-chinas-cultural-revolution/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Lisp hackers: Interviews with 100x more productive programmers</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2024/03/23/lisp-hackers-interviews-with-100x-more-productive-programmers/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc3ce0d6" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc3ce0d6"&gt;Lisp hackers: Interviews with 100x more productive programmers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc3ce0d6"&gt;
&lt;p class="floater"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://simondobson.org/attachments/4f/11131f-cfc4-4d14-8fae-72c78607964b/screenshot.png" alt="nil"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Vsevolod Dyomkin.  &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://leanpub.com/lisphackers"&gt;Lisp Hackers: Interviews with 100x More Productive
Programmers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. Leanpub. 2013.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not convinced by the sub-title: at the very least, there's no
evidence to support the claim that Lisp programmers really are
hundreds of time more productive. But there are some serious
insights here from individuals who've made serious contributions
to the Lisp world – and beyond. The contributions all take the
form of email interviews consisting of a standard prelude of
questions (how did you discover Lisp?, do you use it at work?)
followed by a couple of questions tailored to the interviewee.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The practitioners selected have all been affected by Lisp, either
in terms of it changing their own thought processes, or by helping
to develop the core ecosystem, or by applying Lisp to real-world
problems, and often to great effect. My favourite was the
discussion with someone who was using Common Lisp to develop
low-latency network routing for financial services: it's hard
to think of a better example of Lisp's power and range.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>experience</category><category>lisp</category><category>project:lisp-bibliography</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2024/03/23/lisp-hackers-interviews-with-100x-more-productive-programmers/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2024 14:57:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>My Lisp experiences and the development of GNU Emacs</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2024/03/23/my-lisp-experiences-and-the-development-of-gnu-emacs/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org07eea9a" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org07eea9a"&gt;My Lisp experiences and the development of GNU Emacs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org07eea9a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/gnu/rms-lisp.html"&gt;My Lisp Experiences and the Development of GNU Emacs&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The never-dull Richard Stallman talks about his experiences with
Lisp and with the development of Emacs. It's got some useful
observations on &lt;i&gt;why&lt;/i&gt; Lisp became the core of Emacs: it was news to
me that this hadn't always been the case. It started with an
"editor control" language in the spirit of editors like &lt;code&gt;ed&lt;/code&gt;. But as
people wanted more support from their editor, they wanted to
program it more effectively.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The language that you build your extensions on shouldn't be
thought of as a programming language in afterthought; it should be
designed as a programming language. In fact, we discovered that
the best programming language for that purpose was Lisp.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The result was a re-write of Emacs in C (for portability), with a
Lisp interpreter specialised towards editing tasks.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He then gives an insider's perspective on the Lisp machines and
their evolution, as well as revealing the genesis of his ideas for
the free software movement. While these are interesting to read,
it should be noted that much of it has been rebutted: his
description of the formation and later history of the two
spin-outs, Symbolics and Lisp Machines Inc, is strongly disputed
by Dan Weinreb on &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090101103828/http://danweinreb.org/blog/rebuttal-to-stallmans-story-about-the-formation-of-symbolics-and-lmi"&gt;his blog&lt;/a&gt;.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>experience</category><category>lisp</category><category>project:lisp-bibliography</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2024/03/23/my-lisp-experiences-and-the-development-of-gnu-emacs/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2024 14:55:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Romanovs: 1613-1918</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-romanovs-1613-1918/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1435023227l/21094391._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Simon Sebag Montefiore
	  (2016)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      When complimented on his armies capturing Berlin at the end of the Second World War, Stalin famously replied that "Tsar Alexander made it to Paris." This book describes how, and why, that happened – and why it meant to much to Stalin, on whom Sebag Montefirore is of course a recognised expert.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The sweep of Romanov history is epic in all senses. It's impossible not to realise how deeply &lt;i&gt;personal&lt;/i&gt; their rule was, identifying their own reigns absolutely with Russia and its greatness. The main characters are all flawed in tragic ways, sometimes grotesque but equally often brilliant and self-aware within the limitations of their eras – which none ever really managed to trascend, with the possible exception of Peter and later Catherine, each known as "the Great" for that reason.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The story is made powerful by recent research in the Russian archives and access to previously-unkown letters between Alexander II and his mistress, and later between Nicholas II and Alexandra. They highlight the impact of extra-marital affairs on high policy right across the Romonov era: it's often hard to keep track of who is related to (or sleeping with) whom, or to understand the true importance of some of the less well-known characters in the story who may have have had an advisory impact far beyond what their "official" position might suggest.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's a book that's hard on autocracy – but also quite hard on the alternatives that came after. Sebag Montefiore sees a continuity between the tsars, Lenin, Stalin, and Putin, and almost seems to regard it as inevitable that Russia will need strongman leadership. One can perhaps hope not.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	5/5.
	  Finished Saturday 23 March, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1522092865?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-romanovs-1613-1918/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>