<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description>Aut tace aut loquere meliora silentio</description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 10:11:28 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Lisp from nothing</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2025/11/26/lisp-from-nothing/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb3d1ff4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgb3d1ff4"&gt;Lisp from nothing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgb3d1ff4"&gt;
&lt;p class="floater"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://simondobson.org/attachments/c8/94f691-a88c-44ba-8366-02aa08aad82b/screenshot.png" alt="nil"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Nils Holm.  &lt;i&gt;Lisp from Nothing&lt;/i&gt;. Lulu Press. 2025.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is a fascinating book that's very old-school – and I mean
that in the best possible way. It does exactly what it says:
develops a Lisp interpreter (and then a compiler) from first
principles, bootstrapped on top of an existing Lisp or Scheme
against a runtime written in C, with all code provided.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's more than this, though. There's a thorough discussion of the
differences between dynamic and lexical variable scope (and the
implications for both programming and implementation). There's a
digression into pure lambda calculus and the complexities that &lt;i&gt;it&lt;/i&gt;
introduces. There's a basic mark/sweep garbage collector. There's
a brief history of Lisp and Lisp machines. And there's a
performance evaluation that digs into where the costs lie within
the system.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Overall this is a book that every implementor should read, if only
to see some other parts of the possible design space for Lisp
tooling. Many applications will want to occupy a different point
in that space, for example providing a richer compiler, or a
richer runtime. But there's a lot to learn from the simplicity of
the choices made here.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>implementation-techniques</category><category>lisp</category><category>project:lisp-bibliography</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2025/11/26/lisp-from-nothing/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 10:06:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Book-Makers: A History of the Book in Eighteen Lives</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-book-makers-a-history-of-the-book-in-eighteen-lives/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1705463614l/195430889._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Adam Smyth
	  (2024)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A fascinating history of bookbinding and printing. You may have to be fanatical about your books and book technology to fully enjoy it – but I certainly did.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There are plenty of vignettes and personalities on offer, alongside a deep understanding of the history that accepts the boundaries of what's knowable. The value we place on certain books shifts with time, with Shakespeare's First Folio simply being one amongst many when it is first printed. And the notion of canonical texts can be fluid, with several often entirely different editions of &lt;i&gt;Hamlet&lt;/i&gt; to choose from, as well as an active sub-culture of after-market book repurposing ending in modern zines and found-media works.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The most fascinating aspect for me was the way that some books have been lost and are known only through commentaries on them that (perversely) survived – and some are known through having been cut-up and re-used as parts of the bindings of other books, for example to make covers essentially from &lt;i&gt;papier mâché&lt;/i&gt;, from which they have been recovered during re-binding.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The style can be a bit annoying in places, a mispaced need for levity that comes across as far too heavy-handed and trite. But overall this is a great read, equally full of information and entertainment.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	5/5.
	  Finished Saturday 22 November, 2025.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6768865458?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-book-makers-a-history-of-the-book-in-eighteen-lives/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Knowledge: How to Rebuild Our World from Scratch</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-knowledge-how-to-rebuild-our-world-from-scratch/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1393226489l/18114087._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Lewis Dartnell
	  (2014)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      I'm hard-put to classify this book. On the one hand it's an engaging and valiant attempt to illustrate the crafts that would need to be retained (or rediscovered) after a civilisational collapse – or at least after &lt;i&gt;one kind of&lt;/i&gt; collapse such as a pandemic that leaves the infrastructure intact by decaying rather than pulverised. Dartnell seems to think a more fierce collapse would be unsurvivable, and so focuses on the more positive possibility.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;He traverses a lot of technologies, including for agriculture, building, transportation, clothing, chemistry, and communications. He (correctly in my view) identifies the scientific method itself as the most valuable technology to retain, and explores some of the ways in which modern society is contingent on specific historical accidents that a re-booting society need not copy.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But it's also frustrating. As a scientist and engineer I wanted more detail: perhaps there's a need for another, "how to" manual alongside this book. And Dartnell seems to have a very cavalier attitude towards safety, mentioning and understating the dangers of (for example) lye once and then making use of it extensively, which is a recipe for disaster on the part of any practitioners. And the book is a little too broad, rather than focusing on the technologies of immediate relevance in the aftermath of disaster: should we really be thinking about building vacuum-tube electronics when even basic agriculture is such a challenge?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Despite the positivity on display, reading this confirmed my thinking that a recovery after a disaster would be protracted, with no way to avoid a return to feudalism and warring bands. In that sense technology would be the least of the survivors' worries.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	3/5.
	  Finished Saturday 22 November, 2025.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/7939944087?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-knowledge-how-to-rebuild-our-world-from-scratch/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Early LISP history 1956--1959</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2025/11/07/early-lisp-history-11956-19591/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbb236cc" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgbb236cc"&gt;Early LISP history (1956–1959)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgbb236cc"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Herbert Stoyan.  &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/800055.802047"&gt;Early Lisp History (1956–1959)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. In &lt;i&gt;LFP ’84:
Proceedings of the 1984 ACM Symposium on Lisp and Functional
Programming&lt;/i&gt;, pp.299–310. 1984.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A study of Lisp's evolution from first proposal to practical
implementation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It begins with McCarthy's proposal (co-authored with Marvin
Minsky, Nathaniel Rochester, and Claude Shannon, and dated 31
August 1955) for a summer research project at Dartmouth College to
"study the relationship of language to intelligence".
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In a later (handwritten!) note McCarthy homed-in on the core
challenges in this programme: the lack of a clear way to describe
&lt;i&gt;procedures&lt;/i&gt; to each other (what &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2024/01/27/structure-and-interpretation-of-computer-programs/"&gt;Abelson and Sussman&lt;/a&gt; later refer to
as &lt;i&gt;procedural epistemology&lt;/i&gt;), and the tight binding of programming
systems at that time to specific machines, and hence their need to
bow to engineering (rather than semantic) considerations. The
language that became Lisp sought primarily to overcome these two
challenges.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The journey proceeded by taking the list data structures developed
by Allen Newell and Herb Simon as part of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logic_Theorist"&gt;Logic Theorist&lt;/a&gt; and
embedding them into FORTRAN (for which there was already a working
compiler) – which also incidentally muddied the conceptual waters
by trying to express list and list-functional concepts in a
language built around numbers that barely allowed functions to be
defined by the user at all. Indeed, McCarthy and others had
long-running problems accepting that the list-processing functions
&lt;i&gt;were&lt;/i&gt; functions, given that their result does not depend solely on
their arguments when viewed at the lowest level. This shows how
pernicious a low-level implementation can be. The final resulting
language, the FORTRAN List Processing Language (FLPL), shared many
programming approaches function names with what became Lisp.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
McCarthy went on to champion the functional approach, including
the invention of conditional expressions (alongside or replacing
conditional statements) and the power of the different kinds of
function composition and higher-order functions. It's important to
remember that McCarthy's driving interest remained in AI, not
programming languages &lt;i&gt;per se&lt;/i&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Already in 1956 it was clear that one had to work with symbolic
expressions to reach the goal of artificial intelligence.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Which is a fascinating piece of history in itself, as a large
branch of modern AI concerning machine learning and large language
models has explicit rejects this view in favour of sub-symbolic
AI. Which approach is "correct" in whatever sense remains to be
seen.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But it remains McCarthy's contributions to programming languages
that stand out. As well as conditional expressions he can be
credited with garbage collection, meta-circular interpretation,
and clarifying the relationship between programming and proof:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We should mention here that McCarthy at the same time conceived the
idea of logic-oriented programming, that is, the idea of using logical
formulae to express goals that a program should try to establish and
of using the prover as programming language interpreter.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
(Although it's important to recognise that Newell and Simon's
work, on logic as an application rather than as a general
programming language, pre-dates McCarthy's.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>history</category><category>lisp</category><category>project:lisp-bibliography</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2025/11/07/early-lisp-history-11956-19591/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 09:44:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The history of Lisp</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2025/11/07/the-history-of-lisp/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org67a97ae" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org67a97ae"&gt;The history of Lisp&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org67a97ae"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Herbert Stoyan.  &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.softwarepreservation.org/projects/LISP/book/Stoyan-Geschichte.pdf"&gt;The History of Lisp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. 1980. Updated in the 1990s,
translated into English 2023.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Includes a history of the route from PLANNER to CONNIVER, in which
the former was criticised for being a theorem prover when a
programming language was needed – an argument between two schools
that's still going on today, as seen in the emergence of &lt;a href="https://lean-lang.org/"&gt;Lean&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>history</category><category>lisp</category><category>project:lisp-bibliography</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2025/11/07/the-history-of-lisp/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 08:49:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>History of Lisp</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2025/11/07/history-of-lisp/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd92a09b" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd92a09b"&gt;History of Lisp&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd92a09b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
John McCarthy.  &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/history/lisp/lisp.html"&gt;History of Lisp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. Artificial Intelligence
Laboratory, Stanford University. 1979.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
McCarthy's own take on the early history. It's quite brief, but is
very careful to give broad credit to the others who were involved
in the practical creation of the language.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's also got some great vignettes on &lt;i&gt;why&lt;/i&gt; certain features came
about - for example garbage collection coming from the need to
clean up intermediate structures when experimenting with symbolic
differentiation. McCarthy acknowledges taking the notation for
functions from Church, before admitting that he didn't understand
the rest of &lt;i&gt;Calculi of lambda conversion&lt;/i&gt; and so wasn't tempted to
add the more general aspects!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Perhaps the most fascinating part of the story is that it was
originally so divorced from actual computers. The team had defined
an &lt;code&gt;eval&lt;/code&gt; function for interpreting Lisp programs – in the process
making the decision to represent the programs as lists – before
realising that this could be made interactive to provide a running
interpreter.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What did McCarthy think of his creation? He was conscious that it
would have a lifetime:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
LISP will become obsolete when someone makes a more comprehensive
language that dominates LISP practically and also gives a clear
mathematical semantics to a more comprehensive set of features.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Haskell has a plausible claim to have accomplished the latter but
this doesn't seem to have led domination in practice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>history</category><category>lisp</category><category>project:lisp-bibliography</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2025/11/07/history-of-lisp/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 08:47:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Passenger (The Passenger #1)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-passenger-the-passenger-1/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1646843143l/60581087._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Cormac McCarthy
	  (2022)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A book with wonderful writing by somehow missing something.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And the writing really is superb. McCarthy can build a scene out of almost no words, even somewhere as unfamiliar as a New Orleans flophouse or a powerboat traversing the Caribbean. He can also build credible character backstories for those with even the least credible histories without it ever feeling contrived.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But... The book is premised on a mystery, the finding by divers of a plane crashed at sea that's clearly been visited before they get there, with something of value having been removed. What was it? Why was it valuable? Why are there federal investigators chasing it? – and why do so many of the people involved wind up inexplicably dead? That's a fascinating set-up, and so it's deeply disapointing that it remains exactly that: a set-up, unexplained and unresolved. It's not that there's a lack of plot, it's simply that it leads nowhere, and that's a wasted opportunity for so gifted a writer.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	2/5.
	  Finished Wednesday 22 October, 2025.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6808789445?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-passenger-the-passenger-1/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Brave New World and Brave New World Revisited</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/brave-new-world-and-brave-new-world-revisited/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1331315450l/5479._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Aldous Huxley
	  (1960)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Tuesday 7 October, 2025.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/303643166?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/brave-new-world-and-brave-new-world-revisited/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 09:38:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Neuromancer (Sprawl #1)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/neuromancer-sprawl-1/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1167348726l/22328._SY160_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	William Gibson
	  (1984)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	5/5.
	  Finished Sunday 5 October, 2025.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/303647008?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/neuromancer-sprawl-1/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2025 17:35:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sawdust Caesar: The Untold History of Mussolini and Fascism</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/sawdust-caesar-the-untold-history-of-mussolini-and-fascism/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1245562266l/3788812._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	George Seldes
	  (1935)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &lt;i&gt;"All of Mussolini's monuments will be monuments to the strength of a weakling."&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A journalist's account of Mussolini's rise to (and exercise of) power, written by someone who both lived through parts of it and had significant contacts with the man himself. Despite being written at a time when Fascism was still being somewhat celebrated, and even admired, it's quite a scorching read that dismantles many of its pretensions with both observations and data. It would have provided a lot of ammunition to those wanting to avoid fascist takeovers in their ovn countries to read exactly how imaginary the claims of Fascist Italy were, no matter how dramatically and repeatedly proclaimed.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Surprising for a book of its kind and date (it was first published in 1935), Hitler is conspicuous by his absence, mentioned only in passing: there are far more comparisons with Napoleon. It shows how different history looks when lived forwards.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The title is interesting: Shirer uses a similar turn of phrase to describe Mussolini in &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/767171.The_Rise_and_Fall_of_the_Third_Reich_A_History_of_Nazi_Germany" title="The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich A History of Nazi Germany by William L. Shirer" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich: A History of Nazi Germany&lt;/a&gt; (although he does not reference Seldes as a source). Mussolini's will to power easily overrides any principles he may have had, which makes it hard to decide whether fascism itself had any principles or was simply the inflation of one man's will: Mussolini seems to have been unclear about that himself, but resolving it may be key to understanding the modern trends towards authoritarian politics.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Saturday 20 September, 2025.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6638300592?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/sawdust-caesar-the-untold-history-of-mussolini-and-fascism/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>