<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description>Aut tace aut loquere meliora silentio</description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 08:05:33 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Islands of Abandonment</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/islands-of-abandonment/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Islands of Abandonment&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1645656810l/41830657._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Cal Flyn&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2021
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A book one perhaps shouldn't enjoy as much as I did, but as an exploration of what happens when humans leave a landscape – whether one they've polluted or simply one they've abandoned – it's actually quite reassuring even in the midst of it's being shocking.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There is alost nowhere that's so polluted that life of some kind can't regain a hold, given enough time. That (as Flyn herself is at pains to point out) is not an excuse or a invitation to more spoliation, or to not prosecuting polluters; but it is a reminder that we avoid pollution and climate change &lt;i&gt;for ourselves&lt;/i&gt;, not because the natural world will be irretrievably damaged if we don't: the climate emergency is about saving ourselves, not about saving the planet.&lt;br&gt;
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 01 April 2023.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4954082332?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/islands-of-abandonment/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 14:03:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Plot Against America</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-plot-against-america/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;The Plot Against America&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1553896240l/703._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Philip Roth&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2004
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A carefully-constructed counterfactual of a fictional Lindbergh presidency and of America's descent into fascism – before being saved from itself by the entreaties of a revered and bereaved widow. It's clever and evocatively written from the perspective of a 9-year-old surrogate of Roth himself, and so convincing that the author feels the need to include a summary of the real historical figures he mentions as an appendix.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Reading this book in 2023 brings out some echoes that perhaps wouldn't have been apparent on an earlier reading. There's a lot of consideration of fake news, of misinformation and questionable government initiatives, and even of a "Big Lie" that populists and fabulists can lock onto. And it's shocking that some the anti-Semitism that existed before and during the war still exists today, in an increasingly-less-camouflaged form.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  3/5.
	    Finished 01 April 2023.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2892855684?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-plot-against-america/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 13:59:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Information: A History, a Theory, a Flood</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-information-a-history-a-theory-a-flood/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;The Information: A History, a Theory, a Flood&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1348046486l/8701960._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;James Gleick&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2011
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A popular history of information, and of information theory and computing in particular.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Like Gleick's other books, this book walks the fine line between too much science and too little depth. It avoids the maths entirely without ever abandoning the core insights that the maths provides. That's something many scientists long to achieve, but seldom do: focusing on the concepts and treating the maths as a machine that's only valuable once the concepts have been assimilated. Richard Feynman would have approved.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This book is strongest on Shannon and Babbage, two of the geniuses (along with Turing, von Neumann, and a few others) of the information age as it emerged over the course of a century from mathematics and engineering. The excursion into physicists' treatment of information is less convincing (at least from my computer scientist's perspective), not least because of the inevitable confusions thrown up by quantum information.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 01 April 2023.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4958606303?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-information-a-history-a-theory-a-flood/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 13:53:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Curse of Bigness: How Corporate Giants Came to Rule the World</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-curse-of-bigness-how-corporate-giants-came-to-rule-the-world/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;The Curse of Bigness: How Corporate Giants Came to Rule the World&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1605751283l/55936629._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Tim Wu&lt;/h2&gt;
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A history of corporate interactions with government and customers: in particular, the rise and fall of idea of anti-monopoly and the different philosophies that underpin regulators in the US &lt;i&gt;versus&lt;/i&gt; Europe. The feeling is one of ... well, if not hopelessness, than of an inadequacy of democratic governance in the face of enormous corporate spending on lobbying and political influence to protect corporate greed and profit.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's perhaps unfortunate that I read this at the moment when the corporations identified as the major threats – the tech giants – were busily shedding staff and possibly collapsing to a shadow of their former (and intended future) selves. It demonstrates that what sometimes feels like inevitable and inexorable triumph is often just a phase: that the largest, most successful, corporations are often brought low sooner and more unexpectedly than anyone could have conceived in the times of their pomp.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  3/5.
	    Finished 01 April 2023.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5291445526?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-curse-of-bigness-how-corporate-giants-came-to-rule-the-world/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 13:43:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>More than the Sum of the Parts: Complexity in Physics and Beyond</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/more-than-the-sum-of-the-parts-complexity-in-physics-and-beyond/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;More than the Sum of the Parts: Complexity in Physics and Beyond&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1657236556l/61063423._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Helmut Satz&lt;/h2&gt;
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A great introduction and overview of complex systems.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The definition of &lt;i&gt;complex system&lt;/i&gt; is itself ... well, not obvious. Sometimes &lt;i&gt;complex&lt;/i&gt; feels like a synonym for &lt;i&gt;not understood&lt;/i&gt;, but actually it's more precise than that, referring to systems whose processes can exhibit macro-scale behaviour that isn't simply the aggregation of the micro-scale behaviours of its components: the canonical example is that water freezes, but a single water molecule doesn't. Another approach is to use the term to describe systems where chains of cause and effect are difficult to disentangle.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Whichever definition you prefer, this is a gentle but still very scientific introduction. There's enough maths for it not to feel shallow, but little enough for it to be widely accessible even when dealing with concepts like entropy that are often a challenge to explain clearly. There's a really good discussion of criticality and universality, as well as the irreversibility of phase transitions such as sand pile transitions. It'd be a good introduction for students.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 16 February 2023.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5310451098?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/more-than-the-sum-of-the-parts-complexity-in-physics-and-beyond/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 16:59:05 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Plutoshine</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/plutoshine/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Plutoshine&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1638799159l/57427661._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Lucy Kissick&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2022
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	It's incredible to read a science fiction book that's so informed by something as recent as the "New Horizons" mission to Pluto: a book that couldn't have been written, or whose several key plot elements would have been different, if written fives years earlier. This is a political take on terraforming, focusing on the fact that all major movements are always problematic and opposed s they get started; but it's also about capitalism, family dynamics, and the search for scientific fame that the author has (I imagine) experienced first-hand.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  3/5.
	    Finished 05 February 2023.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4773468600?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/plutoshine/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 12:38:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Dawn of Everything</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-dawn-of-everything/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;The Dawn of Everything&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1656329733l/59603245._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;David Graeber&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2021
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A book with an amazign ambition: to re-visit and re-interpret the whole of political theory from a basis in modern anthropology and archaeology.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The authors have done a deep dive into not only modern archaeological evidence but also into the nearly-forgotten thinkers of the early Enlightenment. And they make some startling discoveries. Wehn we think of the Enlightenment, we think of something unique to a particular moment in European history when the rights of god and kings were being questioned for the first time. But many of the thinkers didn't see it that was at all: they were responding to critiques of the European system by Native American observers, who – far from being overawed and impressed by modernity – were disgusted by the poverty and arbitrary violence they saw: so different to their own societies. This re-discovery leads to further re-considerations: of the linear flow of development, the occurrance of an agricultural revolution as a particular turning-point moment (and whether it persisted), the emergence (or not) of hierarchies and kings, all backed up evidentially from recent sources.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Graeber and Wengrow take issue with the narrative of inevitability in the route to modern civilisation. In part this is based on the observation that many "events", such as the adoption of agriculture, weren't "events" at all, but happened over a period of centuries, were unevenly adopted and frequently rolled-back. Their central theme is that it's a mistake to think of early civilisations as blank canvases in which nothing political happened: that's an assumption, and not one supported in any way by the physical or even the literary evidence.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;They frame their ideas of liberty around three freedoms: freedom to move, freedom to disobey the orders of others, and freedom to re-imagine society. (The last is obviously very different and more abstract than the first two.) They contend that modern societies have become "stuck" without these freedoms as a matter of choice, not of historical inevitability.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's a persuasive narrative, impeded slightly by the very wealth of detail they marshall in its support. And there are some crious omissions: no consideration of anarchy or Kropotkin's &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/51306.Mutual_Aid" title="Mutual Aid by Pyotr Kropotkin" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Mutual Aid&lt;/a&gt;, and (more surprisingly) no reference to Isiah Berlin's &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/36551865.Two_Concepts_of_Liberty_An_Inaugural_Lecture_delivered_before_the_University_of_Oxford_on_31_October_1958" title="Two Concepts of Liberty An Inaugural Lecture delivered before the University of Oxford on 31 October 1958 by Isaiah Berlin" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Two Concepts of Liberty&lt;/a&gt;, although his ideas are clearly part of their intellectual background. Still, this is an intensely political book that deserves a wide reading, if only to defeat the notion that we've somehow arrived at a civilisational peak from which there's no sense in deviating.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 05 February 2023.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4931822228?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-dawn-of-everything/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 12:33:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A quick function to delete whitespace in Lisp programs</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2023/01/13/a-quick-function-to-delete-whitespace-in-lisp-programs/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org74202a8" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org74202a8"&gt;A quick function to delete whitespace in Lisp programs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org74202a8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've recently found myself constantly introducing – and then deleting –
whitespace when writing Lisp. A quick bit of Emacs hacking fixed it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2023/01/13/a-quick-function-to-delete-whitespace-in-lisp-programs/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (4 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>emacs</category><category>lisp</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2023/01/13/a-quick-function-to-delete-whitespace-in-lisp-programs/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 15:32:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>UNIX: A History and a Memoir</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/unix-a-history-and-a-memoir/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;UNIX: A History and a Memoir&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1571699686l/53011383._SX98_SY160_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Brian W. Kernighan&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2019
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	You probably have to be a hard-core Unix head to get anywhere with this book – but it's a gem if you are. Kernighan was there throughout what is possoibly the most formative period of computer history, when Unix was developed and many of the paradigms of operating systems and software tools were developed.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There are other books that handle many of the stories in greater detail, but this book is great for the "sweep" of Unix through Bell Labs and out into the world. The memoir parts are perhaps the most interesting, as they illuminate how the various tools came into being and why. There are cameos by people like Richard Hamming, whose own scientific contributions are matched by his insistence that you can only do important work if you first find the important problems, and by both an expected and unexpected cast of pioneers. I'd like to find a similar book on the early years of Lisp showing how decisions that now seem to be inevitable came to be made, and what alternatives there might have been.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The most hard-core part of the book? It was written using groff, the GNU successor to the roff text formatter than Kernighan himself wrote.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  5/5.
	    Finished 04 January 2023.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4414445582?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/unix-a-history-and-a-memoir/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 15:35:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The First World War: A Complete History</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-first-world-war-a-complete-history/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;The First World War: A Complete History&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1426809743l/191413._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Martin  Gilbert&lt;/h2&gt;
	    1994
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A thoroughly readable narrative history of the First World War and its aftermath. I think the strongest parts are the beginning and end: there's an unavoidable tedium in the middle that reflects the statis of trench warfare.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Churchill comes out well, perhaps unsurprisingly in a book by one of his biographers. Later authors place more of the blame for Gallipoli at his door. The American army also comes out well; Pershing, its commender, somewhat less so, as his insistence on having a solely American field army delayed their deployment and in many ways invited disaster in 1918. The Kaiser cuts a sorry figure throughout, belligerent and indecisive and blind to reality right up until the end.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Gilbert is also very strong on the often-overlooked mior allies of both sides. The complexities of Polish and Finnish independence movements, allied to the Central Powers largely in order to defeat Russia, get a lot of exploration, as does the eventual breakup of the Habsburg Empire. The Middle East and the Ottoman Empire are less well-covered. In each case there are clear lines drawn to the peace treaties and the grievances that later gave rise to the Second World War.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 04 January 2023.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5135648149?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-first-world-war-a-complete-history/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 15:27:40 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>