<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about bonanza)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/bonanza.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:simon.dobson@computer.org"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2022 08:05:41 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Fall: The Mystery of Robert Maxwell</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/fall-the-mystery-of-robert-maxwell/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1577249624l/52240874._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;John  Preston&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2021
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		As biographies of monsters go, this is one of the best. It sets out the whole sweep of Robert Maxwell's complex and in the end perplexing personality: someone who courageously fought the Nazis, but committed (and admitted to) war crimes, who made and lost fortunes but never escaped the need to aggrandise. He transformed academic publishing – something I, as an academic, was unaware of – but engaged in outlandish stunts and competitions in tabloid journalism. His death was as dramatic and inexplicable as many of the events of his life.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It would be an easy story to sensationalise, and while there's some of that in this book, overall it reads as a balances account by someone without too much of a stake in the outcome. It's perhaps inevitable that the story has been overshadowed by the later tribulations of Ghislaine, Robert Maxwell's daughter, but these events are in many ways foreshadowed by her earlier history. They're certainly all of a piece with the story told here.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Thu, 10 Feb 2022 00:00:00 -0800.  
		Rating 4/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/fall-the-mystery-of-robert-maxwell/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Covent Garden Ladies</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/the-covent-garden-ladies/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1597761814l/54869220._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Hallie Rubenhold&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2005
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		An entertaining dive into a part of 18th-century society that's too often only considered voyeuristically. The survival of "Harris' List" provides a starting point, but it's the detailed archival study and the willingness to dig into the histories of the three main protagonists that really sets this book apart. In doing so it also gets to uncover some of the grimier realities of living on (or close to) the streets in a period when money was all that really counted in terms of life chances.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Rubenhold is very sympathetic to the Covent Garden ladies. "Prostitutes" (or "harlots" in the TV adaptation) is a too-harsh judgement: many adopted sex work only because society gave them no other options, or adopted it only periodically when forced to by poverty, or as a semi-acceptable companion to stage-work. She is also unforgiving of the male customers, who avoided most social sanctions or consequences.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The fact that "Harris' List" ran for nearly four decades (and that we have examples of most of them) also makes it a revealing social document as the mores and morals of society change across the 18th century. The descriptions become less straightforward, more ornate and (one would imagine) less useful as time goes by and the publishers become more susceptible to legal action for obscenity (even as the underlying social conditions remain largely unaddressed).
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Sat, 22 Jan 2022 00:00:00 -0800.  
		Rating 4/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/the-covent-garden-ladies/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Stoned: Jewelry, Obsession, and How Desire Shapes the World</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/stoned-jewelry-obsession-and-how-desire-shapes-the-world/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1435608799l/25817092._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Aja Raden&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2015
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		The desire for jewels exists everywhere, and this is an overview written by someone with a deep understanding of jewellery and its place in both fashion and politics. There are some great vignettes, especially about the rise of cultured pearls and the influence of De Beer's on the emergence of diamonds as fashion essentials. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Raden is less sure about history, though, and sometimes gets carried away with detail that doesn't in any way relate to the issues at hand. Many of the comments are alarmingly ahistorical: describing Mary Tudor as "mad" and "insane", for example, for actions that were perfectly sensible in the context of a religious war between Catholics and Protestants. And the notion that there being no market economy means that nothing can have value assigned to it, or that any attempt to better workers' conditions amounts simply to socialism, betrays her own background more than it illuminates either the history of the jewellery.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Sun, 21 Nov 2021 00:00:00 -0800.  
		Rating 3/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/stoned-jewelry-obsession-and-how-desire-shapes-the-world/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2021 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Souls of Black Folk</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/the-souls-of-black-folk/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1309202855l/318742._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;W.E.B. Du Bois&lt;/h2&gt;
				   1903
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		This is a hard work to capture succinctly. A collection of re-worked essays that address the concerns of those working for civil rights in the early 20th century, looking at the failure of Reconstruction and unable to see the currents that would lead to the civil rights movement of the 1960s and its limited successes.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There are some things that place the writing in its particular time. There's an acceptance of race, of racial differences and distinct, widely shared racial characteristics that is jarring to the modern ear. There's also a casual anti-Semitism that's perhaps even more shocking when deployed in the cause of emancipation by such a deep thinker who mainly overflows (at least in the main part of the book) with inclusivity towards white Americans.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The essays range in tone from the high idealisation of education in "Of the training of Black men" to the howl of anguish in "Of the passing of the first-born". And then – in this edition, anyway – there's the sudden &lt;i&gt;volte face&lt;/i&gt; of Du Bois's later thought in "The souls of White folk", where he interprets the First World War as the start of an anti-colonial struggle that's redolent of much recent writing in the same vein.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's only having read Du Bois that I (as a non-American) really come to appreciate his influence and hear the echoes of his thought. Certainly he is being channelled directly in &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25489625.Between_the_World_and_Me" title="Between the World and Me by Ta-Nehisi Coates" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Between the World and Me&lt;/a&gt;, and his ideas and even his speech patterns come through clearly in the voices of the modern civil rights movement.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Mon, 01 Nov 2021 14:27:17 -0700.  
		Rating 5/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/the-souls-of-black-folk/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 21:27:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fracture: Stories of How Great Lives Take Root in Trauma</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/fracture-stories-of-how-great-lives-take-root-in-trauma/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1628358479l/56852065._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Matthew Parris&lt;/h2&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		An enjoyable, if limited, read.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The author's hypothesis is that a lot of "great lives" – and he admits to not being able to define what this means clearly – are formed in childhood trauma. Some of the examples (especially Edward Lear and Rudyard Kipling) illustrate this perfectly. But to coverage of the lives chosen, one in detail and then others in a manner that is really rather perfunctory, left me feeling rather short-changed about the lives not fully explored.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But Parris seems to lose conviction in his approach for three of the later chapters, which deal with trauma in fiction. That's a statement about what we find meaningful or entertaining rather than being about biography, and these feel like "fillers" rather than properly contributing to the book.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Tue, 14 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 3/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/fracture-stories-of-how-great-lives-take-root-in-trauma/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Invasive Aliens: The Plants and Animals from Over There That Are Over Here</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/invasive-aliens-the-plants-and-animals-from-over-there-that-are-over-here/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1542091854l/41716135._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Dan Eatherley&lt;/h2&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		The story of plants and animals invading the UK, mainly (though not entirely) with human intervention. Full of anecdotes and strange twists as species interact.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's hard to say whether the overall impact of invasive species is positive or negative. It's remarkable that many species that invade other countries do &lt;i&gt;better&lt;/i&gt; there than they did at home, which is a positive for global biodiversity in a sense. I also hadn't realised how deliberate a lot of introductions were, and how two-way they went between Europe and the "New World".
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 3/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/invasive-aliens-the-plants-and-animals-from-over-there-that-are-over-here/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fordlandia: The Rise and Fall of Henry Ford's Forgotten Jungle City</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/fordlandia-the-rise-and-fall-of-henry-fords-forgotten-jungle-city/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1312052193l/6214108._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Greg Grandin&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2009
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		A story that's hard to categorise.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the early 20th century, Henry Ford needs rubber for his car tyres. He is persuaded to set up a plantation in the Amazon, where rubber originated, and thus to bypass the global market for rubber that's dominated by rubber grown in Malaya from purloined Amazon seeds.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But rather than simply do this, Ford also attempts some major social engineering. And not for the first time: other Ford facilities offer great wages, but at the cost of intensive domestic surveillance to ensure workers' compliance with Ford's social theories. As a result the master of capitalism falls foul of capitalism at work in providing services for his workers that he'd rather they didn't have access to.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The most amazing thing about this story, to my mind, is exactly how &lt;i&gt;little&lt;/i&gt; time Ford's men spent on the problems of actually growing rubber, compared to the time they spent on labour relations that could easily have been side-stepped. The people trusted with managing the task were loyalists without strong technical backgrounds, and it's hard to see them surviving in roles that were more central to the Ford enterprise.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Tue, 27 Jul 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 4/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/fordlandia-the-rise-and-fall-of-henry-fords-forgotten-jungle-city/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tyrant: Shakespeare on Politics</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/tyrant-shakespeare-on-politics/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1549316807l/41817492._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Stephen Greenblatt&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2018
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		An analysis of Shakespeare's treatment of tyranny in several plays: the Henry VI series, Richard III, Macbeth, King Lear, A Winter's Tale, and Coriolanus. All fascinating discussions as they stand, written by an individual who's clearly a deep Shakespeare scholar – but also cleverly addressing contemporary political themes and events. Make England Great Again!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As with much such scholarship, it often begs the question of how much Shakespeare &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt; meant what is imputed to him: to what extent is his writing a mirror onto which we can project any theme of interest? Perhaps that's not such an interesting question in this case, though, as the reflections cast by the plays – histories and tragedies, including a couple considerably less well-read or -performed in modern times – are really illuminating of the timelessness of events that sometimes feel like they're uniquely modern, rather than be reiterations at some level of eternal themes. The power of this is shown by the fact that this book was published well before some of the events that it parallels, such as the 6 January 2021 storming of the US Capitol. That I think makes clear the depth of the historical context.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Tue, 08 Jun 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 5/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/tyrant-shakespeare-on-politics/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 08 Jun 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Labours of Love: The Crisis of Care</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/labours-of-love-the-crisis-of-care/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1599726850l/55288837._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Madeleine Bunting&lt;/h2&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		Part policy exploration, part history, part memoir, and part anthropological study, this is a detailed and deeply worrying take on the state of modern British healthcare – the most loved and trusted part of the British State that has been under constant attack for decades. Why is that? – why would politicians seeking the approval of voters nevertheless fail to support and recognise the one thing that all voters admire? And do so with such fake affectations of care?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The notion of "care" itself, both as a noun and as a verb. comes under scrutiny. It's a word that's replaced a rich vocabulary of terms, bring aspects of medical and social services that were all previously regarded as separate under a single rubric. And perhaps that's the root of the problem. By destroying the subtlety in search of management and measurement, it becomes easier to neglect the essence of what's being provided and turn social care (and mental health care in particular) into "Cinderella services" adrift from public attention.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Sat, 05 Jun 2021 04:33:32 -0700.  
		Rating 3/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/labours-of-love-the-crisis-of-care/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 11:33:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>It Gets Me Home, This Curving Track: Objects &amp; Essays 2012-2018</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/it-gets-me-home-this-curving-track-objects-essays-2012-2018/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1550777290l/44083289._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Ian Penman&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2019
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		Reports from music criticism. While it presents itself as a book of essays, it's actually an anthology of the author's book reviews over the past decades. That's not a criticism, although until you realise what's happening it's confusing to see repeated mentions of a particular book.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The essays/reviews range over big names like Frank Sinatra, Elvis, Charlie Parker, and Steely Dan, and the lesser-known like John Fahey and entire scenes like the Mods. One name that's missing, but that strangely haunts the book by her absence, is Billie Holiday: I think it's all the jazz references, but you can feel that she &lt;i&gt;should&lt;/i&gt; be here in her own right – and then I read the introduction (having read the book), and read the author's explanation of why he didn't feel he could do her justice. Hopefully he'll write another book just for her.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 4/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/it-gets-me-home-this-curving-track-objects-essays-2012-2018/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>