<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about bonanza)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/bonanza.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 09:13:10 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Herding Hemingway's Cats: Understanding how our genes work</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/herding-hemingways-cats-understanding-how-our-genes-work/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Herding Hemingway's Cats: Understanding how our genes work&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1456091835l/25663760._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Kat Arney&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2016
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A masterful telling of modern genetics.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Everything you know about genetics is wrong: what's how it feels, anyway. The simple story about mutation and inheritance is ... well, not wrong exactly, but woefully incomplete. I think part of the problem is that we lack the right analogies. Genetics is &lt;i&gt;in no way&lt;/i&gt; a blueprint that's simply read when creating life, nor is it &lt;i&gt;in any way&lt;/i&gt; constructed like engineering. Instead it operates at the boundary of chaos, with multiple redundant (and often conflicting) mechanisms finding an uneasy hoeostasis. Genes aren't elementary packets of information, nor does most of the genome consist of them: nor, indeed, is there any well-agreed notion of what a gene actually &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt;. The basic mechanism of RNA reading DNA and then being used to create proteins comes with a set of baroque extensions, as does the supposedly clear notion of heritable characteristics being frozen in the DNA itself.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;All in all it's amazing that any of it is understood at all – let alone well enough to perform modifications and other feats of modern biotechnology. Arney in many ways achieves the impossible in this book, not hiding the complexity of dumbing it down for a popular audience, but also never getting lost or adding to the inevitable confusion that all this complexity induces even in a scientifically literate reader. I learned a huge amount and had several confusions sorted out for me (to the extent that they are understood at all).
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  5/5.
	    Finished 27 November 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5039953329?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/herding-hemingways-cats-understanding-how-our-genes-work/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2022 13:31:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Painful Truth: The New Science of Our Aches, Agonies and Afflictions</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-painful-truth-the-new-science-of-our-aches-agonies-and-afflictions/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;The Painful Truth: The New Science of Our Aches, Agonies and Afflictions&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1628874970l/55539729._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Monty Lyman&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2021
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A book about pain, and why it isn't what we think.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The conventional wisdom is that pain is caused by damage, but it's more subtle than that. Pain is a &lt;i&gt;signal&lt;/i&gt; that can be triggered by damage, but can also be caused in response to less physical causes such as fear and a memory of past damage – and can be suppressed by activity or positive thinking, at least to a degree. This is awkward ground, as Lyman recognises: it's close to saying that "it's all in the mind", which is both literally true and deeply offensive to those suffering persistent pain. But it also offers hope that enormously dangerous pharmaceuticals can – sometimes – be replaced or complemented with cognitive therapies that might be effective.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Everyone has had the experience of being deeply engaged in some activity, incurring damage, and not noticing until afterwards. Soldiers frequently report it: they also sometimes feel significantly less pain from their injuries than civilians, because an injury that takes you off the battlefield makes you &lt;i&gt;safer than you were&lt;/i&gt;. The signals get mixed, and the pain felt changes accordingly. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's much to like in this book, not least a very thorough treatment of placebos. It does sometimes get lost in reporting yet another clinical trial, or yet another insight into neurochemistry. It sometimes feels a little too long and too well-referenced for a popular science take on the issues.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  3/5.
	    Finished 03 November 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5012548665?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-painful-truth-the-new-science-of-our-aches-agonies-and-afflictions/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 22:44:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>We Are Bellingcat: Global Crime, Online Sleuths, and the Bold Future of News</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/we-are-bellingcat-global-crime-online-sleuths-and-the-bold-future-of-news/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;We Are Bellingcat: Global Crime, Online Sleuths, and the Bold Future of News&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1596434293l/54680228._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Eliot Higgins&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2021
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	The history of a still-evolving open-source intelligence collective.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Intelligence collection and analysis used to be limited to governments and a handful of companies. Not any longer: the tools are available on the open internet. Eliot Higgins realises that he can use them to investigate news stories, including the shooting-down of MH-17 over Ukraine. It's this investigation, in which he and his volunteer analysts manage to argue convincingly that the culprits were Russian-backed separatists using Russian anti-aircraft missiles, that really demonstrates how much information can now be found and cross-corollated. The result is for formation of Bellingcat, an amorphous group of international investigators organised in a way that closely resembles that of an open-source software project, where all that matters is an individuals' ability and willingness to share findings, and to have them challenged and possibly refuted in the search for the best explanations.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The book was written before the Russian attack on Ukraine, and so will demand a follow-up given Bellingcat's deep involvement in tracking the conflict and digging-into the details of individual incidents.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  5/5.
	    Finished 16 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4688233164?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/we-are-bellingcat-global-crime-online-sleuths-and-the-bold-future-of-news/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 14:40:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Secret History of Wonder Woman</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-secret-history-of-wonder-woman/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;The Secret History of Wonder Woman&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1408310844l/21855259._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Jill Lepore&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2014
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A comic-book character who not only has a back-story of her own, but also a fascinating creation story, altogether more interesting than those of the other DC and Marvel universe characters.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's an unsettling story, though. The creator of Wonder Woman, William Moulton Marsten, is the somewhat discredited inventor of the lie detector who spent decades trying to persuade law enforcement authorities to take his rather bogus claims seriously. (That he eventually partially succeeded probably worth a book in itself.) He also had a position as an advisor to Hollywood during on of its periodic moral panics, and had an unusual home life involving a wife and a live-in lover pretending to be his children's nanny (while actually being mother to some of them).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Despite all this, the women in his life seem to have exerted an enormous influence over his creation, who is far more independent and feminist than anything else in the genre at that time. While Marsten comes across as unbearably creepy to a modern (male) reader, he seems to have tapped into a style of characterisation that had to wait another half a century before becoming mainstream.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  5/5.
	    Finished 15 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4842502809?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-secret-history-of-wonder-woman/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 12:44:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Bad Blood: Secrets and Lies in a Silicon Valley Startup</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/bad-blood-secrets-and-lies-in-a-silicon-valley-startup/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Bad Blood: Secrets and Lies in a Silicon Valley Startup&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1523311515l/37976541._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;John Carreyrou&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2018
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A history of the Theranos blood-testing scandal.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Theranos was once the hottest Silicon Valley property. There seem to have been several reasons for this, one of which was &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; its technology, which was largely undemonstrated and unproven – and which turned out to be entirely fictitious (or "vapourware", in software terms). But it had a charismatic CEO who self-consciously fashioned herself on Steve Jobs, and an origin story phrased in terms of "disrupting" an existing industry that was worth billions. That, it seems, was enough.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This is really a story of how a weird corporate culture managed to silence its critics within and without. Those within often &lt;i&gt;knew&lt;/i&gt; something was wrong, especially those with experience in other start-ups. Those without were either threatened or bought off. But it's shocking to what extent many senior people seemed quite content to represent, advise, and profit from a company while being contentedly ignorant of what its product actually &lt;i&gt;was&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The executives in charge have faced the courts, and their defence seemed largely to be that "fake it 'till you make it" was a valid new-economy strategy. I have some sympathy with the idea, and they certainly weren't the first group to try it. Where they &lt;i&gt;were&lt;/i&gt; perhaps more innovative was in trying this with a healthcare device, probably the most regulated business niche and not a place to attempt a fraud. Perhaps their enthusiasm ran away with them, but there's plenty in this book that illuminates shady practices and ruthlessness that don't make them look at all sypathetic.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 15 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4828997645?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/bad-blood-secrets-and-lies-in-a-silicon-valley-startup/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 11:12:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Noise: a Human History of Sound and Listening</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/noise-a-human-history-of-sound-and-listening/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Noise: a Human History of Sound and Listening&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1357528091l/17213951._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;David Hendy&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2013
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A social and scientific history of human sound: not just undesired noise, but how sound binds societies together and how we decide what constitutes "noise" in the first place.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There are some fascinating vignettes. My favourite is the relationship between cave paintings and the soundscapes of the caves in which they're painted: many of the works occur in locations that are "significant" in the sounds that can be heard, or in the ways that sounds made there reverberate into the wider cave. There's also a discussion of colonial attitudes to the languages and music of indigenous peoples, and how the contempt for these (as "hellish din") contributed to the colonists' disdain for them.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As someone who loves silence, there are also some explorations that were awkward and discomforting for me, as to how the ability to find silence is a manifestation of "othering" others in society, and regarding their sounds as encroaching and unwanted. There's also a sense that the pursuits one enjoys in silence – like reading – often come about because the noise of their construction has been offloaded elsewhere, to impact on other people.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As to "noise", it seems to boil down to whether the sounds being heard are perceived as being made by "us" or "them", and to what extent we can exercise some control over them. That makes sound a part of the wider behaviour of a society: if we are all "us", then we will tackle excess sound differently than if those sounds are being made by a "them". In that sense, noise complaints are a measure of social cohesiveness and our willingness to rub along well with others.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 15 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4988401719?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/noise-a-human-history-of-sound-and-listening/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 10:00:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Pure Invention: How Japan Made the Modern World</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/pure-invention-how-japan-made-the-modern-world/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Pure Invention: How Japan Made the Modern World&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1625692031l/58511749._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Matt Alt&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2020
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A fascinating take on the effects that Japanese has had (and continues to have) on the rest of the world. This is very much a cultural history grounded in technology, and in the ways that technology drives new cultural possibilities. It's also often a study in the illogic of cultural trends, and how impossible it is to pick cultural winners.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The history of the karaoke machine justifies the book on its own. The vignettes are fascinating, perhaps most of all for me the way in which the actual machines were invented several times in response to different driving forces. But the most outstanding observation was how one of the inventors realised that perfect reproduction of songs wasn't the goal, and spent years re-recording tracks to make them easier for karaoke-singers to perform well. This is the sort of techno-cultural feedback that's fascinating.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Alt tries to draw the threads together, noting that in many ways what Europe and America are suffering in the aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis was presaged by Japan's "Lost decades", making the Japanese experience perhaps more characteristic of late-stage capitalism than we realised. It's an interesting point: I'm not sure Europe will ever have &lt;i&gt;otaku&lt;/i&gt; in quite the same way that Japan has, but that's again a techno-cultural interaction in progress as we see whether social trends follow the technological or &lt;i&gt;vice versa&lt;/i&gt;.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  5/5.
	    Finished 01 May 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4583487740?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/pure-invention-how-japan-made-the-modern-world/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 10:00:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Testosterone: The Story of the Hormone that Dominates and Divides Us</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/testosterone-the-story-of-the-hormone-that-dominates-and-divides-us/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Testosterone: The Story of the Hormone that Dominates and Divides Us&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1628608608l/58743798._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Carole Hooven&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2021
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	Testosterone is perhaps the only hormone with a personality, one that's often blamed when violent things happen. It's interesting to see a "biography" of it that's so grounded in the biochemistry and the limits of what's experimentally verifiable. The fact that testosterone is entwined into so many fates of growth and development makes it a hard subject for study.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;One aspect that jumped out at me was the extent to which evolution creates mechanisms that are the opposite of engineered, for example having the same hormone control several systems that are to some extent in competition, or create systems that run-away without being inhibited (rather than stay quiescent without being stimulated). &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Grounding to firmly in the biochemistry is also a weakness too, though: it's a little too reductionist, a little too fast to dismiss psychology and how testosterone might affect feeling, and therefore affect behaviour indirectly beyond the strict biochemical pathways. I can accept that psychology is a hard regime in which to do fully-grounded experiments: but that's true for &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; complex systems, and so its perhaps better to go looking for the general shapes of behaviour rather than focus so much on the details – and dismiss out of hand areas where these studies can't be performed.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  3/5.
	    Finished 01 May 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4578601136?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/testosterone-the-story-of-the-hormone-that-dominates-and-divides-us/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 09:52:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fall: The Mystery of Robert Maxwell</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/fall-the-mystery-of-robert-maxwell/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Fall: The Mystery of Robert Maxwell&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1577249624l/52240874._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;John  Preston&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2021
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	As biographies of monsters go, this is one of the best. It sets out the whole sweep of Robert Maxwell's complex and in the end perplexing personality: someone who courageously fought the Nazis, but committed (and admitted to) war crimes, who made and lost fortunes but never escaped the need to aggrandise. He transformed academic publishing – something I, as an academic, was unaware of – but engaged in outlandish stunts and competitions in tabloid journalism. His death was as dramatic and inexplicable as many of the events of his life.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It would be an easy story to sensationalise, and while there's some of that in this book, overall it reads as a balances account by someone without too much of a stake in the outcome. It's perhaps inevitable that the story has been overshadowed by the later tribulations of Ghislaine, Robert Maxwell's daughter, but these events are in many ways foreshadowed by her earlier history. They're certainly all of a piece with the story told here.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 10 February 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4513402533?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/fall-the-mystery-of-robert-maxwell/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Covent Garden Ladies</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-covent-garden-ladies/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;The Covent Garden Ladies&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1597761814l/54869220._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Hallie Rubenhold&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2005
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	An entertaining dive into a part of 18th-century society that's too often only considered voyeuristically. The survival of "Harris' List" provides a starting point, but it's the detailed archival study and the willingness to dig into the histories of the three main protagonists that really sets this book apart. In doing so it also gets to uncover some of the grimier realities of living on (or close to) the streets in a period when money was all that really counted in terms of life chances.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Rubenhold is very sympathetic to the Covent Garden ladies. "Prostitutes" (or "harlots" in the TV adaptation) is a too-harsh judgement: many adopted sex work only because society gave them no other options, or adopted it only periodically when forced to by poverty, or as a semi-acceptable companion to stage-work. She is also unforgiving of the male customers, who avoided most social sanctions or consequences.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The fact that "Harris' List" ran for nearly four decades (and that we have examples of most of them) also makes it a revealing social document as the mores and morals of society change across the 18th century. The descriptions become less straightforward, more ornate and (one would imagine) less useful as time goes by and the publishers become more susceptible to legal action for obscenity (even as the underlying social conditions remain largely unaddressed).
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 22 January 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4399838387?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-covent-garden-ladies/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>