<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about bonanza)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/bonanza.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2024 18:08:57 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Diary of an MP's Wife: Inside and Outside Power</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/diary-of-an-mps-wife-inside-and-outside-power/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1599934352l/55310315._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Sasha Swire
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      An insight into the British politics of the 2010s. And not a pretty sight.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The pitch for this book is that, as a political wife, the author had a unique ringside seat from which to observe the goings-on the (mostly male) politicians. And it's true that she has plenty of insight into them and into her own position in the circle.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But she also exposes herself as almost a caricature of a Tory. She accepts the misogyny and crudeness of the male MPs as just how it is, and utterly lacks any understanding of why anyone would disagree with her own positions. She can't accept, for example, that Remainers were sincere and their misgivings might be valid, or that the EU is anything other that fascinated with the idea of humiliating Britain. She constantly refers to the Labour party as "Marxists" and trots-out the usual tropes of how they would bankrupt the country, despite the fact that their "extreme left-wing" positions would be entirely mainstream in many European countries. She's clear-eyed and unenthusiastic about Boris Johnson as Prime Minister, but then fawns over him when he wins his election landslide and glides over the time-bomb he planted on the Irish border issue, even though this was evident at the time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The overwhelming theme, returned to again and again, is how self-interested the political class is, focused entirely on who's up, who's down, and how if affects their own careers. Lots of dinner parties, gentlemen's clubs, and holidays: one is left amazed by how shallow everyone is.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's not a bad book, and an enjoyably light read. But politically insightful it isn't, other than to highlight the trivial nature of politicians.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	3/5.
	  Finished Friday 23 February, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6052150109?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/diary-of-an-mps-wife-inside-and-outside-power/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Edible Economics: A Hungry Economist Explains the World</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/edible-economics-a-hungry-economist-explains-the-world/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1656314692l/61030740._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Ha-Joon Chang
	  (2022)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A book that combines food with economics? Not really.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'm torn by this book. I enjoyed the food parts, especially the author's anecdotes about his move to the UK from Korea, and how he's observed the UK's food scene change from incredibly insular and conservative to amazingly open and dynamic over the course of a couple of decades. It's a change I also lived through and remember well.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I also enjoyed the economics. Chang is an eclectic collector of economic theories – all the more surprising because he's an academic. He has an appropriate degree of scepticism for ideology and single explanation of complex questions, which is refreshing. He skewers some of the common myths, such as the "explanation" that poor countreis stay poor because their people don't work hard enough, ingoring the massive structural factors in play. He's equally scathing about the other "explanation" about the free-trade roots of the successes of the US and UK economies, given that they were actually massively protectionist during their main periods of growth. And he makes several policy suggestions for modern economies.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But.... as a book, I don't think it works at all. The conceit of explaining economics through food remains just that: a conceit that's not really threaded through the narrative in a meaningful way. The links are often just too tenuous. To give one example, a chapter that leads with anchovies ends up talking about natural-resource extraction economics using the example of bird guano – well, birds eat anchovies, so... Most of the chapters are basically diviided between food and economics with an often desperate attempt to tie them together. The economics is accessible, and a writer who can do that probably doesn't need a gimmick to structure his work.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	3/5.
	  Finished Saturday 20 January, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6013201080?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/edible-economics-a-hungry-economist-explains-the-world/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Estates: An Intimate History</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/estates-an-intimate-history/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1328840856l/912517._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Lynsey Hanley
	  (2007)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A social history of segregated housing in Britain, how thw dream of a more equal approach died, and the consequences for those who lived through it.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Mass social (or council) housing was intended, in the immediate aftermath of the Second World War, to act as a social glue by mixing all sorts of people together so as to break down the walls of class that blighted British society. It failed: Aneurin Bevin's vision was diluted, as were the building standards, resulting in housing that was both inferior to private stock and immediately identifiable as such, making it stigmatic to live there. The result has been to enhance the blight, erecting what Hanley refers to as "a wall in the head" of people whose self-image is poisoned by poor housing, poor neighbours, and poor (or indeed non-existent) services.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The wall in the head exists in many forms, and one doesn't have to have grown up on a council estate to have one. But however tall it is, the wall is easy to build when young and hard to climb when older, and it'll affect you all your life in some way or other. Housing and class have a lot to do with forming the wall.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's impossible to miss the connection with &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25489625.Between_the_World_and_Me" title="Between the World and Me by Ta-Nehisi Coates" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Between the World and Me&lt;/a&gt;, not least because of the catchy and often-repeated phrasing. &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/1214964.Ta_Nehisi_Coates" title="Ta-Nehisi Coates" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Ta-Nehisi Coates&lt;/a&gt; was more concerned with physical violence rather than social class, but the parallels are there: different people from different circumstances have completely different perceptions of the country in which they live and what it's supposed to do for them. I see this all the time with different student cohorts. It's to some extent a matter of expectations of others, but also of the ability to see opportunities beyond the present. An inward-looking social environment absolutely stunts people's vision of what's possible for them.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The book ends on quite q positive note: the willingness of housing providers to renovate (rather than simply dispose of) social housing stock, and the availability of cash to do so. Whether this is sufficient is an open question, and certainly we still see developers skirting-round the requirement to provide "affordable" housing, in some cases literally walling-off the social from the private units, just as happened with the first estates built in the 1940s.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Tuesday 19 December, 2023.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6013200590?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/estates-an-intimate-history/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Papyrus: The Invention of Books in the Ancient World</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/papyrus-the-invention-of-books-in-the-ancient-world/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1654622398l/60149545._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Irene Vallejo
	  (2019)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A history of books and reading.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This is a deep and cleverly-constructed history, running from the invention of papyrus scrolls to their replacement by parchment (and later paper) books. The transition away from papyrus brought with it a huge increase in comvenience – but also in the longevity of works, in that the physical stability and portability of books made it less likely that all copies of a work would disappear. Manuscripts needed to be physically copied to create another copy that might survive independently of the original; scrolls needed to be copied because they otherwise disintegrate.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Equally fascinating is the way books formed a central part of culture in the ancient world. I was particularly intrigued by the discussion of Roman libraries built in two rooms, one for the Latin and one for the Greek, and how the Romans saw and took up the challenges of Greek civilisation as a partial model (and counter-model) for their own. The centrality of literature to that endeavour is easy to overlook in more martial histories of Rome. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's also interesting to see the ways in which things now commonplace were once technological innovations – such as tables of contents, library catalogues, punctuation, and the like. These were shaped by the capabilities &lt;i&gt;and&lt;/i&gt; limitations of scrolls as a storage medium, and have persisted functionally unchanged down to the present day.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	5/5.
	  Finished Saturday 4 November, 2023.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5082627704?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/papyrus-the-invention-of-books-in-the-ancient-world/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Power of Geography: Ten Maps That Reveal the Future of Our World</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-power-of-geography-ten-maps-that-reveal-the-future-of-our-world/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1610902279l/56696339._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Tim  Marshall
	  (2021)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A successor to &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25135194.Prisoners_of_Geography_Ten_Maps_That_Tell_You_Everything_You_Need_to_Know_About_Global_Politics" title="Prisoners of Geography Ten Maps That Tell You Everything You Need to Know About Global Politics by Tim Marshall" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Prisoners of Geography: Ten Maps That Tell You Everything You Need to Know About Global Politics&lt;/a&gt; that attempts to do the same thing: to argue that geography constrains the pursuit of politics more than we might realise. It does this, although as a sequel it's far less impactful than the original, and seems to spend too much time on the historical progression of the chosen countries and not enough on the ways these histories actually manifest the geographical constraints under which they're constrained. Indeed, some of the countries' geographies (such as Saudi Arabia's) seem almost irrelevant compared to their geologies.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The inclusion of "space" as a country is interesting from a political perspective, and Marshall does manage to show that it has a "geography" of sorts – as &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/31528889.Robert_Heinlein" title="Robert Heinlein" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Robert Heinlein&lt;/a&gt; is quoted as saying, once you're in Earth orbit you're halfway to anywhere, since getting up the gravity well is the major transport cost. I'm assuming this will be the subject of a later book.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	2/5.
	  Finished Friday 20 October, 2023.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5788060830?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-power-of-geography-ten-maps-that-reveal-the-future-of-our-world/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Entangled Life: How Fungi Make Our Worlds, Change Our Minds &amp; Shape Our Futures</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/entangled-life-how-fungi-make-our-worlds-change-our-minds-shape-our-futures/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1575341220l/52668915._SX98_SY160_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Merlin Sheldrake
	  (2020)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      I often avoid books like these, as I worry that they'll focus on a single aspect of the environment and try too hard to make it all-consumingly special. This isn't a book like that. Perhaps because it's written by a scientist, it's balanced and carefully supported. It covers all the parts of fungi you'd expect, in all their strangeness: we talk of things being "animal, vegetable, or mineral" and ignore the fourth possibility (although we should perhaps also include bacteria, archæa, and viruses too).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The "wood wide web" of communications between trees mediated by fungi gets an excellent treatment, both its mechanics and in terms of how evolution might have brought it about by allowing co-operation to complement individual competition (shades of &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/22565080.Peter_Kropotkin" title="Peter Kropotkin" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Peter Kropotkin&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1310303.Mutual_Aid_A_Factor_of_Evolution" title="Mutual Aid A Factor of Evolution by Peter Kropotkin" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Mutual Aid: A Factor of Evolution&lt;/a&gt;). There's also extensive consideration of the psychotropic effects of fungi and the chemicals they produce, both on humans (which can be pleasant) and insects (which can be &lt;i&gt;far&lt;/i&gt; worse). And there is also the far-less-known ability of fungi to act as decontaminators to break down chemicals that are otherwise extremely difficult to deal with and lethal to most plants – and even more remarkably, that this ability seems to be amenable to being trained or at least steered in useful new directions.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I have to admire Sheldrake's creativity and perseverance in studying fungi. They're clearly a hard topic to research, not least because the fruiting bodies are only a visible clue to a far larger and more diffuse underground body that's a challenge to detect, let alone sense or explore.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	5/5.
	  Finished Thursday 31 August, 2023.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3927610031?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/entangled-life-how-fungi-make-our-worlds-change-our-minds-shape-our-futures/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Between Two Fires: Truth, Ambition, and Compromise in Putin's Russia</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/between-two-fires-truth-ambition-and-compromise-in-putins-russia/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1569298385l/50215644._SX98_SY160_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Joshua Yaffa
	  (2020)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A study of the compromises needed to live in a totalitarian society, and the difficulties this causes for anyone wanting to operate there.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The simple view of an oppressive regime is that everyone is ground down and cowed by the corrupted police and courts, But &lt;i&gt;some&lt;/i&gt; people always manage to succeed, and even more manage to soften the edges of the system by acts of kindness and rememberance. This book is about the latter group, and how they manage to keep some pieces of a gentler vision alive.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Yaffa knows Russia well, and understands the arbitrariness of it: it's never entirely clear what is permitted and what is forbidden, and even the written rules provide little guide. He observes that people manage to find the edges of what the authorities will permit, and stay within within them voluntarily – meaning that the actual application of oppression or terror become less necessary as time goes by and people self-censor.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Along the way he meets several people who are doing just that. Perhaps the most interesting are the lady providing health services in conflict zones, which she manages only with the co-operation of the State – who can therefore claim some credit and whitewash their own behaviour by pointing to her humanitarian activities. Or the founders of a museum to the Gulag, who are driven out of their leadership positions and replaced by someone who better understands the authorities' goal for the museum, subverting its message without actually closing it down.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's hard to know what to think about these actions. On the one hand, one might hope for a more forceful and uncomprimised rebellion against oppression; on the other, such a rebellion would need to be widespread to stand any chance of success, and the individual costs would be horrific. Perhaps the situation that Russians have arrived at is good for now, while they wait for the winds to change in a more liberal direction. They could have a long time to wait.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Saturday 29 July, 2023.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5650968900?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/between-two-fires-truth-ambition-and-compromise-in-putins-russia/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Rare Metals War: the dark side of clean energy and digital technologies</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-rare-metals-war-the-dark-side-of-clean-energy-and-digital-technologies/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1589950483l/50353960._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Guillaume Pitron
	  (2018)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      Is the "green" revolution actually a "ruse"? This book would have one believe so.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's certainly useful to have "the dark side of clean energy" explored in some depth. Many of the observations are chilling, from the environmental impacts of mining to their political consequences in those parts of the world where they occur – and the ever-present shadow of China seeking to get a lock on strategic minerals that will power a world increasingly dependent on rare-earth magnets and specialist semiconductors. In many ways these consequences are the "resource curse" of oil repeating itself, as countries with minerals to extract are exploited and bullied by the companies (and countries) wanting to extract them.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I have to say that the book isn't a convincing read, despite its wealth of anecdotes and quotes. Perhaps this is because the quotes tend to be unattributed, and the science quite shallow. Having said that, it's pacey and well-structured, and a warning that the move away from fossil fuels involves a lot of shady dealing.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	3/5.
	  Finished Saturday 24 June, 2023.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5350730258?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-rare-metals-war-the-dark-side-of-clean-energy-and-digital-technologies/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Butler to the World: How Britain Helps the World's Worst People Launder Money, Commit Crimes, and Get Away with Anything</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/butler-to-the-world-how-britain-helps-the-worlds-worst-people-launder-money-commit-crimes-and-get-away-with-anything/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1647803985l/58725007._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Oliver Bullough
	  (2022)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A searing indictment of how Britain operates as the world's largest tax haven.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;OK, maybe not directly. But despite frequently seeming to champion global tax reform and the fight against evasion, the UK sits at the centre of a network of facilitators, aided and abetted by laws and customs that make it an attractive site for dirty money.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;One can start with the "real" tax havens, many of which are British Dependent Territories. Could their behaviour be changed? – well, the clue is in the name. It could be changed tomorrow, giving them the choice of co-operating with international tax authorities or being cast adrift as newly-independent countries. Some might choose that route, but the fat remains that there's clearly &lt;i&gt;something&lt;/i&gt; attractive in dependency, including access to a legal system that's largely trusted.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;That same legal system is also a facilitator, though. All sorts of ancient laws pop up in unusual circumstances and allow smart accountants to create tax-evading shells, ranging from Scottish partnerships to "carried interest" arrangements originally designed for 16th-century sea captains and now used to shield hedge fund managers. Put enough complexity in place and the trails become impossible to follow.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The question obviously arises as to why this situation isn't cleaned up, since it's simply a matter of cleaning-up the law. This is where Bullough's tale is at its most shocking: the deliberate desire to keep the dirty money flowing through London both to provide revenue and to encourage the network of tax and legal professionals who attract other, hopefully more legitimate, business. Doiing so may make narrow financial sense, but it comes at the cost of protecting money looted by the criminal and the corrupt, and of makinf further looting more likely by making the perpetrators less likely to be caught. It's a dirty business that's being encouraged by Brexit and the need to maintain a global presence.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Friday 2 June, 2023.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5533469987?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/butler-to-the-world-how-britain-helps-the-worlds-worst-people-launder-money-commit-crimes-and-get-away-with-anything/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Matter of the Heart: A History of the Heart in Eleven Operations</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-matter-of-the-heart-a-history-of-the-heart-in-eleven-operations/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1505809245l/31817327._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Thomas   Morris
	  (2017)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A book that I very much enjoyed, but that simultaneously made me quite anxious: if I had a heart condition it would have been unreadable, I suspect.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The operations chosen are all milestones, ranging from the very first surgeries up to heart transplants, stents, and other modern semi-miracles. The most interesting thing to me was the degree to which a lot of the action was performed in very small communities of doctors, often with very varying degrees of commitment and risk appetite: the same surgeons often re-appear in later innovations.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The part that was most anxiety-inducing was that the translation from idea to successful implementation (or from science to engineering) was frequently log, drawn-out, and filled with dashed hopes and dead patients. I don't think it could be any other way given the complexities of the procedures being honed, but the names of the early subjects deserve to be at least as well-known as those of the surgeons, for their willingness to take a risk with their own lives in the interests of saving themselves, but also of eventually saving others eben if their own surgery failed.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Friday 28 April, 2023.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5350729762?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-matter-of-the-heart-a-history-of-the-heart-in-eleven-operations/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>