<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about bonanza)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/bonanza.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:simon.dobson@computer.org"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2021 12:40:40 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Fracture: Stories of How Great Lives Take Root in Trauma</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/fracture-stories-of-how-great-lives-take-root-in-trauma/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1628358479l/56852065._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Matthew Parris&lt;/h2&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		An enjoyable, if limited, read.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The author's hypothesis is that a lot of "great lives" – and he admits to not being able to define what this means clearly – are formed in childhood trauma. Some of the examples (especially Edward Lear and Rudyard Kipling) illustrate this perfectly. But to coverage of the lives chosen, one in detail and then others in a manner that is really rather perfunctory, left me feeling rather short-changed about the lives not fully explored.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But Parris seems to lose conviction in his approach for three of the later chapters, which deal with trauma in fiction. That's a statement about what we find meaningful or entertaining rather than being about biography, and these feel like "fillers" rather than properly contributing to the book.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Tue, 14 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 3/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/fracture-stories-of-how-great-lives-take-root-in-trauma/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Invasive Aliens: The Plants and Animals from Over There That Are Over Here</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/invasive-aliens-the-plants-and-animals-from-over-there-that-are-over-here/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1542091854l/41716135._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Dan Eatherley&lt;/h2&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		The story of plants and animals invading the UK, mainly (though not entirely) with human intervention. Full of anecdotes and strange twists as species interact.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's hard to say whether the overall impact of invasive species is positive or negative. It's remarkable that many species that invade other countries do &lt;i&gt;better&lt;/i&gt; there than they did at home, which is a positive for global biodiversity in a sense. I also hadn't realised how deliberate a lot of introductions were, and how two-way they went between Europe and the "New World".
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 3/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/invasive-aliens-the-plants-and-animals-from-over-there-that-are-over-here/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fordlandia: The Rise and Fall of Henry Ford's Forgotten Jungle City</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/fordlandia-the-rise-and-fall-of-henry-fords-forgotten-jungle-city/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1312052193l/6214108._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Greg Grandin&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2009
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		A story that's hard to categorise.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the early 20th century, Henry Ford needs rubber for his car tyres. He is persuaded to set up a plantation in the Amazon, where rubber originated, and thus to bypass the global market for rubber that's dominated by rubber grown in Malaya from purloined Amazon seeds.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But rather than simply do this, Ford also attempts some major social engineering. And not for the first time: other Ford facilities offer great wages, but at the cost of intensive domestic surveillance to ensure workers' compliance with Ford's social theories. As a result the master of capitalism falls foul of capitalism at work in providing services for his workers that he'd rather they didn't have access to.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The most amazing thing about this story, to my mind, is exactly how &lt;i&gt;little&lt;/i&gt; time Ford's men spent on the problems of actually growing rubber, compared to the time they spent on labour relations that could easily have been side-stepped. The people trusted with managing the task were loyalists without strong technical backgrounds, and it's hard to see them surviving in roles that were more central to the Ford enterprise.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Tue, 27 Jul 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 4/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/fordlandia-the-rise-and-fall-of-henry-fords-forgotten-jungle-city/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tyrant: Shakespeare on Politics</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/tyrant-shakespeare-on-politics/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1549316807l/41817492._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Stephen Greenblatt&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2018
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		An analysis of Shakespeare's treatment of tyranny in several plays: the Henry VI series, Richard III, Macbeth, King Lear, A Winter's Tale, and Coriolanus. All fascinating discussions as they stand, written by an individual who's clearly a deep Shakespeare scholar – but also cleverly addressing contemporary political themes and events. Make England Great Again!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As with much such scholarship, it often begs the question of how much Shakespeare &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt; meant what is imputed to him: to what extent is his writing a mirror onto which we can project any theme of interest? Perhaps that's not such an interesting question in this case, though, as the reflections cast by the plays – histories and tragedies, including a couple considerably less well-read or -performed in modern times – are really illuminating of the timelessness of events that sometimes feel like they're uniquely modern, rather than be reiterations at some level of eternal themes. The power of this is shown by the fact that this book was published well before some of the events that it parallels, such as the 6 January 2021 storming of the US Capitol. That I think makes clear the depth of the historical context.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Tue, 08 Jun 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 5/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/tyrant-shakespeare-on-politics/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 08 Jun 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Labours of Love: The Crisis of Care</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/labours-of-love-the-crisis-of-care/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1599726850l/55288837._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Madeleine Bunting&lt;/h2&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		Part policy exploration, part history, part memoir, and part anthropological study, this is a detailed and deeply worrying take on the state of modern British healthcare – the most loved and trusted part of the British State that has been under constant attack for decades. Why is that? – why would politicians seeking the approval of voters nevertheless fail to support and recognise the one thing that all voters admire? And do so with such fake affectations of care?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The notion of "care" itself, both as a noun and as a verb. comes under scrutiny. It's a word that's replaced a rich vocabulary of terms, bring aspects of medical and social services that were all previously regarded as separate under a single rubric. And perhaps that's the root of the problem. By destroying the subtlety in search of management and measurement, it becomes easier to neglect the essence of what's being provided and turn social care (and mental health care in particular) into "Cinderella services" adrift from public attention.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Sat, 05 Jun 2021 04:33:32 -0700.  
		Rating 3/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/labours-of-love-the-crisis-of-care/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 11:33:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>It Gets Me Home, This Curving Track: Objects &amp; Essays 2012-2018</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/it-gets-me-home-this-curving-track-objects-essays-2012-2018/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1550777290l/44083289._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Ian Penman&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2019
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		Reports from music criticism. While it presents itself as a book of essays, it's actually an anthology of the author's book reviews over the past decades. That's not a criticism, although until you realise what's happening it's confusing to see repeated mentions of a particular book.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The essays/reviews range over big names like Frank Sinatra, Elvis, Charlie Parker, and Steely Dan, and the lesser-known like John Fahey and entire scenes like the Mods. One name that's missing, but that strangely haunts the book by her absence, is Billie Holiday: I think it's all the jazz references, but you can feel that she &lt;i&gt;should&lt;/i&gt; be here in her own right – and then I read the introduction (having read the book), and read the author's explanation of why he didn't feel he could do her justice. Hopefully he'll write another book just for her.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 4/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/it-gets-me-home-this-curving-track-objects-essays-2012-2018/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Libertarian Walks Into a Bear: The Utopian Plot to Liberate an American Town (And Some Bears)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/a-libertarian-walks-into-a-bear-the-utopian-plot-to-liberate-an-american-town-and-some-bears/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1579655265l/50358538._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Matthew Hongoltz-Hetling&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2020
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		A group of libertarians decide that they need to form a free utopia, and move &lt;i&gt;en masse&lt;/i&gt; to a town in the forests of New Hampshire that just happens to be in the middle of a massive boom in the local bear population. Hilarity ensues.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Well, not hilarity exactly, although this book is laugh-out-loud funny in places. But there are serious points being made too. The libertarians take apart the town's community activities and services, to some extent by freeloading off the services in neighbouring towns that have only fractionally higher taxes but have larger populations because they're ... ermm ... better places to live. The collective resources are depleted to the point that the bear become more than a metaphor, a problem for which the town can't summon a collective response. And the final humiliation is that, when a national libertarian movement in the same vein starts, and also picks New Hampshire as their target for their new society, they don't find the original enclave welcoming enough and start their own communities elsewhere.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's hard to know exactly what the moral of the story is, if there is one. Certainly it makes a point about the benefits of community very well. But it's also somewhat trapped within a rather American rubric of democracy simply meaning having more votes than the other groups, where the majority can impose their will without too many safeguards,
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Thu, 25 Mar 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 5/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/a-libertarian-walks-into-a-bear-the-utopian-plot-to-liberate-an-american-town-and-some-bears/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>American Kingpin: The Epic Hunt for the Criminal Mastermind Behind the Silk Road</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/american-kingpin-the-epic-hunt-for-the-criminal-mastermind-behind-the-silk-road/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1578216397l/31920777._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Nick Bilton&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2017
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		The Silk Road occupies an interesting place in the history of the internet. To many it &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; the "dark web", the place where people can buy contraband with cryptocurrency. (Indeed, this is basically the only real-world use case for cryptocurrencies so far.)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's a strange tale of someone who didn't seek to create the world's dark marketplace, but once he had was sucked-in to a vortex of ever-expanding crusade to support "freedom", of that particularly libertarian kind in which no harms are admitted and no constraints regarded as valid. Ross Ulbricht also seems curiously divorced from the success of his creation, in the sense that he never spent any of the millions he made, and never seems to have much intention of doing. It's a fascinating to ask what would have happened to him if he'd walked away (as he told his girlfriend he had) in the relatively early years.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There are some questions left largely unanswered, though. Does having a safe, legal, marketplace for drugs reduce harms, by removing the criminals and violence? It's hard to say, as the Silk Road never really removed the criminals from the equation. Is a recommender system sufficient to regulate a marketplace for contraband? Is the middleman as guilty as the seller – or the buyer? Taking down the Silk Road didn't end the dark web, and indeed it's now a fragmented and dynamic place that's more difficult for both law enforcement and consumers to navigate. Another thing Ulbricht never seems to have foreseen.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Thu, 18 Feb 2021 00:00:00 -0800.  
		Rating 4/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/american-kingpin-the-epic-hunt-for-the-criminal-mastermind-behind-the-silk-road/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Dead Famous: An Unexpected History of Celebrity from Bronze Age to Silver Screen</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/dead-famous-an-unexpected-history-of-celebrity-from-bronze-age-to-silver-screen/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1597600765l/48868613._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Greg  Jenner&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2020
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		A romp through what it means to be famous. And indeed what "famous" means, which is actually a more nuanced question than it might first appear. Are "influencers" famous? – not according to Jenner, and it seems a slightly arbitrary distinction. When did fame begin? – one has to start somewhere, so the start of newspapers seems sensible but excludes some who might otherwise be in consideration. Nonetheless there are some excellent vignettes on what it means to achieve fame, and the consequences when one has done so, enough ( suspect to kill-off many people's latent desire for celebrity.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Fri, 29 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0800.  
		Rating 4/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/dead-famous-an-unexpected-history-of-celebrity-from-bronze-age-to-silver-screen/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jan 2021 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Shanghai Free Taxi: Journeys with the Hustlers and Rebels of the New China</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/the-shanghai-free-taxi-journeys-with-the-hustlers-and-rebels-of-the-new-china/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1580583448l/42283958._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Frank Langfitt&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2019
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		The taxi, while an essential part of the plot, doesn't perhaps feature quite as much as one might expect in this exploration of China and the Chinese as they start to drive the 21st century. It's a view from part way inside: not a Chinese view &lt;i&gt;per se&lt;/i&gt;, but from a Western journalist with deep knowledge and strong sympathies for China, who manages to get a variety of people from the city and countryside to comment reasonably candidly about their experiences. It strikes me as a balanced and important contribution to understanding the nature of the emerging "Chinese century" (as it may, but will not necessarily, become), both its strengths and weaknesses.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Thu, 17 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0800.  
		Rating 3/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/the-shanghai-free-taxi-journeys-with-the-hustlers-and-rebels-of-the-new-china/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2020 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>