<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about books)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/books.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:simon.dobson@computer.org"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 13:33:55 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Shanghai Free Taxi: Journeys with the Hustlers and Rebels of the New China</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/the-shanghai-free-taxi-journeys-with-the-hustlers-and-rebels-of-the-new-china/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1580583448l/42283958._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Frank Langfitt&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2019
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		The taxi, while an essential part of the plot, doesn't perhaps feature quite as much as one might expect in this exploration of China and the Chinese as they start to drive the 21st century. It's a view from part way inside: not a Chinese view &lt;i&gt;per se&lt;/i&gt;, but from a Western journalist with deep knowledge and strong sympathies for China, who manages to get a variety of people from the city and countryside to comment reasonably candidly about their experiences. It strikes me as a balanced and important contribution to understanding the nature of the emerging "Chinese century" (as it may, but will not necessarily, become), both its strengths and weaknesses.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Thu, 17 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0800.  
		Rating 3*/5*.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/the-shanghai-free-taxi-journeys-with-the-hustlers-and-rebels-of-the-new-china/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2020 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What the Dormouse Said: How the Sixties Counterculture Shaped the Personal Computer Industry</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/what-the-dormouse-said-how-the-sixties-counterculture-shaped-the-personal-computer-industry/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1442903066l/725789._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;John Markoff&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2005
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		Another history of the early days of computing. The goal is to link the rise of personal computing to the rise of the counterculture and (especially) to the psychedelics of the acid tests of the Merry Pranksters. There's some overlap in individuals, notably Stewart Brand (who makes a brief appearance in &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/7442.The_Electric_Kool_Aid_Acid_Test" title="The Electric Kool-Aid Acid Test by Tom Wolfe" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;The Electric Kool-Aid Acid Test&lt;/a&gt;). But overall it seems something of a stretch: the most influential players at the time (Doug Engelbart, Alan Kay) weren't especially counter-cultural. But the contrast between the corporate computing world and those of Engelbart and Kay – and for all their differences they share a lot of similarities – is profound, and it's sad that in many ways the corporate side won: modern software draws on the surface aspects of Kay's work on Smalltalk, for example, but at a deeper level is more heavily influenced by corporate needs, and that's become even more pronounced in the years since this book was written.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Wed, 09 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0800.  
		Rating 4*/5*.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/what-the-dormouse-said-how-the-sixties-counterculture-shaped-the-personal-computer-industry/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Mythos:  The Greek Myths Retold</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/mythos-the-greek-myths-retold/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1526867104l/38213085._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Stephen Fry&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2017
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		Billed as "Greek myths for the 21st century", which I think is an accurate description, both good and bad. This is clear, humorous, erudite take on the key stories without giving way to too much modernising, and with the thoughtful and witty asides one would expect from Stephen Fry.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The style does occasionally drift too far into the casual for my tastes, I have to say, but that's a minor criticism: I certainly intend to read the other books in this series, dealing with heroic myths and the Trojan War.&lt;br&gt;
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Wed, 02 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0800.  
		Rating 4*/5*.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/mythos-the-greek-myths-retold/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Seventh Sense: Power, Fortune, and Survival in the Age of Networks</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/the-seventh-sense-power-fortune-and-survival-in-the-age-of-networks/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1463563103l/26245038._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Joshua Cooper Ramo&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2016
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		It was all going so well. A book about how networks change the relationships between objects, processes, and people, to the extent that we have to regard a connected object as a fundamentally different beast to its unconnected counterpart. It's easy to see this for, for example, books, where an e-book has access to hyperlinks, can be networked with other readers, and so forth. It's also easy to see for connected houses or utilities, exposed to new security threats by virtue of being networked. And it's easy to see for companies, where network effects rapidly produce winner-takes-all situations simply because increased participation increases the benefits of further participation. The "seventh sense", although not really ever got to grips with, is the ability to perceive these effects and adapt strategy to them.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But then the argument falls apart. The solution to this networked issue: the US must create the best networks, attracting others to use them but not shrinking from pre-emptively attacking – both by cyber and physical means – any other country who disagrees with the premises established from the start (or changed over time) for use of those networks. Networks must have hard gates to keep out the undesirables. Disconnect from other networks to avoid being caught in a web to others' advantage. The owner makes the rules.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Does this sound like a familiar line of politics? – maybe it wouldn't have done in 2016, but now it's all too familiar. There's no real discussion about how networks emerge other than by the force of specific developments and goals, which clearly isn't the case for natural systems and isn't really so for a lot of human-centred ones. So this isn't a book that works for me: it doesn't get to the heart of what networked systems could do for society. But a useful addition nonetheless.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 -0800.  
		Rating 2*/5*.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/the-seventh-sense-power-fortune-and-survival-in-the-age-of-networks/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Our Man In Havana</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/our-man-in-havana/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1582135707l/51479195._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Graham Greene&lt;/h2&gt;
				   1958
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		A study of the dangers and absurdities of intelligence work, in which by definition it's hard to tell if information was made up or is just really, &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt; hard to find.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The book starts off quite slowly and only really gathers pace when the Wormold's inventions start to come out – at which point things get very interesting indeed. It's interesting to compare the slow and rather plodding protagonist to the racier Bond – or even &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/887797.Ashenden" title="Ashenden by W. Somerset Maugham" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Ashenden&lt;/a&gt;, for that matter. Greene almost certainly captures reality more closely.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 3*/5*.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/our-man-in-havana/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Beauty and the Terror: An Alternative History of the Italian Renaissance</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/the-beauty-and-the-terror-an-alternative-history-of-the-italian-renaissance/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1572906473l/48706204._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Catherine Fletcher&lt;/h2&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		An excellent tour through the Renaissance that doesn't steer away from the bits that don;t fit the usual narrative. Whether I'd agree with the subtitle of "alternative" history I'm less certain: it certainly mentions the role of women and the prevalence of slavery more than other books, and also explores the relationship between Italians and Spaniards in the conquest of the New World in interesting ways, though.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Wed, 28 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 5*/5*.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/the-beauty-and-the-terror-an-alternative-history-of-the-italian-renaissance/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What Is Life?: Understand Biology In Five Steps</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/what-is-life-understand-biology-in-five-steps/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1595344916l/54625938._SY160_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Paul Nurse&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2020
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		A quick and clear introduction to all the main currents in modern biology, especially cell and molecular biology, explained with a fantastic clarity.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The five main chapters and the conclusion all address the core idea of approaching the question of "what is life?" from multiple perspectives. But there's also an additional chapter on how science and scientists need to engage with the wider world, with decision-makers and popular culture, that deserves more prominence than as what is, essentially, an essay sitting slightly uncomfortably with the thrust of the rest of the book.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Fri, 23 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 5*/5*.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/what-is-life-understand-biology-in-five-steps/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2020 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Upstream: Selected Essays</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/upstream-selected-essays/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1576250092l/44244826._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Mary Oliver&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2016
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Fri, 09 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 4*/5*.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/upstream-selected-essays/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2020 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Permanent Record</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/permanent-record/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1564666396l/46223297._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Edward Snowden&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2019
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		The story of a dissident. In Snowden's telling he dissented for entirely principled reasons having found evidence of illegal wiretapping and other activities on the part of his employer, the NSA. And it's certainly true that many subsequent events bear out his story, as Congress has shut down or otherwise controlled the activities he revealed – but without pardoning or exonerating the whistleblower. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's a story that could only happen in America, though, and some americana show through (for Valentine's Day he buys his girlfriend "the revolver she's always wanted"). But it's really a story of conscience followed to its logical conclusion, regardless of the personal consequences. And even having finished the book it's hard to really know what drove Snowden's actions: sacrificing everything to a principle of liberty that he felt wasn't being upheld seems somehow inadequate.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's a broader message here too, to do with how the privatisation of government has affected the behaviour and loyalty of the people involved. A system where you can leave government services, become a contractor, and earn ten times the money for the same job in the same facility alongside the same people – simply to reduce the headline staff cost (by replacing it with an enormously larger contracting cost). It's a recipe for self-serving, and also for moving government-developed technology and approaches into the private sector for private profit.&lt;br&gt;
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 4*/5*.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/permanent-record/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>In Extremis: The Life of War Correspondent Marie Colvin</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/in-extremis-the-life-of-war-correspondent-marie-colvin/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1538076290l/39731655._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Lindsey Hilsum&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2018
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		Hard to think of a better way to tackle the life of such a complex individual in such complex circumstances. This is an excellent read both for its subject matter and for the general experience of war reporting.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I don't think we ever really get to the bottom of Marie Colvin's complexity. though. Perhaps that's inevitable at such a short distance from the events. Lindsey Hilsum avoids the facile explanations (daddy issues, thrill-seeking), but is left with very little else. She (Hilsum) seems to think that the same basic issues drove both Colvin's reporting and her self-destructive personal life that repeated a pattern of unsuitable men: she even shows how Colvin herself knew this was happening and yet seemed unable to escape the pattern. But as to what drove Colvin to the extremes she went to, reporting on stories that even other war reporters thought were too risky, remains in the shade for now at least.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Mon, 21 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 4*/5*.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/in-extremis-the-life-of-war-correspondent-marie-colvin/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2020 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>