<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about books)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/books.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:simon.dobson@computer.org"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2021 14:15:57 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Sea Room: An Island Life in the Hebrides</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/sea-room-an-island-life-in-the-hebrides/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1428638946l/23637522._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Adam Nicolson&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2001
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		An elegy to a Hebridean island through time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The author is the grandson of Vita Sackville-West and Harold Nicolson, and son of the man who last purchased the Shiant Islands (pronounced &lt;i&gt;shant&lt;/i&gt;) that sit in The Minch off Lewis. The book is an homage to them. Not, as might be expected, a tale of living on the islands, which Nicolson never does for any extended period of time. Instead it tells the story of finding out about when they &lt;i&gt;were&lt;/i&gt; inhabited, and how that habitation came to an end around the turn of the nineteenth century as the cash and market economy took over from the more self-sufficient one that had previously been in place. It's hard to say this was an improvement for the islanders, but equally hard to say that many would now seek out the kind of life they lost. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The main resonance here is with &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13369533.The_Old_Ways_A_Journey_on_Foot" title="The Old Ways A Journey on Foot by Robert Macfarlane" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;The Old Ways: A Journey on Foot&lt;/a&gt;, in which Robert Macfarlane covers a lot of similar ground (and water). It makes no attempt to "sell" island life for what it isn't, and is dismissive of attempts at "structured" conservation in place of enlightened private ownership. It's hard to accept this argument, or at least hard to feel safe assuming that all future generations will be enlightened in the same way – although that's perhaps true of government quangos as well.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Fri, 09 Jul 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 4/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/sea-room-an-island-life-in-the-hebrides/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Deadliest Enemy: Our War Against Killer Germs</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/deadliest-enemy-our-war-against-killer-germs/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1488177489l/30841977._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Michael T. Osterholm&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2017
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		Sub-titled as being by the man who predicted the pandemic. He didn't, of course, he predicted &lt;i&gt;a&lt;/i&gt; pandemic – which he expected to be of influenza, not coronavirus, which was relegated to a "regional" risk.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;That's not a criticism of this book, however, which is a powerful exploration of the world's state of preparedness for pandemics and – more importantly – some very detailed policy prescriptions to improve that level that are now even more relevant given what we know about pandemic spread in the modern world.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The style is a mixture between personal anecdotes and broader perspectives: very characteristic of Mark Olshaker, whose style I think I could have recognised (from &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/126584.Mindhunter_Inside_the_FBI_s_Elite_Serial_Crime_Unit" title="Mindhunter Inside the FBI's Elite Serial Crime Unit by John E. Douglas" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Mindhunter: Inside the FBI's Elite Serial Crime Unit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/94340.The_Cases_That_Haunt_Us" title="The Cases That Haunt Us by John E. Douglas" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;The Cases That Haunt Us&lt;/a&gt;, which is co-write with John Douglas) even had I not seen his name on the cover. It gives an immediacy to the content that otherwise risks becoming lost in a maze of science and politics.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 4/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/deadliest-enemy-our-war-against-killer-germs/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Stalin's War</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/stalins-war/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1616693505l/54546065._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Sean McMeekin&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2021
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		Even those who are familiar with Second World War History, and with Stalin, will find a huge amount in this book. It's a complete take-down of the usual western-centric perspective of both the war and its background diplomacy.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's hard to comprehend the degree of duplicity displayed by Stalin, other than as an utterly ruthless and unswerving devotion to both the short- and long-term benefits of any agreement to the USSR. No lie is too brazen, and no-one remains un-betrayed. It renders the war in the West unavoidably morally compromised, as Britain and France fight Germany over its treatment of its neighbours while &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; fighting the USSR which has invaded just as many of &lt;i&gt;its&lt;/i&gt; neighbours. Having said that, it's clearly rather fantastical of McMeekin to suggest that this could have been rectified by the Allies fighting the Russians too in defence of free peoples: no matter that it would have been an unsaleable proposition at the time, it's hard to see how it would have enormously altered the broad strokes of what followed had the Nazis still knocked-out France. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The Western leaders come out very badly: Churchill, but especially Roosevelt. The former is too romantic and too old-world to cope with the diminished nature of Britain's place in the world; the latter is clearly entirely taken in by his belief in his own ability to charm and manage anyone, with this belief being fed by a collection of NKVD assets and Communist fell0w-travellers embedded in the US foreign services. Both are comprehensively outclassed. It's shocking to read of Roosevelt's treatment of Churchill in the wider context of the Lend-Lease programme, from which Russia receives a cascade of material for free while the British receive substantially less and are required to pay exorbitantly for it. It's also shocking in this context to read that the Red Army's supply base from Lend-Lease left it so overwhelmingly superior in men and machinery to the Wehrmacht – and yet still took almost unimaginable casualties in almost every encounter.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;McMeekin's overall view of the war is that the Russians won in terms of their final positioning in the world, and that both Lend-Lease and the looting of German and the other countries of Eastern Europe positioned them as a superpower ready for the Cold War. It's a hard diagnosis, but one that's also hard to counter.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Mon, 28 Jun 2021 05:57:51 -0700.  
		Rating 5/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/stalins-war/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2021 12:57:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Savage arena</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/savage-arena/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1482365193l/33350573.jpg" style="width: 100px; float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Joe Tasker&lt;/h2&gt;
				   1982
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
Still one of the greatest mountaineering books ever written, all the
more poignant for being posthumous. It's the book that first fired my
imagination for the mountains.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The climbs that Tasker tackles (with a variety of "great names" from
British muntaineering of the era) gradually grow in severity –
although starting with the north face of the Eiger is hardly a normal
progression! His honesty in describing his feelings is remarkable, not
least because they're generally feelings of technical and emotional
inadequacy. These are set amid quite epic descriptions of climbing
challenges and the (often grim) reality of being on expeditions in the
Himalayas.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Tasker often compares his own emotional state to that of his
companions, notably the notoriously self-contained Dick Renshaw and
equally notoriously voluble Doug Scott. It's hard to know from this
book what they would have thought of him: he gives the impression of
being rather inscrutable himself (an impression that Chris Bonnington
reinforces in his forward). It's perhaps a trait that served him well
on the walls when the going got especially tough, as it did
frequently. He finds himself repeatedly questioning his motivations
for climbing without reaching too much of a conclusion. He seems
simply to accept it: it's what he does, there doesn't have to be a
reason, and the dangers and isolation are simply part of the cost. It
never feels over-examined.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 4/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/savage-arena/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tyrant: Shakespeare on Politics</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/tyrant-shakespeare-on-politics/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1549316807l/41817492._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Stephen Greenblatt&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2018
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		An analysis of Shakespeare's treatment of tyranny in several plays: the Henry VI series, Richard III, Macbeth, King Lear, A Winter's Tale, and Coriolanus. All fascinating discussions as they stand, written by an individual who's clearly a deep Shakespeare scholar – but also cleverly addressing contemporary political themes and events. Make England Great Again!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As with much such scholarship, it often begs the question of how much Shakespeare &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt; meant what is imputed to him: to what extent is his writing a mirror onto which we can project any theme of interest? Perhaps that's not such an interesting question in this case, though, as the reflections cast by the plays – histories and tragedies, including a couple considerably less well-read or -performed in modern times – are really illuminating of the timelessness of events that sometimes feel like they're uniquely modern, rather than be reiterations at some level of eternal themes. The power of this is shown by the fact that this book was published well before some of the events that it parallels, such as the 6 January 2021 storming of the US Capitol. That I think makes clear the depth of the historical context.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Tue, 08 Jun 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 5/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/tyrant-shakespeare-on-politics/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 08 Jun 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Everest the Cruel Way</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/everest-the-cruel-way/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1481693672l/33377089._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Joe Tasker&lt;/h2&gt;
				   1981
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		A classic of mountaineering, although not to the same extent as &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/19294505.Savage_Arena" title="Savage Arena by Joe Tasker" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Savage Arena&lt;/a&gt;, Tasker's other (later) book.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This is the story of an ill-fated expedition to climb Everest by an unusual route, in winter. The challenge was too great and the team had to turn back, plagued by illness and atrocious weather. But that in no way diminishes their achievement, and they laid the ground work for later winter expeditions to the Himalayas having exposed exactly how cruel the wind in particular made climbing in that season.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Tasker is quite an acute observer of his partners, especially of their strengths as climbers and team-mates. He himself comes through less strongly, and this is a far less personally revealing account than is "Savage Arena". It's probably best read as an inspiring tale of what can be achieved even when short of ultimate success.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Mon, 07 Jun 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 4/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/everest-the-cruel-way/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Labours of Love: The Crisis of Care</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/labours-of-love-the-crisis-of-care/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1599726850l/55288837._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Madeleine Bunting&lt;/h2&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		Part policy exploration, part history, part memoir, and part anthropological study, this is a detailed and deeply worrying take on the state of modern British healthcare – the most loved and trusted part of the British State that has been under constant attack for decades. Why is that? – why would politicians seeking the approval of voters nevertheless fail to support and recognise the one thing that all voters admire? And do so with such fake affectations of care?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The notion of "care" itself, both as a noun and as a verb. comes under scrutiny. It's a word that's replaced a rich vocabulary of terms, bring aspects of medical and social services that were all previously regarded as separate under a single rubric. And perhaps that's the root of the problem. By destroying the subtlety in search of management and measurement, it becomes easier to neglect the essence of what's being provided and turn social care (and mental health care in particular) into "Cinderella services" adrift from public attention.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Sat, 05 Jun 2021 04:33:32 -0700.  
		Rating 3/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/labours-of-love-the-crisis-of-care/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 11:33:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Living Mountain</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/the-living-mountain/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1585798950l/25773742._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Nan Shepherd&lt;/h2&gt;
				   1977
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		&lt;i&gt;Here then may be a life of the senses so pure, so untouched by any&lt;br&gt;mode of apprehension but their own, that the body may be said to&lt;br&gt;think. Each sense heightened to its most exquisite awareness is in&lt;br&gt;itself total experience. This is the innocence we have lost, living in&lt;br&gt;one sense at a time to live all the way through. ... The many details&lt;br&gt;– a stroke here, a stroke there – come for a moment into perfect&lt;br&gt;focus, and one can read at last the word that has been from the&lt;br&gt;beginning.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Jeanette Winterson, in her afterword to this edition, describes the book as a "geo-poetic exploration of the Cairngorms". That's a good description, though incomplete: this is a meditation on mountains and mountain-centred living in all its forms, often quite breathtaking in its imagery and always rather meditative and spiritual in its perception of the wholeness of the environment.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The style of writing itself is fascinating, almost Victorian but without the heaviness. The grammar is flawless, which in itself is quite dated and dating, and every now and again there are some passages that jump off the page with their insight and lucidity. It's a book I want to take into the mountains to read in the situation of its conception.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Sat, 05 Jun 2021 04:26:48 -0700.  
		Rating 5/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/the-living-mountain/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 11:26:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>To Be a Machine: Adventures Among Cyborgs, Utopians, Hackers, and the Futurists Solving the Modest Problem of Death</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/to-be-a-machine-adventures-among-cyborgs-utopians-hackers-and-the-futurists-solving-the-modest-problem-of-death/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1521728537l/39346483._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Mark O'Connell&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2017
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		A review of transhumanist ideas by an avowed sceptic.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Transhumanism is a difficult belief system to tackle. At its more extreme end it rests on the idea of the "singularity", the point at which scientific and technological problem-solving become so advanced that any solvable problem is solvable quickly – which of course includes the "problems" of sickness, death, brain uploading, and a host of other radical ideas. (In recent years the singularity is assumed to involve super-intelligent AI, although that wasn't originally the conception, and such AI could be regarded as a consequence rather than a cause of the singularity.)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's an easy notion to ridicule, which this book sets out to do, and does well. But the long-term notion of accelerating progress isn't as fragile as it can be made to appear. The ideas deserve a better exploration than this book attempts. It's good for laughs and for making the participants sound like either idiots or charlatans – and maybe they are, but there's also some interesting and solid science going on that goes beyond these stereotypes, beyond those seeking publicity rather than knowledge.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Sat, 15 May 2021 00:00:00 -0700.  
		Rating 3/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/to-be-a-machine-adventures-among-cyborgs-utopians-hackers-and-the-futurists-solving-the-modest-problem-of-death/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Old Ways: A Journey on Foot</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/the-old-ways-a-journey-on-foot/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1328811154l/13369533._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Robert Macfarlane&lt;/h2&gt;
				   2012
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		A beautiful and poignant volume that's hard to categorise: part travelogue, part biography of the poet Edward Thomas, part meditation, part exploration. Macfarlane traces old footpaths, from the South Downs to the Hebrides to Palestine, reading the landscape and the marks that people have left on it. He follows the diversions as he encounters them, musing about the "pathways" in the sea that are clear and long-lived despite being written in the water, formed from the ways in which current and wind interact to lay down the "natural" route to travel before powered craft. He spends night under the stars, including a rather unnerving and supernatural encounter while sleeping (ill-advisedly, as he puts it) in a neolithic ring. And he brings out literary gems, such as the relationship between Thomas (whose work I've now been inspired to read) and Robert Frost's poem The road not taken. Altogether a delight to read.
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		   Finished on Tue, 04 May 2021 14:00:37 -0700.  
		Rating 5/5.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>goodreads</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/goodreads/the-old-ways-a-journey-on-foot/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 21:00:37 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>