<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about books)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/books.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 16:32:52 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The World According to Colour</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-world-according-to-colour/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1623144261l/56155215._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	James     Fox
	  (2022)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A book using colour as a way to access a range of other topics, without ever losing focus.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Some of the choices will probably be controversial, such as the emergence of "whiteness" as a racial classification, even though supported plentifully by evidence. There are plenty of other less challenging anecdotes, though. Why do we usually consider there that there are &lt;i&gt;seven&lt;/i&gt; colours? – at least in part because of Newton's religious and alchemical ideas that led him to want to tie colour to the notes on the musical scale&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I most enjoyed the chapter on purple, mainly because it focused on the significant technological change that synthetic aniline dyes brought into culture, changing the relative abundances of various colours and changing the ways in which they were perceived as signifiers of wealth and status.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Sunday 11 August, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6565806725?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-world-according-to-colour/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Build: An Unorthodox Guide to Making Things Worth Making</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/build-an-unorthodox-guide-to-making-things-worth-making/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1652120231l/59696349._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Tony Fadell
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      Twenty-five years ago, more or less, I ran a start-up company. I wish books like this had existed back then to help me understand what start-ups need to do.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Fadell has perhaps the best pedigree imaginable, including being involved both in massive successes (the iPod, the iPhone, the Nest thermostat) and crashing failures (General Magic), and the best thing about this book is his willingness to share them, warts and all. He's clearly come to a place in his life where he regards everything as a learning opportunity and a teaching opportunity, rather than needing to project a particular image of himself.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The business advice is fascinating, even for someone who doesn't intend to start a company: there's plenty to learn about organisation structures and politics. I suspect it'd be absolute gold for anyone thinking of making hardware devices for the modern software-dominated world, though. Fadell has a clear understanding of what's needed to make a physical product succeed, and his emphases on story-telling and understanding the customer's journey as a route to success are compelling. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's also a lot of insight into some of the major companies and personalities he's met along the way. He's positive about Apple, clear-eyed about Steve Jobs' strengths and weaknesses – and clearly quite shell-shocked by his exposure to Google as not what he was expecting them to be.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	5/5.
	  Finished Saturday 3 August, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6567722144?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/build-an-unorthodox-guide-to-making-things-worth-making/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>SS-GB</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/ss-gb/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1689536758l/63326204._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Len Deighton
	  (1979)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      An alternative history that has aged well. The premise is quite common: what if Nazi Germany had invaded Britain in the Spring of 1941, and succeeded? The plot revolves around rescuing the King and retrieving atomic secrets, both to be sent to America.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But it's the politics of a Nazi occupation that clearly most fascinated Deighton, because he build a labyrinth of plots and counter-plots between Army, SS, British Resistance, and American isolationism. These internecine struggles are actually quite familiar from the actual history of Nazi occupations, so it's quite fascinating to see them transplanted to a fictional Britain. It's so well done that it's a shame it isn't part of a series (of which Deighton wrote several).
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Saturday 3 August, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6432286432?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/ss-gb/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Notes on Complexity: A Scientific Theory of Connection, Consciousness, and Being</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/notes-on-complexity-a-scientific-theory-of-connection-consciousness-and-being/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1673876917l/62686859._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Neil Theise
	  (2023)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      I'd heard a lot about this book, and expected a lot from it. Theise isn't the first writer get lost in quantum weirdness, and he won't be the last.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The first half is a tour of complexity science, focusing on where the boundaries of complex systems lie: the "quenched disorder" threshold between static order and complete disorder, and the existence of emergent phase changes in systems constructed from lots of simple interactions. Lovelock's "daisyworld" is a great example of this, and Theise is very strong on assigning credit where it is due (Lynn Margulis' contributions are often overlooked). It's an approach that could be taken a lot further.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But then it all goes wrong, lost in the mazes of quantum theory and its superficial compatibilities with various kinds of mysticism. But there are lots of different mystic systems, and choosing to focus on three that have been selected for their similarities with a naive interpretation of quantum mechanics tells us precisely nothing about reality: there are plenty of others that are entirely incompatible (including most mainstream religions), which suggests it's at least possible for mysticism and science to coincide by chance. And it's a category error to then try to reason &lt;i&gt;back&lt;/i&gt; from the mystic to the scientific in an attemot to "explain" complexity.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This absolutely &lt;i&gt;isn't&lt;/i&gt; what it claims to be – a scientific theory of consciousness and connectedness – because it commits the fundamental error of being selective with the data. Just because we can't (yet) explain quantum entanglement and decoherence doesn't mean that panpsychism has anything to tell us about reality. This sort of "reconciliation" of science ("western") and mysticism ("eastern") isn't new, isn't informative, and (to my mind) does both a disservice.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	1/5.
	  Finished Wednesday 17 July, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5814381629?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/notes-on-complexity-a-scientific-theory-of-connection-consciousness-and-being/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A New Kind of Science</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/a-new-kind-of-science/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1386925097l/238558._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Stephen Wolfram
	  (1997)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      I have very mixed feelings about this book. On the one hand it's a triumph of computational experimental technique, taking an idea that was well-known (cellular automata) and subjecting it to rigorous exploration. This uncovers a lot of new science, not least showing that complex systems can arise from even the simplest set of rules, but also that this complexity falls into classes that show graded complexity depending purely on the fine structure of the initial conditions. That's a massively important discovery.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;On the other hand.... It's hard to describe this as a "new kind" of science. "New science," yes, but not indicative of a new paradigm or &lt;i&gt;way&lt;/i&gt; of doing science, other than by emphasising the structured use of simulation. Wolfram completely over-sells what he's achieved, making claims he can't substantiate to aggrandise his own contributions. And that's a shame, not least because it's so &lt;i&gt;unnecessary&lt;/i&gt;: Wolfram has made some important discoveries, both here and to several other branches of physics and computer science, as well as popularising computational methods and tools. It's tragic that he doesn't seem to be able to appreciate himself as being sufficient.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The book is also quite terribly written, being almost half-composed of footnotes, meaning a reader is constantly skipping forwards and back: difficult in print, and I suspect impossible in a digital edition unless it's been very carefully hyperlinked. And the footnotes are often important! – indeed, they often provide evidence to back-up a claim in the main text that's entirely unsupportable from what's been presented. So it can be seen as both excessively long and insufficiently detailed, which is quite an achievement.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	3/5.
	  Finished Sunday 7 July, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4934435584?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/a-new-kind-of-science/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Shikasta: Canopus Dans Argos: Archives</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/shikasta-canopus-dans-argos-archives/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1516764001l/38189412._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Doris Lessing
	  (1979)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      Why is modern civilisation so self-destructive and complicated? The answer from this alternative history is that a previously time of happiness and long lives was subverted by a change in the universal forces to induce the current malaise.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I did enjoy this book, but it does live up to its sub-title: &lt;i&gt;Personal, psychological, historical documents relating to visit by Johor (George Sherban) Emissary (Grade 9) 87th of the Period of the Last Days&lt;/i&gt;. It's told in a very disjointed form using purported reports and other documents, much of the time from the diary of a young girl who doesn't really know what's going on, and so can't really advance the plot very effectively. That makes it hard work, even though the writing and the overall premise are excellent.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	2/5.
	  Finished Sunday 7 July, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5723914316?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/shikasta-canopus-dans-argos-archives/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ultra-Processed People: The Science Behind Food That Isn't Food</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/ultra-processed-people-the-science-behind-food-that-isnt-food/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1679715862l/62586003._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Chris van Tulleken
	  (2023)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      Food &lt;i&gt;versus&lt;/i&gt; food-shaped industrial products.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Ultra-processed food (UPF) is pervasive in modern diets, and with it comes a litany of actual, conjectured, and supposed harms. UPF itself is a strange beast, taking food crops and turning them into pure components that can then be re-mixed to construct new products. This has some perverse consequences, such as flavours being removed from purified and "modified" oils and starches in order to make them more broadly usable – and then having &lt;i&gt;those same flavours&lt;/i&gt; re-introduced later in the process, again in "modified" form. That sounds insane – how can it be cheaper than using the original oil? – but in fact it makes perfet commercial sense for companies wanting fungible raw materials to produce unvarying, known-ahead-of-time tastes and textures. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The resulting products (I'm now reluctant to call them foods), being created in labs, can be re-worked in pursuit of particular commercial goals, for example by adding powdered soya when looking to create a "high-protein" snack. They can also be re-engineered to be far more pleasurable and addictive for consumers, for example by hacking the body's responses to food (which are themselves coming to be understood as far more subtle and complicated than we used to think).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;van Tulleken has a science background, and it shows in the writing: most of the claims are carefully framed and evidenced. His background also saves him from falling for the industry's faux-refutations about there not being definitive causal links to specific harms: randomised controlled trials &lt;i&gt;aren't&lt;/i&gt; the "scientific gold standard" in situations where they're impossible to conduct in the real world, and epidemiological evidence coupled with some knowledge of the possible harm pathways can provide sufficient evidence. Having said that, he does sometimes deviate from this careful path, and there are a few instances of words like "may" and "could" doing a lot of heavy lifting.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;One of the most powerful elements of the book is that it simultaneously doesn't preach or prescribe, but does offer suggestions for ways forward. UPF is very difficult to precisely define, and is therefore difficult to legislate for or avoid. Does a single stabiliser in a product render it UPF? – because if so literally &lt;i&gt;anything in a packet&lt;/i&gt; would be included. van Tulleken also takes aim at some of the wider social drivers of UPF, notably its cheapness and ease of preparation compared to "real" food, reinforcing poor diet as a consequence of poverty. He also suggests some interesting policy options, while also taking aim at a policy infrastructure that's heavily co-opted by the UPF industry. Regulators and the food industry are &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; partners and have goals that are mutually irreconcilable within the current framework of pre-eminent shareholder value.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	5/5.
	  Finished Thursday 4 July, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6565805510?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/ultra-processed-people-the-science-behind-food-that-isnt-food/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sandworm: A New Era of Cyberwar and the Hunt for the Kremlin's Most Dangerous Hackers</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/sandworm-a-new-era-of-cyberwar-and-the-hunt-for-the-kremlins-most-dangerous-hackers/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1567555830l/41436213._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Andy Greenberg
	  (2019)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A history of cybersecurity with an emphasis on attacks against critical infrastructure.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Rather than bomb a power plant or dam, why not have its own IT systems turn on it? That's the premise of a lot of modern cyberattacks, and they can be run with all the same sophistication as more conventional attacks against purely digital targets – but with the proviso that a lot of the targets don't think of themselves as IT organisations and haven't interalised the importance of their digital control systems. Since they don't emphasise security at board level, it gets neglected and becomes a weak spot that can be exploited from anywhere on the globe.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The remedies aren't always trivial. Many attacks detailed in this book are almost incredibly elongated, involving the compromise of several servers and softwate packages on the way to the target. Keeping industrial control systems up-to-date can be difficult (or impossible): physical infrastructure exists on far longer timescales than the digital systems than control it. (I've had personal experience of laboratory equipment with control software that can &lt;i&gt;only&lt;/i&gt; run on Windows 95, which isn't being upgraded. Keeping that secure needs dedicated changes in the network architecture, and has a lot of knock-on consequences for efficiency and data management.)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The value of such hacking for criminals is easy to understand, but it's also the ultimate technique of asymmetric warefare, letting an attacker deny responsibility and avoid counterattacks. Even the most powerful countries have an incentive to stop responses going kinetic, after all. But the asymmetry works both ways, with the US as one of the primary developers of sophisticated cyberweapons and so having an incentive not to push for international controls even while at the same time the US critical infrastructure is more vulnerable than others' to those weapons.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Greenberg is a long-time student of cyberwarfare, and writes with a lot of insight into both the politics and the technology. He highlights the impacts of many short-sighted decisions made in the interests of national security advantage, culminating in the Shadow Brokers' release of a cache of NSA tools that form the basis for a new generation of cyberweapons. This is a great book to pair with &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/49247043.This_Is_How_They_Tell_Me_the_World_Ends_The_Cyberweapons_Arms_Race" title="This Is How They Tell Me the World Ends The Cyberweapons Arms Race by Nicole Perlroth" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;This Is How They Tell Me the World Ends: The Cyberweapons Arms Race&lt;/a&gt; for a broad-ranging and highly technically literate exploration of the new arms frontier.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Friday 28 June, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6337793870?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/sandworm-a-new-era-of-cyberwar-and-the-hunt-for-the-kremlins-most-dangerous-hackers/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Mathematician's Apology</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/a-mathematicians-apology/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1348629338l/154060._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	G.H. Hardy
	  (1940)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A short dispatch from another world. It's hard to recognise the academia portrayed by Hardy, and I'm not sure that's a bad thing. One has to admire its purity, though: a principled neglect of everything outside a particular field of study, and the deeply interwoven social life that goes with it. It sounds at once attractive and claustrophobic, inspiring and shallow.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Hardy is a perfect narrator and exemplar, being so diffident about his own accomplishments as to characterise them as having worked with one excellent mathematician (Littlewood) and discovered another (Ramanujan). He was a lot more than that within the small world of number theory in which he worked, including being a foundational contributor to computational complexity theory (although not in the exact definition currently used).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Reading this book sometimes feels like an intellectual making a trip to the world of &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/58045504.Brideshead_Revisited_The_Sacred_and_Profane_Memories_of_Captain_Charles_Ryder" title="Brideshead Revisited The Sacred and Profane Memories of Captain Charles Ryder by Evelyn Waugh" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Brideshead Revisited&lt;/a&gt;, and that may be the right way to think of academia in the inter-war years: tied-up in upper-class privilege, class-consciousness, and repression.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	3/5.
	  Finished Friday 24 May, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2907726884?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/a-mathematicians-apology/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sideshow: Kissinger, Nixon &amp; the Destruction of Cambodia</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/sideshow-kissinger-nixon-the-destruction-of-cambodia/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1172210282l/150092._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	William Shawcross
	  (1979)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A shocking tale of aggression and duplicity, where a country whose only fault is to be too weak to resist incursions by another is attacked and undermined by a third country still claiming the moral high ground.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Alost every character comes out badly from this story – but especially Henry Kissinger, whose willingness to sacrifice foreign lives while protecting his own reputation and influence are quite breathtaking. It's troubling that Nixon's fall was for reasons &lt;i&gt;other&lt;/i&gt; than his orders to bomb Cambodia and his willingness to lie to Congress (whom he was constitution-bound to consult and inform). The fact that the Cambodian leadership of Lon Nol and Sihanouk were also corrupt and self-serving offers no excuse. The US Joint Chiefs stood behind him because it suited them to extend the Vietnam War rather than end it, even after the point that they knew it was un-winnable and were extracting their own ground forces. Together these people all opened the door for the Khmer Rouge and the killing fields that followed, and did so knowing the risks they were running.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Saturday 18 May, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6051760452?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/sideshow-kissinger-nixon-the-destruction-of-cambodia/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>