<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about book-reviews)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/cat_book-reviews.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 10:21:43 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Islands of Abandonment</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/islands-of-abandonment/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1645656810l/41830657._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Cal Flyn
	  (2021)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A book one perhaps shouldn't enjoy as much as I did, but as an exploration of what happens when humans leave a landscape – whether one they've polluted or simply one they've abandoned – it's actually quite reassuring even in the midst of it's being shocking.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There is alost nowhere that's so polluted that life of some kind can't regain a hold, given enough time. That (as Flyn herself is at pains to point out) is not an excuse or a invitation to more spoliation, or to not prosecuting polluters; but it is a reminder that we avoid pollution and climate change &lt;i&gt;for ourselves&lt;/i&gt;, not because the natural world will be irretrievably damaged if we don't: the climate emergency is about saving ourselves, not about saving the planet.&lt;br&gt;
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Saturday 1 April, 2023.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4954082332?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/islands-of-abandonment/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Dopesick: Dealers, Doctors, and the Drug Company that Addicted America</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/dopesick-dealers-doctors-and-the-drug-company-that-addicted-america/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1533010748l/37486540._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Beth Macy
	  (2018)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A personal but very balanced history of how the opioid epidemic erupted in Appalachia, drawing heavily on the authors' experiences in her home town of Roanoke, VA.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's a story that starts with drug company malfeasance, and I expected that to be the core of the story – but it's really only the start, as the impact of available prescription painkillers triggers an avalanche of users switching to heroin and then to fentanyl, with each change of drug generating fresh overdoses. There's a fascinating change in the dynamic between healthcare and law enforcement as the user population changes and the drugs invade more affluent areas, as well as being an indictment of America's very disjointed and vey much for-profit healthcare system. Many of the treatments that &lt;i&gt;are&lt;/i&gt; available are snarled in a culture-wars debate about the "rightness" different approaches, entirely divorced from the evidence. It's also interesting (and somewhat terrifying) to understand exactly &lt;i&gt;how many&lt;/i&gt; pathways there are to addiction, how many "gateway" drugs there can be, and how social pressures can prevent many people from seeking treatment even if it's readily available. Very sobering.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	5/5.
	  Finished Thursday 23 December, 2021.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4399837736?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/dopesick-dealers-doctors-and-the-drug-company-that-addicted-america/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Italian Life: A Modern Fable of Loyalty and Betrayal</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/italian-life-a-modern-fable-of-loyalty-and-betrayal/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1588350082l/51825064._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Tim Parks
	  (2020)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A tale of Italian life, and especially Italian academic life. I've seen this as an outsider, and recognise some of the terms and issues described: it'd be fascinating to hear an Italian academic's view too.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The story goes well beyond academia, though, to the things that make Italy both a wonderful and damaging culture: the impact of tight families and high expectations, especially for people moving from the south (Puglia and Basilicata) to the north (Milan, Bologna). Many of the themes have equivalents in other places, especially Ireland, but the differences in perception are often hard to decode as an outsider, and this book was often like listening-in on episodes that I've seen but not understood.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Thursday 2 December, 2021.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3886201506?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/italian-life-a-modern-fable-of-loyalty-and-betrayal/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Stoned: Jewelry, Obsession, and How Desire Shapes the World</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/stoned-jewelry-obsession-and-how-desire-shapes-the-world/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1435608799l/25817092._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Aja Raden
	  (2015)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      The desire for jewels exists everywhere, and this is an overview written by someone with a deep understanding of jewellery and its place in both fashion and politics. There are some great vignettes, especially about the rise of cultured pearls and the influence of De Beer's on the emergence of diamonds as fashion essentials. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Raden is less sure about history, though, and sometimes gets carried away with detail that doesn't in any way relate to the issues at hand. Many of the comments are alarmingly ahistorical: describing Mary Tudor as "mad" and "insane", for example, for actions that were perfectly sensible in the context of a religious war between Catholics and Protestants. And the notion that there being no market economy means that nothing can have value assigned to it, or that any attempt to better workers' conditions amounts simply to socialism, betrays her own background more than it illuminates either the history of the jewellery.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	3/5.
	  Finished Sunday 21 November, 2021.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4313355490?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/stoned-jewelry-obsession-and-how-desire-shapes-the-world/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>We Don't Know Ourselves</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/we-dont-know-ourselves/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1635721503l/43083428._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	O'TOOLE Fintan
	  (2022)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A personal but wide-ranging exploration of Ireland in the last sixty years, by someone who's reported on a lot of it. That makes for an insightful reading of political events in particular, the rise in national self-confidence and fall in religious influence across Irish society.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's probably largely incomprehensible to anyone who hasn't spent a &lt;i&gt;lot&lt;/i&gt; of time in Ireland, though: many things remain under-explained, as perhaps they have to given the sweep of the narrative. The deep-seated feelings of guilt that underpin many social relationships go unmentioned, for example. And the description of the boom-and-bust of the 2000s won;t be clear to anyone who doesn't already know the story.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But O'Toole does manage to dive deeply into something that many outsiders find perplexing: the "dual consciousness" in Irish life whereby something can be known about but not acted upon, or rather where daily life goes on without any reference to things that "everyone knows". (I lived in Ireland off and on for over twenty years, and this still baffles me.) How was Charles Haughey treated as a man of the people when he lived quite clearly beyond his means? Why did no-one investigate? – well, because there was nothing to expose, because "everyone knew", and so no demand to read about it. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But with those provisos, this is an excellent history of a period of tumultuous change for Ireland, during which it emerged into the modern world, peacefully and culturally intact.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Wednesday 10 November, 2021.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4317873486?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/we-dont-know-ourselves/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>We Don't Know Ourselves: A Personal History of Ireland Since 1958</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/we-dont-know-ourselves-a-personal-history-of-ireland-since-1958/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1635721503l/43083428._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Fintan O'Toole
	  (2022)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A personal but wide-ranging exploration of Ireland in the last sixty years, by someone who's reported on a lot of it. That makes for an insightful reading of political events in particular, the rise in national self-confidence and fall in religious influence across Irish society.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's probably largely incomprehensible to anyone who hasn't spent a &lt;i&gt;lot&lt;/i&gt; of time in Ireland, though: many things remain under-explained, as perhaps they have to given the sweep of the narrative. The deep-seated feelings of guilt that underpin many social relationships go unmentioned, for example. And the description of the boom-and-bust of the 2000s won;t be clear to anyone who doesn't already know the story.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But O'Toole does manage to dive deeply into something that many outsiders find perplexing: the "dual consciousness" in Irish life whereby something can be known about but not acted upon, or rather where daily life goes on without any reference to things that "everyone knows". (I lived in Ireland off and on for over twenty years, and this still baffles me.) How was Charles Haughey treated as a man of the people when he lived quite clearly beyond his means? Why did no-one investigate? – well, because there was nothing to expose, because "everyone knew", and so no demand to read about it. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But with those provisos, this is an excellent history of a period of tumultuous change for Ireland, during which it emerged into the modern world, peacefully and culturally intact.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Wednesday 10 November, 2021.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4317873486?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/we-dont-know-ourselves-a-personal-history-of-ireland-since-1958/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Souls of Black Folk</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-souls-of-black-folk/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1309202855l/318742._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	W.E.B. Du Bois
	  (1903)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      This is a hard work to capture succinctly. A collection of re-worked essays that address the concerns of those working for civil rights in the early 20th century, looking at the failure of Reconstruction and unable to see the currents that would lead to the civil rights movement of the 1960s and its limited successes.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There are some things that place the writing in its particular time. There's an acceptance of race, of racial differences and distinct, widely shared racial characteristics that is jarring to the modern ear. There's also a casual anti-Semitism that's perhaps even more shocking when deployed in the cause of emancipation by such a deep thinker who mainly overflows (at least in the main part of the book) with inclusivity towards white Americans.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The essays range in tone from the high idealisation of education in "Of the training of Black men" to the howl of anguish in "Of the passing of the first-born". And then – in this edition, anyway – there's the sudden &lt;i&gt;volte face&lt;/i&gt; of Du Bois's later thought in "The souls of White folk", where he interprets the First World War as the start of an anti-colonial struggle that's redolent of much recent writing in the same vein.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's only having read Du Bois that I (as a non-American) really come to appreciate his influence and hear the echoes of his thought. Certainly he is being channelled directly in &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25489625.Between_the_World_and_Me" title="Between the World and Me by Ta-Nehisi Coates" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Between the World and Me&lt;/a&gt;, and his ideas and even his speech patterns come through clearly in the voices of the modern civil rights movement.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	5/5.
	  Finished Monday 1 November, 2021.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4266555350?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-souls-of-black-folk/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Travellers in the Third Reich: The Rise of Fascism Through the Eyes of Everyday People</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/travellers-in-the-third-reich-the-rise-of-fascism-through-the-eyes-of-everyday-people/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1523549955l/36570428._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Julia Boyd
	  (2017)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      Subtitled "The rise of Fascism through the eyes of everyday people" is perhaps disingenuous, unless by "everyday" one means ambassadors' wives, countesses, academics, and the Mitfords. Perhaps it's inevitable that it's such people who leave the raw material of diaries and reports from which to draw this view of Nazism's rise. It's fascinating nonetheless, notable again because of the casual anti-Semitism that blights so many utterances and otherwise insightful observations.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Tuesday 26 October, 2021.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2879946141?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/travellers-in-the-third-reich-the-rise-of-fascism-through-the-eyes-of-everyday-people/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>There Are Places in the World Where Rules Are Less Important Than Kindness</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/there-are-places-in-the-world-where-rules-are-less-important-than-kindness/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1592028653l/53993435._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Carlo Rovelli
	  (2018)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A collection of essays that showcases the author's quite breathtaking range of interests and erudition, beautifully written – perhaps especially the last essay on the outbreak of covid-19 in Italy. Although I think my favourite is the essay "Ideas don't fall from the sky," where an early-career Rovelli is given unexpected advice from a Nobel prize-winner, that hard work and an immersion in contemporary ideas and their origins is more important that raw talent in achieving success. Spotting contradictions or gaps in the corpus of work in an area often shows where there is new knowledge to be found, and this requires one to be an expert, not necessarily to have superior insights. It's a gratifyingly modest view of science.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Tuesday 19 October, 2021.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3639372115?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/there-are-places-in-the-world-where-rules-are-less-important-than-kindness/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Lost City of Z: A Tale of Deadly Obsession in the Amazon</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-lost-city-of-z-a-tale-of-deadly-obsession-in-the-amazon/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1320487318l/3398625._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	David Grann
	  (2009)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A retelling of a story that was once front-page news across the world: the disappearance of probably the last of the "gentleman explorers", Percy Harrison Fawcett, his son, and his friend in the Xingu river basin in 1925.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Grann mixes the history – both of Fawcett and of some of the Fawcett-hunters who've emerged over the decades – with his own archival research and explorations around the Xingu. He shows how Fawcett's obsession within finding the lost city of Z (as he called it) led him to falsify the information he gave to others about his intended route. He also traces the growth of the obsession, setting Fawcett's undoubted skills in the jungle with his demanding and unforgiving manner and his gradual eclipse by other, more professional, anthropologists and archaeologists, who decided his ideas about the Amazon being able to support a large civilisation were fatally flawed. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And yet the professionals may have been wrong in their criticisms. A new generation now argues that there &lt;i&gt;might&lt;/i&gt; have been exactly such a civilisation, building cities in wood and cultivating large tracts of jungle. Disease wiped them out leaving only subtle traces, such as the earthworks now being re-discovered.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The story trails-off a little at the end, which is perhaps inevitable given that there's been no proper resolution of the disappearance. It's still a great story, of a time not long past when there remained significant gaps on the map.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	5/5.
	  Finished Tuesday 5 October, 2021.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2403177430?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-lost-city-of-z-a-tale-of-deadly-obsession-in-the-amazon/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>