<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about book-reviews)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/cat_book-reviews.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 14:42:48 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Chessboard and the Web: Strategies of Connection in a Networked World</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-chessboard-and-the-web-strategies-of-connection-in-a-networked-world/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;The Chessboard and the Web: Strategies of Connection in a Networked World&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1488446839l/34446808._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Anne-Marie Slaughter&lt;/h2&gt;
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A book on grand strategy and its application to less-grand challenges in a world dominated by networks.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The central thesis of this book is that the world of hierarchies and direct state-to-state diplomacy – the chessboard – is giving way to a much more nuanced world in which state and non-state actors interact and co-operate in far ore complex ways – the web. The network effects change everything, from the nature of power and how it's used to the nature of leadership and how one can actually get things done.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's interesting to see the concepts of network science being applied to social and political science in a way that doesn't trivialise them. The applications range from analysis of interaction patterns to trying to engineer particular interactions such as improving information sharing.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's an obvious comparison to &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26245038.The_Seventh_Sense_Power__Fortune__and_Survival_in_the_Age_of_Networks" title="The Seventh Sense Power, Fortune, and Survival in the Age of Networks by Joshua Cooper Ramo" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;The Seventh Sense: Power, Fortune, and Survival in the Age of Networks&lt;/a&gt;, with which Slaughter contrasts her work, she being a "Wilsonian" humanist &lt;i&gt;versus&lt;/i&gt; Joshua Ramo's "Kissingerian" realist. Slaughter's view is that there is a need for more understanding of how small-scale interactions can happen – contrasting with Ramo's desire for aggressive "gatekeeping" of a US-led networked order. I can't help thinking that her view is more realistic and democratic.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 27 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4611651217?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-chessboard-and-the-web-strategies-of-connection-in-a-networked-world/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2022 18:51:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Atoms and Ashes: A Global History of Nuclear Disasters</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/atoms-and-ashes-a-global-history-of-nuclear-disasters/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Atoms and Ashes: A Global History of Nuclear Disasters&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1645247265l/59011975._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Serhii Plokhy&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2022
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A history of nuclear energy in six disasters: five civilian and one military.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Competition seems to lie at the heart of all the problems: a lack of willingness to share details of accidents and near-accidents, and an unwillingness to learn if this requires changes in procedure. Collaboration seems lacking even within organisations and with regulators, while governments treat these matters as merely part of larger strategic concerns (even when they threaten to overwhelm them). It's also clear that the commercial operation of nuclear power is impossible without state subsidy, and acquiring this opens-up possibilities from regulatory capture – weakening requirements to make them attainable within a fixed cost – to outright bribery.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The science and engineering also seem lacking. The Castle Bravo (and other) nuclear tests massively under-estimate the weapons' yields, and this seems to be more the case the larger the bomb (culminating in the apocalyptic &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tsar_Bomba" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Tsar Bomba&lt;/a&gt;, which isn't covered in this book as it somewhat miraculously &lt;i&gt;wasn't&lt;/i&gt; actually an accident). But all the systems described make use of technology little changed since the 1930s: imagine if we were still driving cars from that era!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I find Plokhy's conclusions nuanced but weak. He decides that nuclear and renewable energy sources are both risky approaches to tackling climate change, but with completely different risk profiles: the former perhaps being too slow to start up and with huge accident risks; the latter relying on technologies as yet untested at the necessary scale. But in coming to his conclusion backing renewables and the phasing-out of nuclear stations (with which I entirely agree) he devotes &lt;i&gt;exactly two sentences&lt;/i&gt; to the problem of nuclear waste and spent fuel, which should surely be one of the major deciding factors. It's a strange omission at the end of a book that revolves around radiation hazards.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  3/5.
	    Finished 21 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4939077454?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/atoms-and-ashes-a-global-history-of-nuclear-disasters/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2022 11:47:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>We Are Bellingcat: Global Crime, Online Sleuths, and the Bold Future of News</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/we-are-bellingcat-global-crime-online-sleuths-and-the-bold-future-of-news/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;We Are Bellingcat: Global Crime, Online Sleuths, and the Bold Future of News&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1596434293l/54680228._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Eliot Higgins&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2021
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	The history of a still-evolving open-source intelligence collective.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Intelligence collection and analysis used to be limited to governments and a handful of companies. Not any longer: the tools are available on the open internet. Eliot Higgins realises that he can use them to investigate news stories, including the shooting-down of MH-17 over Ukraine. It's this investigation, in which he and his volunteer analysts manage to argue convincingly that the culprits were Russian-backed separatists using Russian anti-aircraft missiles, that really demonstrates how much information can now be found and cross-corollated. The result is for formation of Bellingcat, an amorphous group of international investigators organised in a way that closely resembles that of an open-source software project, where all that matters is an individuals' ability and willingness to share findings, and to have them challenged and possibly refuted in the search for the best explanations.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The book was written before the Russian attack on Ukraine, and so will demand a follow-up given Bellingcat's deep involvement in tracking the conflict and digging-into the details of individual incidents.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  5/5.
	    Finished 16 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4688233164?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/we-are-bellingcat-global-crime-online-sleuths-and-the-bold-future-of-news/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 14:40:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Childhood's End</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/childhoods-end/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Childhood's End&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1320552628l/414999._SY160_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Arthur C. Clarke&lt;/h2&gt;
	    1953
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	An entirely unexpected take on alien invasion. The aliens come, take over – and then allow humanity to proceed as its wants, without revealing themselves or really taking much control at all. Why? What are they hiding? And how is it that, when they &lt;i&gt;do&lt;/i&gt; reveal themselves, they look so familiar?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The reasons are all thought out with the rigour and open-endedness you'd expect from Arthur C. Clarke. The very fact that he can build such a narrative is a testament to his abilities as a world-creator, with an ability to pose questions and then not answer them definitively without this spoiling the enjoyment of the story.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 16 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2902185066?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/childhoods-end/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 14:33:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Spike: The Virus vs. The People - the Inside Story</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/spike-the-virus-vs-the-people-the-inside-story/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Spike: The Virus vs. The People - the Inside Story&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1626896615l/57095247._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Jeremy Farrar&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2021
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	I wonder if this book was too early: were we sufficiently out of the coronavirus pandemic to assess it and our healthcare systems' abilities to deal with it? Perhaps. But this is a good look at the early days from the perspective of the Wellcome Trust, one of the world's biggest medical charities.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 16 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4145716114?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/spike-the-virus-vs-the-people-the-inside-story/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 14:29:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Empire of Pain: The Secret History of the Sackler Dynasty</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/empire-of-pain-the-secret-history-of-the-sackler-dynasty/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Empire of Pain: The Secret History of the Sackler Dynasty&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1611952534l/43868109._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Patrick Radden Keefe&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2021
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	If there was ever a story that demonstrated one rule for the rich and another for the poor, this is it.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The Sackler dynasty has had a huge social prominence, with its name adorning university medical research institutes and wings of art galleries. The wealth all came from selling oxycontin, one of the most potent painkillers available and a boon to many with chronic pain. Their innovation was to own the company that developed a slow-release mechanism to allow a morphine derivative to be delivered orally. All this is a great service to humanity.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But... In Keefe's telling, the way oxycontin was sold made no attempt to ensure that it wasn't being over-prescribed or abused, and indeed targeted doctor and pharmacists who were clearly off-loading more pills that their communities could possibly need. And it's hard to believe that the company didn't know this, given that they'd also been early investors in medical information collection and analysis that could spot such patterns. The rest of the story degenerates into legal wranglings designed to keep the Sackler name out of any court decisions and away from personal blame.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's a troubling history that taints what should have been a clear and welcome medical breakthrough by the search for enormous profits by any means.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  5/5.
	    Finished 16 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4828997259?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/empire-of-pain-the-secret-history-of-the-sackler-dynasty/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 14:26:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>I Am an Island</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/i-am-an-island/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;I Am an Island&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1572615381l/49569074._SX98_SY160_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Tamsin Calidas&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2020
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	Moving to an island is many people's dream (including mine). This is a cautionary tale of the challenges, both inflicted and self-inflicted.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Calidas and her then-husband took the hardest possible route, leaving London to start crofting with sheep and horses. That's a challenge at any time, but when utterly separated and with no friends or relative nearby it becomes almost impossible. The hostility from the locals varies in intensity from indifference to outright abuse, running into assumptions of who is "allowed" on the island and under what circumstances – a situation that becomes worse when her marriage breaks down and she nevertheless stays and attempts to make things work, something that no-one (including the local women) expects, understands, or supports.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Times change. The later parts of the book show her almost accepted and with a new influx of islanders who are less ... well, insular than the original inhabitants.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's hard to decide what to take from this book. For a start, it's unclear how much of the hostility was triggered by Calidas and her husband themselves, not understanding the local sensibilities (although of course it's also hard to know how they'd've learned them). A lot of the tension comes from their efforts at crofting: running a shop would have been easier and perhaps less threatening to others, who felt their life was being intruded-into. But it's also an indication that moving from anonymous city life to a tiny community means adapting to a way of life that normalises surveillance and comment, and makes it difficult to remain aloof.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  3/5.
	    Finished 16 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4856066215?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/i-am-an-island/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 14:16:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Social Distance Between Us: How Remote Politics Wrecked Britain</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-social-distance-between-us-how-remote-politics-wrecked-britain/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;The Social Distance Between Us: How Remote Politics Wrecked Britain&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1643293353l/60224356._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Darren McGarvey&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2022
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A troubling tale of disaffection between classes in Britain – it's resolute in its class-based analysis, despite how out of fashion that is, and after reading this book it's difficult to disagree. That makes it an uncomfortable read for any middle-class person, since it's the middle class who takes the brunt of Garvey's assignment of blame. By allowing the working class to be demonised, and by allowing the creation of a benefits and support environment at least as "hostile" as that facing immigrants, the stage has been set for a breach between people that allows everyone to be manipulated by those in power.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;All this came about (in Garvey's telling – and I have to agree to a large extent) because social mixing across class lines has collapsed, leaving groups in echo chambers that exclude views that might challenge their established beliefs. And indeed it's hard to think of counter-examples, beyond perhaps sporting and music events (and even they are now segregated by ticket price).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There are some very uncomfortable ideas in this book, and for that reason it should be recommended for everyone in Britain wanting a challenging explanation of how we find ourselve in our current predicament.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 16 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4791092837?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-social-distance-between-us-how-remote-politics-wrecked-britain/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 13:57:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Man from the Future: The Visionary Life of John von Neumann</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-man-from-the-future-the-visionary-life-of-john-von-neumann/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;The Man from the Future: The Visionary Life of John von Neumann&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1632417945l/56155133._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Ananyo Bhattacharya&lt;/h2&gt;
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	Not so much a biography of the man (although there's plenty of that), but of his work and the major activities going on in maths and computing to which he contributed.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's almost impossible to comprehend how influential Von Neumann was to mid-twentieth-century science. He seemed to be able to see where the next set of major problems were going to appear, and then lay the groundwork for them – only to have shifted on to some new problem by the time others caught up. He was "first" into game theory and cellular automata, and early (though definitely &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; first) into computing. He made enormous mathematical contributions to the Manhattan Project. He also seems to have been quite at home at Princeton's Institute for Advanced Study, which many others have described very negatively in terms of the new work accomplished there. Perhaps that was a feature of being an exile: he had to be self-contained and able to take his work anywhere with him.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 16 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4271186547?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-man-from-the-future-the-visionary-life-of-john-von-neumann/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 13:01:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Time on Rock: A Climber's Route into the Mountains</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/time-on-rock-a-climbers-route-into-the-mountains/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Time on Rock: A Climber's Route into the Mountains&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1639233652l/58978033._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Anna   Fleming&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2022
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A modern rock-climbing autobiography. The thing that struck me most (as an ex-climber) is how little the culture and terminology have changed in the nearly thirty years since I was active. The ethos and approach have remained very communal and collaborative, with less of the competitiveness one sees elsewhere.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There were &lt;i&gt;some&lt;/i&gt; changes, though, notably taking a climbing holiday on a Greek island, which is something I couldn't even have dreamed of, before the era of cheap flights and European holidays. It certainly made a change from the damp of gritstone and gabbro!
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  3/5.
	    Finished 16 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4475002260?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/time-on-rock-a-climbers-route-into-the-mountains/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 12:50:32 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>