<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about data science)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/data-science.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 14:42:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>PhD data science studentships available at Trinity College Dublin</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2015/09/18/phd-data-science/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are five PhD posts on offer to work with the ADAPT Centre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits: Payment of tax-free stipend for 4 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, payment of academic fees; fully for EU students and partially for non-EU students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General enquires concerning this post can be addressed to &lt;a class="moz-txt-link-abbreviated" href="mailto:aoife.brady@adaptcentre.ie"&gt;aoife.brady@adaptcentre.ie&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initial deadline is October 7th 2015, but with each position remaining open until filled. This and other positions listed under vacancies at: &lt;a class="moz-txt-link-freetext" href="http://adaptcentre.ie"&gt;http://adaptcentre.ie&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Research Topic&lt;/h4&gt;
Increasingly in data-driven enterprises, organisations are having to cope with a wide variety of information sources and standards, leading to a lack of interoperability and increasing data integration costs. Resulting labour-intensive data integration practices are brittle in the face of accelerating innovation in data-driven applications and growing demand for agile data analytics. At the same time organisations must react to increasing public and legislative focus on privacy and data protection. Empowering users to control the information that flows around them in a privacy-sensitive and personalised manner also offers many challenges.
&lt;p&gt;These 5 PhD positions will advance the state of the art in linked data, semantic web and personalisation technologies to explore new approaches to data integration that are self-managing (towards autonomic), and in addition explore new ways to deliver personalised multimodal information (towards a digital companion).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These posts are part of the new ADAPT Centre (&lt;a class="moz-txt-link-freetext" href="http://www.adaptcentre.ie"&gt;http://www.adaptcentre.ie&lt;/a&gt;). ADAPT has received €50 Million research funding from Industry and Science Foundation Ireland to support 120 researchers across 4 universities in Dublin. The ADAPT Centre’s mission is to produce world class research that delivers disruptive innovations for the digital media and intelligent content industry. These PhD positions will be supervised by a member of the following ADAPT Centre academics; Professor Vincent Wade, Professor Declan O’Sullivan, Professor Dave Lewis, Professor Owen Conlan and Dr Rob Brennan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ADAPT is Ireland’s global centre of excellence for digital content and media innovation. Led by TCD, it combines the expertise of researchers at four universities (Trinity College Dublin, Dublin City University, University College Dublin, and Dublin Institute of Technology) with that of its industry partners to produce ground-breaking digital content innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ADAPT brings together more than 120 researchers who collectively have won more than €100m in funding and have a strong track record of transferring world-leading research and innovations to more than 140 companies. With EURO 50M in new research funding from Science Foundation Ireland and industry, ADAPT is seeking talented individuals to join its growing research team. Our research and technologies will continue to help businesses in all sectors and drive back the frontiers of future Web engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Why join ADAPT @ TCD&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Work on hard, relevant problems in an interdisciplinary and exciting research environment. The ADAPT Centre combines expertise of researchers at Trinity College Dublin, Dublin City University, University College Dublin and Dublin Institute of Technology. It brings together more than 120 researchers who have collectively won more than €100M in competitive research funding and have an international track record of bridging research and innovations to more than 140 companies. With €50M in new research funding from SFI and industry, ADAPT research and technologies will help businesses in all sectors to manage, personalise and deliver digital content more effectively.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Work in a University where excellence of research is valued. Trinity College Dublin is Ireland’s premier University and is ranked in 71st position in the top 100 world universities by the QS World University Rankings 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Work in a centre focussed on advancing your career. Whether you want to take an academic, industrial, or entrepreneurial career path, ADAPT prides itself in the support and mentoring that enables all its Students and early-stage researchers to reach their full potential. This year alone its postdoc-to-PI programme has helped three postdocs transition to be Principal Investigators on their own H2020 projects, while four others have recently won funding with ADAPT support to realise the commercialisation of their research through spin outs and licensing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Requirements:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The successful candidate will have an excellent academic record (first class or II.1 primary degree) in Computer Science or a related discipline. Experience in Knowledge Engineering is a distinct advantage. The successful candidate will be highly motivated, with strong written and oral communication skills and a demonstrated proficiency in software development, with strong design and programming skills. They must be eager to work in and learn from multi-disciplinary and multi-organisation teams. They should have English language certification if English is not their first language, the requirement being: IELTS: 7.0+, TOEFL iBT: 100+, TOEFL pBT: 600+, CEF: C1+, or equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Application Procedure&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For further information and informal contact, please refer to the PhD topic details. Please apply via email to &lt;a class="moz-txt-link-abbreviated" href="mailto:vacancies@adaptcentre.ie"&gt;vacancies@adaptcentre.ie&lt;/a&gt;, referencing this advert, and including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A targeted cover letter (600-1000 words) expressing your suitability for a position&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A complete CV&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be an interview process; a successful candidate will then be invited to apply via the TCD graduate studies admission system.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>big data</category><category>Blog</category><category>data science</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2015/09/18/phd-data-science/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2015 10:54:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fully-funded PhD scholarship available</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2015/02/03/phd-cs-med/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have a fully-funded PhD scholarship available, tenable from September 2015, to work on data science in medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;University of St Andrews&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;School of Computer Science&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;School of Medicine&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funded PhD studentship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Schools of Computer Science and Medicine are looking to recruit a talented student to work on improving clinical trials of tuberculosis and other conditions using computational techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TB and related conditions are extremely costly in human and financial terms, and trials of new drugs and therapies are complicated by difficult environmental conditions and other factors. Improvements to the trials process will potentially translate directly into improved interventions, and so will help save lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We seek to apply data-driven techniques to the design, analysis, and management of such trials. These techniques might include complex networks, computational epidemiology, machine learning, Bayesian analysis, and other cutting-edge approaches to data analytics. The ideal candidate will have an interest in data science applied to medical and biological problems, and an enthusiasm for working as part of a challenging multi-disciplinary project within St Andrews' new &lt;a href="http://www.idir.st-andrews.ac.uk" target="_blank"&gt;Institute for Data-Intensive Research (IDIR)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The studentship will be held jointly between the two Schools, with supervisors from Computer Science (Prof Simon Dobson, &lt;a href="https://risweb.st-andrews.ac.uk/portal/en/persons/tom-kelsey%28289c44af-c861-4f85-a604-6be4e43855f1%29.html" target="_blank"&gt;Dr Tom Kelsey&lt;/a&gt;) and Medicine (&lt;a href="https://risweb.st-andrews.ac.uk/portal/da/persons/stephen-henry-gillespie%28ce4435fa-8cee-4e25-92fe-30f18dfec159%29.html" target="_blank"&gt;Prof Stephen Gillespie&lt;/a&gt;, Dr Ruth Bowness).  We offer a stimulating and supportive environment within a small and intimate university in a beautiful setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scholarship is fully funded to cover tuition fees and stipend for a registration period normally expected to be three-and-a-half years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Informal inquiries can be made in the first instance to &lt;a href="mailto:simon.dobson@st-andrews.ac.uk"&gt;Prof Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt;. Applications will be considered until mid-March.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>data science</category><category>medicine</category><category>phd</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2015/02/03/phd-cs-med/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2015 12:12:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Scholarships available to study data science in Lancaster</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2014/06/10/data-science-lancaster/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The University of Lancaster has a new MSc programme starting in Data Science, with lots of full scholarships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme is a one-year MSc that allows specialisation in computing, statistics, or environmental science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More details &lt;a href="http://www.lancaster.ac.uk/data-science/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>data science</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2014/06/10/data-science-lancaster/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2014 14:43:47 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>