<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about history)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/history.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 09:47:43 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Early LISP history 1956--1959</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2025/11/07/early-lisp-history-11956-19591/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbb236cc" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgbb236cc"&gt;Early LISP history (1956–1959)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgbb236cc"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Herbert Stoyan.  &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/800055.802047"&gt;Early Lisp History (1956–1959)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. In &lt;i&gt;LFP ’84:
Proceedings of the 1984 ACM Symposium on Lisp and Functional
Programming&lt;/i&gt;, pp.299–310. 1984.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A study of Lisp's evolution from first proposal to practical
implementation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It begins with McCarthy's proposal (co-authored with Marvin
Minsky, Nathaniel Rochester, and Claude Shannon, and dated 31
August 1955) for a summer research project at Dartmouth College to
"study the relationship of language to intelligence".
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In a later (handwritten!) note McCarthy homed-in on the core
challenges in this programme: the lack of a clear way to describe
&lt;i&gt;procedures&lt;/i&gt; to each other (what &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2024/01/27/structure-and-interpretation-of-computer-programs/"&gt;Abelson and Sussman&lt;/a&gt; later refer to
as &lt;i&gt;procedural epistemology&lt;/i&gt;), and the tight binding of programming
systems at that time to specific machines, and hence their need to
bow to engineering (rather than semantic) considerations. The
language that became Lisp sought primarily to overcome these two
challenges.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The journey proceeded by taking the list data structures developed
by Allen Newell and Herb Simon as part of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logic_Theorist"&gt;Logic Theorist&lt;/a&gt; and
embedding them into FORTRAN (for which there was already a working
compiler) – which also incidentally muddied the conceptual waters
by trying to express list and list-functional concepts in a
language built around numbers that barely allowed functions to be
defined by the user at all. Indeed, McCarthy and others had
long-running problems accepting that the list-processing functions
&lt;i&gt;were&lt;/i&gt; functions, given that their result does not depend solely on
their arguments when viewed at the lowest level. This shows how
pernicious a low-level implementation can be. The final resulting
language, the FORTRAN List Processing Language (FLPL), shared many
programming approaches function names with what became Lisp.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
McCarthy went on to champion the functional approach, including
the invention of conditional expressions (alongside or replacing
conditional statements) and the power of the different kinds of
function composition and higher-order functions. It's important to
remember that McCarthy's driving interest remained in AI, not
programming languages &lt;i&gt;per se&lt;/i&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Already in 1956 it was clear that one had to work with symbolic
expressions to reach the goal of artificial intelligence.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Which is a fascinating piece of history in itself, as a large
branch of modern AI concerning machine learning and large language
models has explicit rejects this view in favour of sub-symbolic
AI. Which approach is "correct" in whatever sense remains to be
seen.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But it remains McCarthy's contributions to programming languages
that stand out. As well as conditional expressions he can be
credited with garbage collection, meta-circular interpretation,
and clarifying the relationship between programming and proof:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We should mention here that McCarthy at the same time conceived the
idea of logic-oriented programming, that is, the idea of using logical
formulae to express goals that a program should try to establish and
of using the prover as programming language interpreter.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
(Although it's important to recognise that Newell and Simon's
work, on logic as an application rather than as a general
programming language, pre-dates McCarthy's.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>history</category><category>lisp</category><category>project:lisp-bibliography</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2025/11/07/early-lisp-history-11956-19591/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 09:44:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The history of Lisp</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2025/11/07/the-history-of-lisp/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org67a97ae" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org67a97ae"&gt;The history of Lisp&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org67a97ae"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Herbert Stoyan.  &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.softwarepreservation.org/projects/LISP/book/Stoyan-Geschichte.pdf"&gt;The History of Lisp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. 1980. Updated in the 1990s,
translated into English 2023.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Includes a history of the route from PLANNER to CONNIVER, in which
the former was criticised for being a theorem prover when a
programming language was needed – an argument between two schools
that's still going on today, as seen in the emergence of &lt;a href="https://lean-lang.org/"&gt;Lean&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>history</category><category>lisp</category><category>project:lisp-bibliography</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2025/11/07/the-history-of-lisp/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 08:49:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>History of Lisp</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2025/11/07/history-of-lisp/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd92a09b" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd92a09b"&gt;History of Lisp&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd92a09b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
John McCarthy.  &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/history/lisp/lisp.html"&gt;History of Lisp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. Artificial Intelligence
Laboratory, Stanford University. 1979.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
McCarthy's own take on the early history. It's quite brief, but is
very careful to give broad credit to the others who were involved
in the practical creation of the language.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's also got some great vignettes on &lt;i&gt;why&lt;/i&gt; certain features came
about - for example garbage collection coming from the need to
clean up intermediate structures when experimenting with symbolic
differentiation. McCarthy acknowledges taking the notation for
functions from Church, before admitting that he didn't understand
the rest of &lt;i&gt;Calculi of lambda conversion&lt;/i&gt; and so wasn't tempted to
add the more general aspects!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Perhaps the most fascinating part of the story is that it was
originally so divorced from actual computers. The team had defined
an &lt;code&gt;eval&lt;/code&gt; function for interpreting Lisp programs – in the process
making the decision to represent the programs as lists – before
realising that this could be made interactive to provide a running
interpreter.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What did McCarthy think of his creation? He was conscious that it
would have a lifetime:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
LISP will become obsolete when someone makes a more comprehensive
language that dominates LISP practically and also gives a clear
mathematical semantics to a more comprehensive set of features.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Haskell has a plausible claim to have accomplished the latter but
this doesn't seem to have led domination in practice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>history</category><category>lisp</category><category>project:lisp-bibliography</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2025/11/07/history-of-lisp/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 08:47:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Metacircular Semantics for Common Lisp Special Forms</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2024/08/02/metacircular-semantics-for-common-lisp-special-forms/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org298cb35" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org298cb35"&gt;Metacircular Semantics for Common Lisp Special Forms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org298cb35"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Henry G. Baker. &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/382126.382662"&gt;Metacircular Semantics for Common Lisp Special Forms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;.
ACM SIGPLAN Lisp Pointers &lt;b&gt;V&lt;/b&gt;, pp.11–20. 1992.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A response to the criticisms of McCarthy's semantics for Common
Lisp that it didn't specify the behaviours of special forms, and
of the standardisation process of adopting prose definitions that
are too "lawyerly" for engineering.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The approach is to define the special forms in terms of other
constructions, for example &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; in terms of nested lambda
abstractions to prevent execution of the unwanted branch. This is
both useful for understanding and a way of minimising the number
of under-defined special forms.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It suggests treating &lt;code&gt;catch&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;throw&lt;/code&gt; as basic, both because other
control-transfer forms can be expressed sing them and because it
emphasises the interactions that preclude Common Lisp having
continuations like Scheme's. However there's also an argument
pursued that some other structures (like &lt;code&gt;values&lt;/code&gt;) provide extra
information that can be useful for compilers looking to optimise.
It's a deep exploration of the underpinnings of the language from
both theoretical and practical perspectives.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>history</category><category>lisp</category><category>project:lisp-bibliography</category><category>semantics</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2024/08/02/metacircular-semantics-for-common-lisp-special-forms/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 10:29:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The roots of Lisp</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2024/07/23/the-roots-of-lisp/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org0029935" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0029935"&gt;The roots of Lisp&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0029935"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/rootsoflisp.html"&gt;http://www.paulgraham.com/rootsoflisp.html&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
(Only has an PostScript version, but a PDF is available
&lt;a href="https://languagelog.ldc.upenn.edu/myl/llog/jmc.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Re-visits McCarthy's discoveries (or inventions, depending on
your point of view), translating the &lt;a href="/2024/03/07/recursive-functions-of-symbolic-expressions-and-their-computation-by-machine-part-i/"&gt;earliest work&lt;/a&gt; into modern
Lisp notation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It's worth understanding what McCarthy discovered, not just as a
landmark in the history of computers, but as a model for what
programming is tending to become in our own time. It seems to me that
there have been two really clean, consistent models of programming so
far: the C model and the Lisp model. These two seem points of high
ground, with swampy lowlands between them. As computers have grown
more powerful, the new languages being developed have been moving
steadily toward the Lisp model. A popular recipe for new programming
languages in the past 20 years has been to take the C model of
computing and add to it, piecemeal, parts taken from the Lisp model,
like runtime typing and garbage collection.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Does a great job of making the central insights accessible,
including re-phrasing the meta-circular Lisp interpreter so as to
be executable in modern Common Lisp.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>history</category><category>lisp</category><category>project:lisp-bibliography</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2024/07/23/the-roots-of-lisp/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 08:00:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A micro-manual for Lisp: Not the whole truth</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2024/03/15/a-micro-manual-for-lisp-not-the-whole-truth/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org010c5f9" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org010c5f9"&gt;A micro-manual for Lisp: Not the whole truth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org010c5f9"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
John McCarthy.  &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/960118.808386"&gt;A Micro-Manual for Lisp: Not the Whole Truth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. ACM
SIGPLAN Notices &lt;b&gt;13&lt;/b&gt;, pp.215–216. 1978.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A "manual" in the sense of providing a complete implementation of
Lisp – in Lisp itself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Is that useful? A semantics expert would say "no", since such a
model has no real explanatory power: the recursion doesn't
bottom-out to define the concepts. However, a programming language
expert might disagree and observe that this is &lt;i&gt;meta-linguistic
abstraction&lt;/i&gt;, the use of one high-level language to capture the
definition of another. The "host" language provides a higher level
of abstraction than is usual when writing interpreters and
compilers, so it becomes easier to experiment with different forms
of "target" language as there's less low-level work to do. This
benefit exists even when host and target are the same: essentially
the target is bootstrapped and can then be adjusted while running
within an earlier version of itself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As far as I know this is the first example of meta-linguistic
abstraction in the computer science literature. The idea was
popularised by &lt;a href="/2024/01/27/structure-and-interpretation-of-computer-programs/"&gt;SICP&lt;/a&gt; (using Scheme), and forms the basis for a lot
of modern bootstrapped compilers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>history</category><category>lisp</category><category>project:lisp-bibliography</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2024/03/15/a-micro-manual-for-lisp-not-the-whole-truth/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 17:25:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>List processing</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2024/03/07/list-processing/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org38afa4d" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org38afa4d"&gt;List processing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org38afa4d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
J.M. Foster.  &lt;i&gt;List Processing&lt;/i&gt;. Macdonald and Co. 1967.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A slim volume discussing list processing with reference to Lisp
and to other list processing systems of the time (including some
libraries embedded into Fortran).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The most fascinating part of the book is its bibliography, which
references a lot of papers that have disappeared from the
collective memory of computer science, but whose implications
were profound.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>history</category><category>lisp</category><category>project:lisp-bibliography</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2024/03/07/list-processing/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 19:39:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Recursive functions of symbolic expressions and their computation by machine, Part I</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2024/03/07/recursive-functions-of-symbolic-expressions-and-their-computation-by-machine-part-i/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org6846515" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org6846515"&gt;Recursive functions of symbolic expressions and their computation by machine, Part I&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org6846515"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
John McCarthy.  &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/367177.367199"&gt;Recursive Functions of Symbolic Expressions and
Their Computation by Machine, Part I&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. Communications of the ACM
&lt;b&gt;3&lt;/b&gt;, pp.184–195. 1960.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The original Lisp paper from 1960, which opens:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A programming system called LISP (for LISt Processor) has been
developed for the IBM 704 computer…
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The paper then proceeds to lay out everything that's since been
built on: the basic constructs, the use of cons cells (pairs) as a
data representation, the world's first garbage collection algorithm,
an equational semantics, and ideas for interpretation and
compilation. It's awesome, and humbling to read it and realise its
age and the vision of computing it developed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
(Despite this paper being labelled Part I, incidentally, there
isn't a part II.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>history</category><category>lisp</category><category>project:lisp-bibliography</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2024/03/07/recursive-functions-of-symbolic-expressions-and-their-computation-by-machine-part-i/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 19:34:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>TIL: The first ever .com domain</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2024/01/02/til-the-first-ever-com-domain/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org6e774fc" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org6e774fc"&gt;TIL: The first ever .com domain&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org6e774fc"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today I learned that the first .com internet domain registered on
the internet was &lt;a href="https://symbolics.com"&gt;https://symbolics.com&lt;/a&gt; and belonged to Symbolics, a
company that made Lisp machines.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It doesn't relate to Lisp any more, of course. It's been sold to
someone who "helps entrepreneurs and investors acquire high-end
domain names", which seems about as meta as things can get: the
first-ever .com domain name now points a company focused on
acquiring domain names.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Symbolics itself has a storied history, spinning-out from the MIT AI
lab to sell hardware dedicated to running Lisp: one of &lt;i&gt;two&lt;/i&gt; such
start-ups actually. The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symbolics"&gt;Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt; is a good place to start.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Incidentally, the rest of the top-ten first .com domains can be
found &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/media/pda/2008/dec/22/internet-domains"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>history</category><category>internet</category><category>lisp</category><category>til</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2024/01/02/til-the-first-ever-com-domain/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 11:44:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>When not to return a library book</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2012/05/08/library-book/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Beware of books bearing illnesses.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

I recently read &lt;em&gt;Hindenburg: the wooden titan&lt;/em&gt;, John Wheeler-Bennet's biography of the presidency of the man who ushered Hitler into power. It's an interesting book, written just after Hindenburg's death and so before the second world war and the realisation of exactly what had been brought forth. You can also find &lt;a href="http://www.vqronline.org/articles/1937/summer/hoover-wooden-titan/" target="_blank"&gt;contemporary book reviews online&lt;/a&gt; which are likewise fascinating in what they don't know. It really brings home AJP Taylor's comment (in &lt;em&gt;The struggle for mastery in Europe&lt;/em&gt;) that that hardest thing about the study of history to to remember that events now long in the past once lay in the future.

&lt;a href="http://blogs.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/simondobson/files/2012/05/2012-03-17-17.12.12-e1336223919163.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="alignleft size-medium wp-image-1138" title="Bookplate" src="http://blogs.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/simondobson/files/2012/05/2012-03-17-17.12.12-e1336223919163-190x300.jpg" alt="" width="190" height="300"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What was unexpectedly fascinating was the bookplate in the front of the volume I borrowed from the university library, which was published in 1937. (I think it's a first edition.) The top half is fairly standard, but the bottom part describes something you wouldn't expect to find &lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;in a library book:

&lt;em&gt;"A person shall not return any public library book which he knows to have been exposed to infection from a notifiable disease ... [including] smallpox, cholera, diphtheria, ..."&lt;/em&gt;

And so on. The list of diseases includes things against which we are now routinely vaccinated (diphtheria, tuberculosis), those we haven't seen in the UK in my lifetime (typhus), and those most people would now brush-off with a course of antibiotics (flu, pneumonia). Except, of course, that at the time there was far less vaccination and no antibiotics at all, since &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penicillin" target="_blank"&gt;mass production didn't start until the 1940's&lt;/a&gt;.

So as well as being an observation of a period in history from a point in time from which its significance was only poorly understood, this book is a time capsule from a period when diseases were a lot bigger and broader threat than they are now.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>history</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2012/05/08/library-book/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2012 07:00:55 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>