<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about humour)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/humour.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 15:57:24 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Commuting again</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2020/11/05/commuting/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, for the first time since mid-March, I went physically back to
my University to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2020/11/05/commuting/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>covid-19</category><category>essay</category><category>humour</category><category>pandemic</category><category>teaching</category><category>university</category><category>writing</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2020/11/05/commuting/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2020 13:20:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why is my wheelie bin measured in decibels?</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2011/06/10/wheeliebin/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;An unexpected curiosity arising from a common household appliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've just been clearing up the remains of a tree that came down in my garden after the recent storms. Morningside isn't generally noted for hurricane-force winds, but we got them a fortnight or so ago while we were away. In doing so I noticed that the inside of the wheelie bin that we're supplied with by Edinburgh council for garden waste has a peculiar marking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Wheeliebin decibels" src="https://simondobson.org/images/posts/20110610-wheeliebin-db.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems to indicate that there's something about the bin measured in decibels: a &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Decibel" target="_blank"&gt;logarithmic unit of relative power&lt;/a&gt;. There's also what looks like a speaker next to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which rather begs the question: why is my wheelie bin measured in decibels?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first thought was sound: wheelie bins are notoriously noisy when wheeled around, so perhaps this is the sound output one expects from this particular model. However, 99dB is &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Sound_pressure#Examples_of_sound_pressure_and_sound_pressure_levels" target="_blank"&gt;approximately the sound level of a jackhammer at 1m distance&lt;/a&gt;, and considerably more than the sound level at which one is recommended to wear ear defenders.  Much as I dislike wheelie bins being wheeled around early in the morning, I doubt they're a threat to my hearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this is a level of sound that the wheelie bin can muffle? Quality product though it is, it hardly seems likely that it would muffle the sound of a jackhammer being used inside it. Even if one wanted to. And such an application seems, shall we say, a little exotic for the manufacturer to have printed this specification on every wheelie bin they sell. If this &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the case, it should perhaps be better advertised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be the sound made by a wheelie bin full of bottles being tipped out, but that's surely a function of the bottles and the manner in which they're emptied rather than being a property that should be stamped on the bin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another use of decibels is in electronics, specifically to measure the power of an amplifier or radio antenna. It'd certainly be possible to use a wheelie bin as an amplifier for a speaker, although that too sounds somewhat esoteric. As a radio antenna it suffers the disadvantage of not being conductive and so not suitable as a waveguide. I suppose you could coat the inside with tinfoil, but we're again into  not-exactly-mainstream-customer-uses territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I'm somewhat at a loss: any suggestions, however inane, gratefully
received.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>curiosity</category><category>humour</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2011/06/10/wheeliebin/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2011 14:44:06 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>