<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about ireland)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/ireland.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 17:16:10 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Research fellowships available in Dublin</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2014/05/16/research-fellowships/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Two post-doctoral positions in smart cities now available at Trinity College Dublin.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Research Fellowships in Autonomic Service-Oriented Computing for Smart Cities&lt;/strong&gt;

Applications are invited for two Postdoctoral Research Fellowships at &lt;a href="http://www.dsg.cs.tcd.ie/" target="_blank"&gt;Trinity College Dublin’s Distributed Systems Group&lt;/a&gt; to investigate the provision of a new service-oriented computing infrastructure that provides demand-based composition of software services interacting with a city-wide, dynamic network infrastructure. The project will investigate autonomic adaptation of services and infrastructure, ensuring resilient service provision within an integrated, city-wide system.

Applicants should have a Ph.D. in Computer Science, Computer Engineering or a closely-related discipline and strong C++/C#/Java development skills. Experience with autonomic computing, service-oriented middleware, and/or smart city technologies is desirable as are strong mathematical skills.

The project is supported by Science Foundation Ireland under the Principal Investigator programme between 2014-2018 and will be conducted in collaboration with Cork Institute of Technology, NUI Maynooth, IBM Smarter Cities Research Centre, Intel Intelligent Cities Lab, EMC2 Research Europe, and Arup.  The position is tenable from September 2014.

Please apply by email to &lt;a href="mailto:Siobhan.Clarke@scss.tcd.ie"&gt;Siobhan.Clarke@scss.tcd.ie&lt;/a&gt; quoting “Smart Cities Fellowship” in the subject line. Applications should include a curriculum vitae, in PDF format, giving full details of qualifications and experience, together with the names of two referees. The closing date for applications is the 20th June, 2014.

Trinity College is an equal opportunities employer.

 &lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ireland</category><category>jobs</category><category>pervasive systems</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2014/05/16/research-fellowships/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2014 12:39:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief scientific advisor for Ireland</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2012/11/17/csa/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm a little perplexed by the direction of the current discussion over Ireland's chief scientific advisor.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

The need for scientific advice, as a driver of (and sanity check upon) evidence-based policy formation, has arguably never been greater. Certainly many of the challenges we face living in the 21st century are, directly or indirectly, influenced by a sound understanding of both the science and its limitations. This is why it's attractive for governments to have dedicated, independent scientific advisors.

We need first to be clear what a good chief scientific advisor &lt;em&gt;isn't&lt;/em&gt;, and that is an oracle. The chief scientist will presumably be a trained, nationally and internationally respected practitioner who brings to the job an experience in the practice of science but also in its wider analysis and impact. In many respects these are the qualities one looks for in a senior academic -- a full professor -- so it's unsurprising that chief scientists are often current or former (emeritus) professors at leading institutions. They will not be expert on all the areas of science required to address any particular policy question -- indeed, they might &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; be expert in the details pertaining to &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; question asked -- but they can act as a gateway to those who &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; expert, and collate and contrast the possibly conflicting views of different experts who might be consulted in each case. They provide a bridge in this sense between the world of the research and the world of policy, and will need to be able to explain clearly the basis and consequences of what the science is saying.

Ireland has recently abandoned having a chief scientist as an independent role, and has instead elected to combine it with the role of Director of &lt;a href="http://www.sfi.ie" target="_blank"&gt;Science Foundation Ireland&lt;/a&gt;, the main advanced research funding agency. There are &lt;a href="http://www.rte.ie/news/2012/1112/richard-bruton-science.html" target="_blank"&gt;several stated reasons&lt;/a&gt; for this, most centring on the current resource constraints facing government spending.

I don't think this structure is really consistent with the role of chief scientist, nor with the principles of good governance.

To avoid any misunderstandings, let's be clear that this has nothing to do with the individuals involved: the current or former directors of SFI would be eminently suited to be a chief scientist in their own right. However, having the SFI director fill this additional role &lt;em&gt;ex officio&lt;/em&gt; seems not to be best practice. The concern must be that the combined role cannot be independent by its very nature, in that the &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2012/09/sfi-consultation/" target="_blank"&gt;scientific direction&lt;/a&gt; of SFI may wholly or in part be involved in the policy decisions being made as a consequence of advice received. If this occurs, the chief scientist is then recommending actions for which the director must take responsibility, and the perception of a confusion of interest is inevitable if these roles are filled by the same individual. To repeat, the integrity of the office-holders is not the issue, but rather a governance structure that conflates the two roles of execution and oversight.

If resource constraints are really the issue, one might say that the chief scientist does not need to be independently employed to be independent in the appropriate sense. The chief scientific advisory roles in the UK, for example, are typically filled by academics on part-time release from their host institutions. They collate and offer scientific advice, possibly made better by the fact that they remain active researchers and so remain current on both the science and its practice, rather than being entirely re-located into the public service. (The &lt;a href="http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Topics/Business-Industry/science/OCSA" target="_blank"&gt;chief scientific advisor for Scotland&lt;/a&gt;, for example, remains a computer science researcher at the University of Glasgow in addition to her advisory role.) The risk of confusion is significantly less in this structure, because a single academic in a single institution does not exert executive control or influence over wider funding decisions. Moreover the individual remains employed by (and in the career and pension structure of) their host university and is bought-out for part of their time, which reduces the costs significantly. It also means that one can adjust the time commitment as required.

I thought when the post was first created that it was unusual that the Irish chief scientist's post was full-time: requiring the (full-time) SFI director to find time in addition for the (presumably also full-time) duties of chief scientific advisor is expecting a lot.

It is of course vital for the government to be getting good science advice, so it's good that the chief scientist role is being kept in some form. But I think it would be preferable to think about the governance structure a little more, to avoid any possible perception of confusion whether or not such confusion exists in practice.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ireland</category><category>strategy</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2012/11/17/csa/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Nov 2012 08:00:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Response to Science Foundation Ireland's consultation on its strategic plan</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2012/09/26/sfi-consultation/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;a href="http://www.sfi.ie" target="_blank"&gt;Science Foundation Ireland&lt;/a&gt; (SFI) recently launched its strategic plan for the coming years. This is my contribution to the consultation process.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

It's quite unusual for there to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; a consultation process, of course: many such documents are drafted by governments and their agencies without reference to the opinions of outside stakeholders, so it's gratifying that SFI is confident enough to put its thoughts out for public comment. It's also gratifying that the aims and aspirations embodied by the document are so forward-looking and ambitious, given the parlous state of the country's finances: the straightened times only make government investment in science &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; important, as a route to improving the country's position.
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;There are however some issues that I think merit further consideration. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;the orientation of basic research;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;the demands on staff from different phases of the research lifecycle;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;the career trajectories of PhD students;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;the significance of capacity-building, especially in the area of spin-outs and other indirect benefits; and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;the possible extended leveraging of the expertise present in Irish science as part of the organisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
What follows is abstracted from the letter I submitted to the consultation. I've removed some of the extraneous detail and generalised slightly to make the content less Ireland-specific, as a lot of the issues will be faced (or indeed are being faced) by funding agencies elsewhere.
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Orientation of basic research.&lt;/strong&gt; The orientation of research suggests that one can create a clear vision of what is going to be successful and impactful. This is clearly not the case: many areas that have changed the world in the long term had little or no short-term applicability when they were first investigated (for example lasers and hypermedia). The notion of government funding as “sowing seeds” therefore needs to be regarded with caution, and the history of (for example) Silicon Valley is notable mostly for the &lt;em&gt;lack&lt;/em&gt; of directed and co-ordinated government investment and a focus instead on capacity-building (see below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;To maximise the chances of breakthroughs, one must allow experimentation that cannot be justified in terms of its known or predicted impact.&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;One hears a lot about the “impact” and “spillover” of “basic” research into more “applied” areas. It is worth noting that such a hard distinction between “basic” and “applied” research is now largely discredited: a more accurate characterisation might be between “applied” and “not applied (yet)”. This is important, as it implies that any calculation of the value for money of any piece of research is often more a matter of timescale than of any intrinsic property of the work or field. Much of the mathematics that now underlies on-line cryptography, for example, was developed decades before its was practically applied, without such number theory having any obvious applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;The basic difficulty with orientating basic research is that it is almost always a backward-facing activity, in the sense that one can only generate evidence in support of areas that have already demonstrated relevance and/or which already have a significant local industrial presence. Unless care is taken this can exclude promising areas for which there is currently no market but which have the capacity for enormous impact going forward. (3-D printing is the technology that springs most to mind here.) Setting a limit on the funding that will go to non-prioritised areas seems unlikely to provide for a broad exploration of speculative areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phases and skills.&lt;/strong&gt; It is important to recognise that excellent research scientists are often not the appropriate individuals to commercialise their own work. When one is speaking of the research lifecycle, it is clearly true that the translation phase is as creative and exciting as the discovery phase. However, it must be recognised that the skills required in these two phases are very different. While some exceptional individuals are able to muster excellence in both discovery and translation, this is extremely rare, as evidenced by the tendency of the founders of research-led start-ups to leave (or be eased out) as their companies grow: most scientists function better in one regime or the other. Put another way, excellent research scientists will be more productive overall if they are not forced into an inappropriate role. It would therefore be appropriate to generate structures whereby research can be ”handed off” between groups, and that recruitment and funding structures be introduced to ensure that scientists in each phase are treated equally and fairly – although not necessarily identically, to reflect their different motivations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PhD careers. &lt;/strong&gt;The decision whether to go into industry or academia is a complex one, driven by an individual's temperament and interests&lt;em&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;I believe that care is needed in aspiring to move some given percentage of PhD graduates into industry. It would be a mistake to attempt to direct such career decisions, since trained researchers wanting to pursue academic careers that are not available locally will not generally take up industrial posts as an alternative: they will simply move abroad. This cohort of researchers is highly mobile and motivated, and only by providing matching opportunities will their skills be retained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capacity-building.&lt;/strong&gt; While there is clearly enormous potential value in direct commercialisation of research products, there is far more value in the ICT space from simply building capacity. I have been struck by the number of start-up companies in Dublin formed by former PhD students (including several of my own) – but I have been further struck by the work these companies are doing, which often does not relate to the research topics of their founders. Indeed, in most cases the companies' work &lt;em&gt;could not&lt;/em&gt; have led to a PhD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;This I think underlines the importance of intellectual capacity-building, and a corollary is that what is important is that the system generate researchers, rather than being solely concerned about the actual research done in training these individuals. Brilliant, educated minds will go on to do good work: if attracting the best minds is best accomplished by supporting them in basic research for their PhDs, this will be a good investment. It is noticeable that many staff in Silicon Valley companies have PhDs from local universities in very foundational topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;Another aspect of capacity-building that often goes unmentioned is the progression of staff in post: the recognition that the excellent researchers need to have their career aspirations met and respected. There is ample evidence that this function is not properly dealt with by many institutions within their current structures: the exclusive focus on importing “iconic” and “prize-winning” staff can be demoralising to local staff, who can then become demotivated or induced to emigrate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;I believe the evidence supports the notion that staff in post will overall be more motivated, and more committed, by promotion than many high-flying individuals who may regard their appointment as a temporary base or a prelude to retirement, and may not continue to do the world-leading work that underpinned their recruitment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integrating expertise. &lt;/strong&gt;SFI aspires to be a “model” department in terms of supporting scientific activity. One approach that might be beneficial is that pursued by the NSF, to second scientists into the organisation as programme officers. This approach – which I believe is currently unique to NSF – seems to deliver very well-managed programmes, gives the organisation access to a range of scientific talent, ensures that the staff in charge of programmes are up-to-date with the latest science, and also immensely benefits the management skills of the scientists involved. It is true that  it can be challenging to manage conflicts of interest, but the research community in the US is also “a small country” in this sense, so I am sure that mechanisms can be found. Providing seconded individuals with a funded postdoc &lt;em&gt;ex officio&lt;/em&gt; (as we do in St Andrews for Heads of School) might allow their own research to proceed in their absence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;It'll be interesting to see what happens to the strategic plan as a result of the consultation, but whatever the result it's a creative and constructive exercise to test the plan against an outside audience. I'd like to think this can only improve the process of governance for State-supported science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="LEFT"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ireland</category><category>strategy</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2012/09/26/sfi-consultation/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2012 07:00:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why do people go to university?</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2011/09/08/people-university/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Changes to admissions systems in the UK and Ireland simply tinker with the existing approach. They don't address the more fundamental changes in the relationship between university education, economic and social life.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

We're in the middle of a lot of changes in academia, with the fees increase for students in England eliciting a response in Scotland, and a &lt;a href="http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/opinion/2011/0908/1224303701553.html"&gt;report in Ireland suggesting changes to the "points" system of admissions&lt;/a&gt; to introduce more targeting. Despite the upsets these changes cause to academics -- they heighten the arbitrary and distressing discontinuity in costs between Scottish and English students in St Andrews, for example -- they're actually quite superficial in the sense of not massively changing the degrees on offer or their structure. However, these would seem to be the areas in which change could be most fruitful, in response to changing patterns of life, patterns of access to information and the like. It's hard to generate enthusiasm for this amid the problems of managing the financial structures. In other words, the fees &lt;em&gt;débâcle&lt;/em&gt; may be masking changes that we would otherwise be well advised to make.

What are these changes? First of all we need to understand what we believe about the lives and futures of the people who might attend university. For me this includes the following:

&lt;strong&gt;People don't know what they're passionate about.&lt;/strong&gt; Passionate enough to want to spend a substantial portion of their lives on it, that is. There's a tendency to follow an "approved" path into a stable career, and this in may in some cases lead people to do the "wrong" degree as they worry about their job prospects. But if you're going into a career in something, you have to accept that you'll spend about half your waking life on it. It makes sense to be sure you'll enjoy it. So we need to focus on allowing people to find their passions, which argues against too-early specialisation and for a broader course of study.

&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;My first postdoc supervisor, Chris Wadsworth, told me about 20 years ago that "it takes you 10 years to decide what you're actually interested in." In your mid-20s you tend to disregard statements like this and assume you &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; what your research interests are, but on reflection he was right: it &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; take me about 10 years to work out what I wanted to spend my career researching, and it wasn't really what I was doing back then: related, yes, but definitely off to one side. I've also become interested in a whole range of other things that were of no interest to me back then, not least because most of them didn't exist. If that's true of an academic, it's just as true of an 18-year-old undergraduate. You can have an idea what you like and what interests you, but not much more than that.

&lt;strong&gt;We can't teach enough.&lt;/strong&gt; It used to be simpler: go to university, learn all the things you'll need, then go and practice those skills with marginally upgrading for the rest of your career. I can't think of many topics like that any more.

This changes the emphasis of education: it's not the stuff we teach that's important, it's the ability to upskill effectively. For that you need foundations, and you need to know the important concepts, and you need to be able to figure out the details for yourself. It's not that these details aren't important -- in computing, for example, they're critical -- but they're also changing so fast that there's no way we &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; keep up. And in fact, if we &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt;, we'd be doing the students a dis-service by suggesting that this isn't a process of constant change.

&lt;strong&gt;The jobs that people will want to do in 20 years' time don't exist now.&lt;/strong&gt; Fancy a career as a web designer? Didn't exist 20 years ago; 10 years ago it was a recognised and growing profession; lately it's become part and parcel of graphic design. The world changes &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; rapidly. &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2011/07/arts-humanities/"&gt;Even if the job you love still exists&lt;/a&gt;, there's a good chance you'll want to change to another one mid-career. Again, the ability to learn new skills becomes essential. I suspect a lot of people -- including politicians -- haven't appreciated &lt;em&gt;just how fast&lt;/em&gt; the world is changing, and that the pace of change is accelerating. You don't have to believe in &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Technological_singularity"&gt;the Sigularity&lt;/a&gt; to believe that this has profound implications for how economies and careers work.

&lt;strong&gt;We don't know where the future value comes from.&lt;/strong&gt; In a time of increased financial stress, governments fall back on supporting courses that "obviously" support economic growth: the STEM subjects in science, engineering, technology and medicine. The only problem with this as an argument is that it's wrong. Most of the value in the digital age &lt;em&gt;hasn't&lt;/em&gt; come from these areas. The profits at Apple and Google pale into insignificance behind the aggregate profits of the companies (often much smaller) making content to add value to the devices and services these companies provide. I've argued before that &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2011/07/arts-humanities/"&gt;this value chain is best supported by humanities graduates&lt;/a&gt;, not scientists and engineers. (If you want a supporting example, consider this as a proposition: the whole argument about network neutrality is essentially an argument about whether  ISPs should be allowed to tax the producers and consumers of the content they transmit in terms of its end-user value, rather than in terms of its transmission cost. That's where the value is.)

Does the above have anything to suggest about changes in admissions or the structure of degrees. To me it suggests a number of things. Have broad introductory years in which students are encouraged to explore their wider interests before specialising. (The Scottish broad curriculum attempts to do this, but in sciences we don't do it particularly well.) Focus teaching on core principles and on how these affect the evolution of tools and techniques. Also focus on students learning the tools and techniques themselves, and showing how they relate back to the taught core. Generate a set of smaller degree-lets that people can take over their career with less commitment: at a distance, in the evening, in compressed blocks, over a long period -- whatever, just suitable for people to do alongside working at something else. Above all, don't assume we (either the universities or the State) can pick winners in terms of subjects. We're definitely in a post-industrial world, that means new intellectual territory and that what worked before won't always work in the future. I hope &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2010/04/computer-microscope/"&gt;computer science will continue to change the world&lt;/a&gt;, but I'm also completely confident that a history graduate will come up with one of the Next Big Things.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ireland</category><category>university</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2011/09/08/people-university/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2011 10:56:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Book: Tumbledown -- the old houses of Co Sligo</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2011/02/09/tumbledown/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The west of Ireland is full of old, decrepit buildings that seem to have been left behind by the Celtic Tiger years -- and just crying out to be photographed.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

Over summer 2010 I spent a happy few days touring around Sligo and nearby counties taking shots of the half-hidden, half-derelict houses hidden in the undergrowth. Then I discovered on-demand book publishing, so now the collection is a book.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:left;width:450px"&gt;&lt;a target="_new" href="http://www.blurb.com/books/preview/1807775?ce=blurb_ew&amp;amp;utm_source=widget"&gt;&lt;img src="http://bookshow.blurb.com/bookshow/cache/P2507577/md/wcover_2.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.blurb.com/bookstore/detail/1807775?ce=blurb_ew&amp;amp;utm_source=widget" target="_blank" style="margin:12px 3px"&gt;Tumbledown by Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
The publishing service is called &lt;a href="http://www.blurb.com"&gt;Blurb&lt;/a&gt;, and lets you download a desktop-publishing program that can be used to generate books from a range of different templates, including some that are designed for art photography. The quality of the printing is excellent -- &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; better than results I've had from other similar services. What's even better is that Blurb hosts a bookshop from which anyone else can buy a copy of your book, so if you'd like a copy just follow the link above.

I have a feeling this sort of vanity publishing could become quite addictive. I've thought of half a dozen other photo projects that'd make decent books -- undoubtedly &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2011/01/unpopular-book/"&gt;more popular than any of my technical writing&lt;/a&gt;, anyway. For art books it's clearly much more attractive than an ebook; and while it's more expensive per book than traditional publishing, the huge advantage is that you don't have to pay for, stack up and distribute inventory beforehand.  It certainly reduces the barriers to entry for stroking your own ego, anyway :-)</description><category>ireland</category><category>photography</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2011/02/09/tumbledown/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2011 08:00:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The (new) idea of a (21st century) university</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2011/01/18/university-vision/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;What should the university of the 21st century look like? What are we preparing our students for, and how? And how should we decide what is the appropriate vision for modern universities?

&lt;!--more--&gt;

There's a tendency to think of universities as static organisations whose actions and traditions remain fixed -- and &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2010/12/inauguration/"&gt;looking at some ceremonial events&lt;/a&gt; it's easy to see where that idea might come from. Looking in from the outside one might imagine that some of the teaching of "old material" (such as my teaching various kinds of sorting algorithms) is just a lack of agility in responding to the real world: who needs to know? Why not just focus on the modern stuff?

This view is largely mistaken. The point of teaching a core of material is to show how subjects evolve, and to get students used to thinking in terms of the core concepts rather than in terms of ephemera that'll soon pass on. Modern stuff doesn't &lt;em&gt;stay&lt;/em&gt; modern, and that is a feature of the study of history or geography as much as of computer science or physics. Universities by their nature have a ringside view of the changes that will affect the world in the future, and also contain more than their fair share of maverick &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2010/10/academic-stereotypes/"&gt;"young guns"&lt;/a&gt; who want to mix things up. It's natural for academics to be thinking about what future work and social spaces will be like, and to reflect on how best to tweak the student experience with these changes in mind.

What brought this to my mind  is Prof Colm Kenny's &lt;a href="http://www.independent.ie/opinion/columnists/colum-kenny/colum-kenny-years-of-neglect-have-taken-their-toll-on-higher-education-2497962.html"&gt;analysis piece in the &lt;em&gt;Irish Independent this weekend&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a response to the recently-published Hunt report ("&lt;em&gt;National strategy for higher education: draft report of the strategy group&lt;/em&gt;." 9 August 2010) that tries to set out a vision for Irish 3rd-level (undergraduate degree) education. Although specific to Ireland, the report raises questions for other countries' relationships with their universities too, and so is worth considering broadly.

A casual read of even the executive summary reveals a managerial tone. There's a lot of talk of productivity, broadening access, and governance that ensures that institutions meet performance targets aligned with national priorities. There's very little on encouraging free inquiry, fostering creativity, or equipping students for the 21st century. The report -- and similar noises that have emerged from other quarters, in Ireland and the UK -- feel very ... well ... 20th century.

Life and higher education used to be very easy: you learned your trade, either as an apprentice or at university; you spent forty years practising it, using essentially those techniques you'd been imparted with plus minor modifications; you retired, had a few years off, and then died. But that's past life: future, and indeed current, life aren't going to be like that. For a start, it's not clear when if ever we'll actually get to retire. Most people won't stay in the same job for their entire careers: indeed, a large percentage of jobs that one could do at the start of a career won't even &lt;em&gt;exist&lt;/em&gt; forty years later, just as many of those jobs haven't been thought of now. When I did my PhD 20 years ago there was no such thing as a web designer, and music videos were huge projects that no-one without access to a fully-equipped multi-million-pound studio could take on. Many people change career because they want to rather than through the influence of outside forces, such as leaving healthcare to take up professional photography.

What implications does this have for higher education? Kenny rightly points out that, while distance education and on-line courses are important, they're examples of mechanism, not of vision. What they have in common, and what drives their attractiveness, is that they lower the barriers to participation in learning. They actually do this in several ways. They allow people to take programmes without re-locating and potentially concurrently with their existing lives and jobs. They also potentially allow people to "dip-in" to programmes rather than take them to their full extent, to mash-up elements from different areas, institutions and providers, and to democratise the generation and consumption of learning materials.

Some students, on first coming to university, are culture-shocked by the sudden freedom they encounter. It can take time to work out that  universities aren't schools, and academics aren't teachers. In fact they're dual concepts: a school is an institution of &lt;em&gt;teaching&lt;/em&gt;, where knowledge is pushed at students in a structured manner; a university is an institution of &lt;em&gt;learning&lt;/em&gt;, which exists to help students to find and interact with knowledge. The latter requires one to learn skills that aren't all that important in the former.

The new world of education will require a further set of skills. Lifelong learning is now a reality as people re-train as a matter of course. Even if they stay in the same career, the elements, techniques and technologies applied will change constantly. It's this fact of constant change and constant learning that's core to the skills people will need in the future.

(Ten years or so ago, an eminent though still only middle-aged academic came up to me in the senior common room of the university I taught in at the time and asked me when this "internet thing" was going to finish, so that we could start to understand what it had meant. I tried to explain that the past ten years were only the start of the prologue to what the internet would do to the world, but I remember his acute discomfort at the idea that things would &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; settle down.)

How does one prepare someone for lifelong learning? Actually many of the skills needed are already being acquired by people who engage with the web intensively. Anyone who reads a wide variety of material needs to be able to sift the wheat from the chaff, to recognise hidden agendas and be conscious of the context in which material is being presented. Similarly, people wanting to learn a new field need to be able to determine what they need to learn, to place it in a sensible order, locate it, and have the self-discipline to be able to stick through the necessary background.

It's probably true, though, that most people can't be successful autodidacts. There's a tendency to skip the hard parts, or the background material that (however essential) might be perceived as old and unnecessary. Universities can provide the road maps to avoid this: the curricula for programmes, the skills training, the support, examination, quality assurance and access to the world's foremost experts in the fields, while being only one possible provider of the material being explored. In other words, they can separate the learning &lt;em&gt;material&lt;/em&gt; from the learning &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; -- two aspects that are currently conflated.

I disagree with Colm Kenny on one point. He believes that only government can provide the necessary vision for the future of higher education. I don't think that's necessary at all. A system of autonomous universities can set their own visions of the future, and can design processes, execute them, assess them, measure their success and refine their offerings -- all without centralised direction. I would actually go further, and argue that the time spent planning a centralised national strategy would be better spent decentralising control of the university system and fostering a more experimental approach to learning. That's what the world's like now, and academia's no different.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ireland</category><category>strategy</category><category>university</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2011/01/18/university-vision/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2011 08:00:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Modern postcodes</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2011/01/12/modern-postcodes/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Ireland doesn't have a postcode system -- a state of affairs that causes endless problems with badly-designed web sites that expect them, as well as with courier deliveries. But of course in the internet age there's no reason to wait for the State to act...

&lt;!--more--&gt;

It always surprises people that Ireland &lt;em&gt;doesn't&lt;/em&gt; have post codes, when pretty much everywhere else does. Dublin has postal districts -- I used to work in Dublin 4, which covers about 50 square kilometres and so doesn't really function as an aid to delivery or navigation -- but there's nothing similar in the rest of the country. Add to this the fact that many country villages don't have street names either, and you start to understand why getting a package delivered by a courier usually involves a phone call to talk them along the route.

In actual fact the problem is &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; severe than you might expect, because the postal system works rather well. This is because the postmen and women get very good at learning where each person lives by name, so a name, village and county will normally get through (outside a major town). The villages are small and people tend not to move too frequently, so human-based routing works well for frequent contacts. For couriers and infrequent service providers, though, it's a different story. I usually have to take phone calls from the people who deliver heating oil, for example, because a twice-a-year delivery isn't enough for them to remember where we live.

One might think that this situation would be easily remedied: choose a postcode system and implement it. But this leads to the next thing that people often find surprising: many people in the countryside, despite the obvious benefits in terms of convenience and efficiency, are implacably opposed to postcodes. The fear is that such a system would do away with the quaint townland names: each village will often have several smaller townlands surrounding it, that get mentioned in the postal addresses. These often have a lot of history attached to them, and in some parts of the country are written in Irish even when nothing else is. Every time the idea of national postcodes is raised in the national press a whole host of letters are published opposing it and predicting the death of the rural Irish lifestyle, and it seems that this has been enough to stymie the implementation of the system on a national basis. There are a disproportionate number of Irish parliamentary seats in rural areas, so political parties are loath to do anything that alienates the rural vote.

In past times, that would have been it: the State doesn't act, end of story. But we're now in the internet age, and one doesn't have to wait for the State.

I just came across &lt;a href="http://www.myloc8ion.com/"&gt;Loc8&lt;/a&gt;, a company that has established an all-Ireland post code system. They've devised a system of short codes that can be used to locate houses to within about 6m. So -- to take an example directly from the web site -- the Burlington Hotel in Dublin has Loc8 code NN5-39-YD7. The codes are structured according to the expected hierarchy of a zone, a locality and then a specific location, with the latter (as far as I can tell) being sparse and so not predictable from neighbouring codes: you can't derive the code of one property by knowing one nearly. (I might be wrong about that, though.)

So far so good. If the service is useful, people will use it: and apparently they are. You can enter a Loc8 code into some GPS systems already, which is a major step forward. The courier companies -- and even, apparently, the national postal service, An Post -- will apparently take Loc8 codes too. There's also a &lt;a href="http://www.myloc8ion.com/xueli/Firefox_download"&gt;plug-in for Firefox&lt;/a&gt; that will lookup a Loc8 code from the context menu: try it on the code above. It's a bit clunky -- why does it need to pop-up a confirmation dialogue? -- and integration with something like &lt;a href="http://www.hyperwords.net/"&gt;Hyperwords&lt;/a&gt; would make it even more useable, but it's a start.

What I like about Loc8 is that it's free and (fairly) open: you can look a code up on their web site and it'll be displayed using Google Maps. The integration with commercial GPS systems is a great move: I don't know if it's integrated with the Google navigation on Android, but if it isn't it'd be easy enough for LOC8 to do -- or indeed &lt;em&gt;for anyone else&lt;/em&gt;, and that's the great bonus over (for example) the closed pay-world of UK postcode geolocation.

The real story here is that it's possible to mash-up a national-scale system using extremely simple web tools, make it available over the web -- and then, if there's value enough, cut commercial deals with other providers to exploit the added value. That sort of national reach is a real novelty, and something we're bound to see more of: I'd like something similar for phone numbers, skype names and the like, all mashed-up and intermixed.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ireland</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2011/01/12/modern-postcodes/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2011 08:00:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Call for panels in integrated network management</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2010/09/24/im11-panels/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;We're looking for expert panels to be run at the IFIP/IEEE International Symposium on Integrated Network Management in Dublin in May 2011.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IFIP/IEEE International Symposium on Integrated Network Management (IM 2011)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
Dublin, Ireland, 23-27 May 2011
&lt;a href="http://www.ieee-im.org/"&gt;http://www.ieee-im.org/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Call for panels&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
IM is one of the premier venues in network management, providing a forum for discussing a broad range of issues relating to network structure, services, optimisation, adaptation and management. This year's symposium has a special emphasis on effective and energy-efficient design, deployment and management of current and future networks and services.
We are seeking proposals for expert discussion panels to stimulate and inform the audience as to the current "hot topics" within network management. An ideal panel will bring the audience into a discussion prompted by position statements from the panel members, taking account of both academic and industrial viewpoints. We are interested in panels on all aspects of network management, especially those related to the theme of energy awareness and those discussing the wider aspects of networks and network management. This would include the following topics, amongst others:
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Multi-transport and multi-media networks&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Network adaptation and optimisation&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Co-managing performance and energy&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The uses and abuses of sensor networks&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The science of service design and implementation&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Programming network management strategies&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Tools and techniques for network management&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Socio-technical integration of networks&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Energy-efficiency vs equality of access&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Network-aware cloud computing&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The future of autonomic management&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Coping with data obesity&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Managing the next-generation internet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to propose a panel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
Please send a brief (1-page) proposal to the panel chairs, &lt;a href="mailto:sd@cs.st-andrews.ac.uk"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="mailto:gp.parr@ulster.ac.uk"&gt;Gerard Parr&lt;/a&gt;. Your proposal should indicate the  relevance of the panel to the broad audience of IM, and include the names of proposed panel members.
&lt;h3&gt;Important dates&lt;/h3&gt;
Submission of panel proposals: 20 October 2010
Notifications of acceptance: mid-November 2010
Conference dates: 23-27 May 2011</description><category>conference</category><category>internet</category><category>ireland</category><category>networking</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2010/09/24/im11-panels/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 24 Sep 2010 09:32:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Are the grey philistines really in charge?</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2010/05/08/grey-philistines/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Recently there's been an exchange in the Irish media about the decline of intellectuals in universities and calling into question whether universities are still fit for purpose given their funding and management structures. The fundamental question seems to me to be far deeper, and impacts on the UK and elsewhere as much as Ireland: what is  -- or  should be -- the relationship between academics and their funding  sources? To what extent does the person paying the academic piper call  the research tune?

&lt;!--more--&gt;

The &lt;a href="http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/opinion/2010/0501/1224269475580.html"&gt;opening shot&lt;/a&gt; in this discussion was published in the &lt;em&gt;Irish Times&lt;/em&gt; as an op-ed piece by Tom Garvin, an emeritus (retired but still recognised) professor of politics at &lt;a href="http://www.ucd.ie"&gt;UCD&lt;/a&gt;, Ireland's largest university, although perhaps his intervention was triggered by a rather more supportive &lt;a href="http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/opinion/2010/0503/1224269588445.html"&gt;editorial&lt;/a&gt; in the same paper a few days before. The piece is something of a polemic, but revolves around the lack of support for curiosity-driven ("blue skies") research within the university system. "A grey philistinism [Garvin writes] has established itself in our universities,  under  leaders who imagine that books are obsolete, and presumably  possess none  themselves." He then goes on to attack the application of science-based research methods such as team-based investigation to humanities, and observes that even for sciences there is no longer scope for free inquiry: "Researchers are being required by bureaucrats to specify what they are   going to discover before the money to do the research is made  available." The article provoked a large number of supportive comments from readers and a rather &lt;a href="http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/opinion/2010/0506/1224269791606.html"&gt;narrow response&lt;/a&gt; from UCD's management team.

The questions Garvin raises deserve consideration, and he should be commended for raising them. Indeed, they cut to the heart of whether universities are fit for purpose. Does the linking of funding to student numbers (whether under- or post-graduate) and to the pursuit of State-guided research programmes, the desire to profit from commercially significant results, and the need (or at least desire) to excel in international league tables impact on academics' ability to investigate the world and pass on their results freely?

(For full disclosure, I should point out that I'm a computer science  academic who, until last year, worked at UCD.)

There are, of course, major differences in topic area and research philosophy between research in sciences and in humanities, and I'm sure it's fair to say that the same research approaches won't translate seamlessly from one to the other: studying and commenting on the writings of others wouldn't constitute computer science, for example. Having said that, though, there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; advantages to be had from considering the ways in which techniques translate across fields. I'm sure some projects in history (to use Garvin's example) would benefit from a team-based approach, although clearly others wouldn't -- any more than all physics research is conducted in large teams with large machines.

As a science researcher I have to point out that the crux of this argument -- specifying results before being granted funding -- is of course nonsense. When I apply for a grant I'm required to describe what I intend to investigate, the methods I'll use and the expected benefits of the investigation. This of course is a long way from specifying what I'll find, which of course I don't know, in detail: that's the whole point, after all. I don't find this to be the mental straitjacket that Garvin seems to think it is: quite the contrary, spelling these matters out is an essential planning phase to design and manage what is likely to be a complex, elongated and collaborative endeavour. If I can't explain what I want to do in a research proposal, then &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; don't know myself.

But the real question isn't about management: its about justification. Research proposals can (and probably should) be written for any research programme, but they're typically used to get funding. And it's here that we encounter the constraints on blue-skies research. A funding agency, whether public or private, will only fund research from which they'll get an acceptable impact and return on investment. Different agencies will judge that return differently. Commercial funding usually follows topics that will lead, directly or indirectly, to future profits: it's hard to see how a company's board would be meeting its fiduciary duties if it did otherwise. Private foundations and State agencies such as research councils generally have a different definition of impact, for example the abstract scientific significance of a topic or its ability to effect social change. So to that extent, an academic who takes on research funding agrees, at least tacitly, to support the funder's chosen model for assessing their research. There are some nasty examples where this causes problems, the classic case being research sponsored by tobacco companies, and taking funding doesn't excuse from their duties as scientists to collect and report their findings honestly and completely, but in the main the system doesn't cause too many dilemmas.

Given that many universities derive a large fraction of their  income (approaching 100% for some) from the State, it is natural that the State will have an interest in directing resources to topics that it regards as more significant. To do otherwise would be to neglect the State's responsibility to the electorate. Academics are not democratically accountable: it is unreasonable to expect that they should be responsible for the allocation funds they have no authority to collect.

However, there's another point that needs to be made. Most academic appointments centre around teaching and conducting research, and &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; around getting funding. This has important implications for Garvin's argument. The UK and Irish university systems are such that there is &lt;em&gt;absolutely no constraint on an academic's ability to do curiosity-driven research&lt;/em&gt;: I can conduct research on whatever topic I choose, and publish it (or not) as I see fit, at my absolute discretion (absent ethical considerations). I would be meeting fully my obligations to my employer, since these relate to my meeting my teaching and research commitments. But &lt;em&gt;I can't expect an external agency to fund me additionally&lt;/em&gt;, and it would be surprising if it were otherwise. Put another way, my academic position is my opportunity to conduct my own  curiosity-driven research, but if I require resources beyond my own I have to justify the wider benefits that will derive from that additional funding. There may be other side-effects: certainly in sciences, anyone without a significant funding profile would struggle to be promoted. But a requirement to justify the value one expects from a research programme before it's funded is hardly a crimp on academic freedom.

There's also a mis-understanding in some circles about how science is conducted: a perception that scientists go rather robotically about the conduct of the scientific method, collecting data and then drawing conclusions. This is hardly a surprising mis-perception, given that it's almost implicit in the structure of a typical paper. But it nonetheless mis-states the importance of intuition and curiosity in deciding &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; hypothesis -- amongst the infinite possibilities -- one chooses to explore. (Peter Medawar. &lt;a href="http://maagar.openu.ac.il/opus/static/binaries/editor/bank66/medawar_paper_fraud_1.pdf"&gt;Is the scientific paper a fraud?&lt;/a&gt; The Listener &lt;strong&gt;70&lt;/strong&gt;, pp. 337-378. 12 September  1963.) Without curiosity there can't really &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; any science: in fact one could go further and say that science is simply curiosity with a bit of useful structure attached.

Garvin's other point, about the lack of influence of academics on public life, was picked by &lt;a href="http://www.independent.ie/opinion/columnists/kevin-myers/kevin-myers-irish-academia-is-dominated-by-cowards-and-philistines-2168496.html"&gt;Kevin Myers&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;em&gt;Irish Independent&lt;/em&gt; as evidence of cowardice and a disinclination to risk-taking. From the perspective of the humanities this may be true, and it's not for me to comment, but from the perspective of the sciences academics have become more engaged over time in the big issues: climate science, online-privacy and evolutionary biology are the three highest-profile examples of where science academics have stepped into the public realm. It's also important to note that these three examples are first and foremost &lt;em&gt;social&lt;/em&gt; in their impact: the science is there to inform public understanding, debate and policy.

It's unfortunate that in many of these discussions "academic" has been taken tacitly to imply "academic in the humanities" -- as though scientists were somehow less "academic" (whatever that means). In the past it was perhaps more expected for humanities academics to engage as public intellectuals, but a lot of the modern world's problems &lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;simply can't be understood, let alone be debated and addressed, without the serious and deep engagement of the scientists themselves in the debate.  This, perhaps, is the biggest challenge: to capture, leverage and pass on the excitement for learning and for research into the wider community. As long as that continues to be a central goal, universities remain fit for purpose.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ireland</category><category>university</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2010/05/08/grey-philistines/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2010 17:28:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sensing financial problems</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2010/04/27/sensing-financial-problems/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Just as we can think of large-scale, detailed financial modeling as &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2010/04/computer-science-financial-crisis/"&gt;an exercise in simulation and linked data&lt;/a&gt;, we can perhaps also see the detection of hazards as an exercise in sensor fusion and pervasive computing, turning a multitude of sensor data into derived values for risk and/or situations requiring attention. There's a wealth of research in these areas that might be applicable.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

Environmental and other sensing is intended to make real-world phenomena accessible directly to computers. Typically we simply collect data and archive it for later analysis; increasingly we also move decision-making closer to the data in order to take decisions in close to real time about the ways in which the data is sensed in the future (so-called &lt;em&gt;adaptive&lt;/em&gt; sensing) or to allow the computers to respond directly in terms of the services they provide (&lt;em&gt;autonomic&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;pervasive&lt;/em&gt; systems).

Can we treat the financial markets as the targets of sensing? Well, actually, we already do. An index like the &lt;a href="http://www.ftse.com/"&gt;FTSE&lt;/a&gt; is basically providing an abstracted window onto the behaviour of an underlying process -- in this case a basket of shares from the top 100 companies listed on the London exchange -- that can be treated as an observation of an underlying phenomenon. This further suggests that the technology developed for autonomic and pervasive computing could potentially be deployed to observe financial markets.

In some sense, pricing is already based on sensing. A put option, for example -- where the buyer  gains the right to compel  the seller to buy some goods at some  point in the future at some  defined cost -- will, if exercised, have a definite value to the buyer &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; (when executed). It's value &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt; (when sold) will  be less than this, however,  because of the risk that the option will not be exercised (because, for  example, the buyer can sell the goods to someone else for more than the  seller has contracted to pay for them). Deciding what value to assign to  this contract is then a function over the expected future behaviour of  the market for the underlying goods. This expectation is formed in part by observing the behaviour of the market in the past, combined with the traders' knowledge of (or guesses about) external factors that might affect the price.

These external factors are referred to in pervasive computing as &lt;em&gt;context&lt;/em&gt;, and are used to condition the ways in which sensor streams are interpreted (see &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/research/publications/#ContextIsCentral"&gt;Coutaz &lt;em&gt;et alia&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for an overview). One obtains context from a number of sources, typically combining expert knowledge and sensor data. A typical pervasive system will build and maintain a &lt;em&gt;context model&lt;/em&gt; bringing together all the information it knows about in a single database. We can further decompose context into &lt;em&gt;primary&lt;/em&gt; context sensed directly from a data source and &lt;em&gt;secondary&lt;/em&gt; context derived by some reasoning process. If we maintain this database in a semantically tractable format such as &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/RDF/"&gt;RDF&lt;/a&gt;, we can then reason about what's happening in order to classify what's happening in the real world (&lt;em&gt;situation recognition&lt;/em&gt;) and respond accordingly. Crucially, this kind of context processing can treat &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; context as being sensed, not just real-world data: we often "sense" calendars, for example, to look for clues about intended activities and locations, integrating web mining into sensing. Equally crucially, we use context as evidence to support model hypotheses ("Simon is in a meeting with Graeme and Erica") given by the situations we're interested in.

A lot of institutions already engage in automated trading, driven by the behaviour of indices and individual stocks. Cast into sensor-driven systems terminology, the institutions develop a number of situations of interest (a time to buy, hold, sell and so forth for different portfolios) and recognise which are currently active using primary context sensed from the markets (stock prices, indices) and secondary context derived from this sensed data (stock plummeting, index in free-fall). Recognising a situation leads to a particular behaviour being triggered.

Linked data opens-up richer opportunities for collecting context, and so for the management of individual products such as mortgages. We could, for example, sense a borrower's repayment history (especially for missed payments) and use this both to generate secondary context (revised risk of default) and to identify situations of interest (default, impaired, at-risk). Banks do this already, of course, but there are advantages to the sensor perspective. For one, context-aware systems show us that it's the richness of links between  context that is the key to its usefulness. The more links we have, the more semantics we have over which to reason. Secondly, migrating to a context-aware platform means that additional data streams, inferences and situations can be added as-and-when required, without needing to re-architect the system. Given the ever-increasing amount of information available on-line, this is certainly something that might become useful.

Of course there are massive privacy implications here, not least in the use of machine classifiers to evaluate -- and of course inevitably &lt;em&gt;mis&lt;/em&gt;-evaluate -- individuals' circumstances. It's important to realise that this is going on anyway and isn't going to go away: the rational response is therefore to make sure we use the best approaches available, and that we enforce audit trails and transparency to interested parties. Credit scoring systems are notoriously opaque at present -- I've had experience of this myself recently, since credit history doesn't move easily across borders -- so there's a screaming need for systems that can explain and justify their decisions.

I suspect that the real value of a sensor perspective comes not from considering an individual institution but rather an entire marketplace. To use an example I'm familiar with from Ireland, one bank at one stage pumped its share price by having another bank make a large deposit -- but then loaned this second bank the money to fund the deposit. Contextualised analysis might have picked this up, for example by trying to classify what instruments or assets each transaction referred to. Or perhaps not: no system is going to be fully robust against the actions of ingenious insiders. The point is not to suggest that there's a foolproof solution, but rather to increase the amount and intelligence of surveillance in order to raise the bar. Given the costs involved in unwinding failures when detected late, it might be an investment worth making.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>context</category><category>finance</category><category>ireland</category><category>linked data</category><category>risk</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2010/04/27/sensing-financial-problems/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2010 12:32:57 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>