<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about jobs)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/jobs.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:simon.dobson@computer.org"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 08:30:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Research fellow in verifiable sensor systems</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2018/03/16/s4-glasgow/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.dcs.gla.ac.uk/research/S4/"&gt;Science of Sensor Systems Software&lt;/a&gt; (S4) programme grant (of which I'm a PI) has a vacancy for a research fellow based at the University of Glasgow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.jobs.ac.uk/job/BHZ314/research-assistant-associate-fellow/"&gt;Research Assistant / Associate / Fellow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Glasgow&lt;/strong&gt; - College of Science and Engineering - School of Computing Science&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salary: Grade 6/7/8; £28,098 - £31,604 / £34,520 - £38,833 / £42,418 - £49,149 per annum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The School of Computing Science at the University of Glasgow invites applications for a Post Doctoral Research Associate or Fellow position in the leading-edge research project &lt;a href="http://www.dcs.gla.ac.uk/research/S4/"&gt;Science of Sensor System Software&lt;/a&gt; (S4)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research is focused on delivering new principles and techniques for the development and deployment of verifiable, reliable, autonomous sensor-based systems that operate in uncertain, multiple and multi-scale environments. The S4 programme grant is a collaboration between four universities and you will be expected to work closely with researchers across the four universities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This position offers an exciting opportunity to gain first-hand insights into the development of sensor-based systems and to develop and apply novel modelling and reasoning techniques that contribute to the goals of verifying reliability, robustness, security, etc. Depending on your experience, the role offers considerable intellectual freedom and opportunities for you to take significant initiative, leadership, and responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The job requires expert knowledge in one or more of: formal modelling and specification, stochastic and temporal logics, automated reasoning, sensor networks, run-time verification, real-world applications. Experience of bigraphs and model checking would be an advantage. You must have started to build up a strong publication record, have excellent programming and modelling skills, and be able to quickly integrate software, e.g. for model-checking, simulation, and verification. You should be competent to undertake hands-on work related to modelling and verification of chosen, real-life case-studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You hold, or expect to hold, a PhD in Computer Science or in a closely related field; alternatively, you have a first degree in one of the above-mentioned subjects and substantial experience in a research role in industry. Fresh PhD graduates are also encouraged to apply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For appointment at Grade 8 you will need to meet the additional criteria as per the Job Description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is offered as open-ended contract with funding available for up to 30 months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is anticipated that interviews will be held in March or April 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For further information and to discuss details please contact the Principal Investigator, Professor Muffy Calder (email: &lt;a href="mailto:muffy.calder@glasgow.ac.uk"&gt;muffy.calder@glasgow.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>jobs</category><category>s4</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2018/03/16/s4-glasgow/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Mar 2018 12:29:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>2 Lecturer/Senior Lecturer positions at St Andrews</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2017/05/28/academic-positions/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We're looking to recruit new academics as part of a large on-going expansion of our academic staff. We wish to appoint two new &lt;a href="https://www.vacancies.st-andrews.ac.uk/ViewVacancyV2.aspx?enc=mEgrBL4XQK0+ld8aNkwYmLYAYEGVHElLWsnTJgL+CarIHBCM/EiQaeKOsYHKP51KpI3DcpxT/zQcAl/8iq/B+IMGPJwugR63L68sBJUS3+i3hCU7JR/EJv31DirWmhwtDXIz2HSywsmfeey5lSxnIg=="&gt;Lecturers/Senior Lecturers&lt;/a&gt; (depending on experience) to join our vibrant teaching and research community that is ranked amongst the top venues for Computer Science education and research worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The successful candidate will be expected to have a range of interests, to be active in research publication that strengthens or complements those in the School and to be capable of teaching the subject to undergraduate and taught postgraduate students who come to us with a wide range of backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excellent teaching skills and an interest in promoting knowledge exchange are essential. You should also have some familiarity with grant-seeking processes in relation to research councils and other sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More details are available on the &lt;a href="https://www.vacancies.st-andrews.ac.uk/ViewVacancyV2.aspx?enc=mEgrBL4XQK0+ld8aNkwYmLYAYEGVHElLWsnTJgL+CarIHBCM/EiQaeKOsYHKP51KpI3DcpxT/zQcAl/8iq/B+IMGPJwugR63L68sBJUS3+i3hCU7JR/EJv31DirWmhwtDXIz2HSywsmfeey5lSxnIg=="&gt;university vacancies page&lt;/a&gt;. Informal enquiries can be directed to Professor Steve Linton (&lt;a href="mailto:hos-cs@st-andrews.ac.uk"&gt;hos-cs@st-andrews.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;) or Dr Dharini Balasubramaniam (&lt;a href="mailto:dot-cs@st-andrews.ac.uk"&gt;dot-cs@st-andrews.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>jobs</category><category>st andrews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2017/05/28/academic-positions/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2017 15:17:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>PhD position in proximal sensing available at UCD Dublin</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2017/05/10/proximal-sensing-ucd/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A PhD position is available at UCD, my old employer, int he area of location sensing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Ph.D. Studentship Available&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Proximal Sensing&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;University College Dublin, Ireland&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Ph.D. studentship is now available in the School of Computer Science, University College Dublin, Ireland. The objective of the Ph.D. research project is to develop transformative algorithms for proximal sensing in outdoor environments using active and passive technologies, including LIDAR, imaging, and UWB radar. The research intersects the fields of image processing, digital signal processing, and machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is part of a larger research programme, CONSUS, which brings together the Schools of Computer Science, Agriculture and Food Science at UCD and Origin Enterprises Plc. The programme is focused on the development of novel precision agriculture techniques for enhanced crop production. CONSUS is jointly funded by Science Foundation Ireland and Origin Enterprises Plc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The successful candidate will have obtained, or will expect to obtain, a 1st class or 2.1 honours B.Sc. or B.Eng. degree in computer science, electronic engineering, or a related discipline. The successful candidate will have the ability to work both independently and as part of a multi-disciplinary team. The successful candidate will have excellent problem solving and communications skills, as well as an on-going commitment to research. A M.Sc. or M.Eng. degree or commercial experience in a relevant area is an advantage. Prior knowledge of the research topics associated with the project is an advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ph.D. position is funded for 4 years. Funding includes payment of a tax-free student stipend plus SFI fees contribution. The starting date for the position is September 2017 or as soon as possible thereafter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A full CV giving details of courses completed, marks obtained, relevant experience, and the names of two referees should be sent to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assoc. Prof. Chris Bleakley
School of Computer Science
University College Dublin
Belfield, Dublin 4, Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telephone +35317162915
Email &lt;a class="moz-txt-link-abbreviated" href="mailto:chris.bleakley@ucd.ie"&gt;chris.bleakley@ucd.ie
&lt;/a&gt;Web &lt;a class="moz-txt-link-freetext" href="http://goo.gl/bP7qWw"&gt;http://goo.gl/bP7qWw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>jobs</category><category>phd</category><category>sensor networks</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2017/05/10/proximal-sensing-ucd/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2017 08:01:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>3-year postdoctoral researcher post available</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2017/05/09/s4-postdoc/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of the Science of Sensor Systems Software programme we have a 3-year postdoc post available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.dcs.gla.ac.uk/research/S4"&gt;S4 programme&lt;/a&gt; aims to develop a unifying science, across the breadth of mathematics, computer science and engineering, that will let developers engineer for the uncertainty and ensure that their systems and the information they provide is resilient, responsive, reliable, statistically sound and robust. The vision is smarter sensor based systems in which scientists and policy makers can ask deeper questions and be confident in obtaining reliable answers, so the programme will deliver new principles and techniques for the development and deployment of verifiable, reliable, autonomous sensor systems that operate in uncertain, multiple and multi-scale environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S4 is funded by EPSRC as a five-year, £5.2M Programme Grant. It brings together four of the UK’s leading research teams in sensor systems, their design, analysis, deployment, and evaluation. Led overall by Prof Muffy Calder at the University of Glasgow, the other academic collaborators are the University of St Andrews (Prof Simon Dobson), the University of Liverpool (Prof Michael Fisher), and Imperial College (Prof Julie McCann). S4 also includes a portfolio of industrial partners ranging from start-up SMEs to multinational companies and State agencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;St Andrews leads the work on adaptive systems engineering, especially on how systems need to change as time progresses, the system components fail, and goals change. We are looking for someone to join us to work on how to program adaptive sensor systems. A strong track record in sensor systems, programming languages, data analytics, or another related area is essential, as is an ability to work within a larger team using formal methods, advanced statistics, and novel programming languages and approaches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find full application details &lt;a href="https://www.vacancies.st-andrews.ac.uk/ViewVacancyV2.aspx?enc=mEgrBL4XQK0+ld8aNkwYmIC6qnEzeM4xd5XT+e/5IQxO+OlhRndjgKS6p4BoRNl+UNu83Iiv8J1lWOCFqijDqZx6/oDoGWuUe3/xaL5So5YSmMSr2o2hu+3HhHpd8mWDap8m2c0rxOmXWk95vI/KJw=="&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>jobs</category><category>s4</category><category>sensor networks</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2017/05/09/s4-postdoc/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 13:33:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Research fellowships available in Dublin</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2014/05/16/research-fellowships/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two post-doctoral positions in smart cities now available at Trinity College Dublin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research Fellowships in Autonomic Service-Oriented Computing for Smart Cities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applications are invited for two Postdoctoral Research Fellowships at &lt;a href="http://www.dsg.cs.tcd.ie/" target="_blank"&gt;Trinity College Dublin’s Distributed Systems Group&lt;/a&gt; to investigate the provision of a new service-oriented computing infrastructure that provides demand-based composition of software services interacting with a city-wide, dynamic network infrastructure. The project will investigate autonomic adaptation of services and infrastructure, ensuring resilient service provision within an integrated, city-wide system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applicants should have a Ph.D. in Computer Science, Computer Engineering or a closely-related discipline and strong C++/C#/Java development skills. Experience with autonomic computing, service-oriented middleware, and/or smart city technologies is desirable as are strong mathematical skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is supported by Science Foundation Ireland under the Principal Investigator programme between 2014-2018 and will be conducted in collaboration with Cork Institute of Technology, NUI Maynooth, IBM Smarter Cities Research Centre, Intel Intelligent Cities Lab, EMC2 Research Europe, and Arup.  The position is tenable from September 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please apply by email to &lt;a href="mailto:Siobhan.Clarke@scss.tcd.ie"&gt;Siobhan.Clarke@scss.tcd.ie&lt;/a&gt; quoting “Smart Cities Fellowship” in the subject line. Applications should include a curriculum vitae, in PDF format, giving full details of qualifications and experience, together with the names of two referees. The closing date for applications is the 20th June, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trinity College is an equal opportunities employer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>ireland</category><category>jobs</category><category>pervasive systems</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2014/05/16/research-fellowships/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2014 12:39:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Funded research studentships available in St Andrews</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/11/17/funded-studentships/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are looking for world-class students to come and work with us. This is open to individuals of any nationality, not just UK or EU citizens. I'm especially interested in people wanting to work on programming languages, but I'd welcome inquiries in any research areas that &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/research/" target="_blank"&gt;align with mine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Funded PhD Research Studentships&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of St Andrews&lt;/strong&gt; - School of Computer Science&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div id="job-advert-text"&gt;

The School of Computer Science at the University of St  Andrews has funding for students to undertake PhD research in any of  the general research areas in the school:

&lt;a href="http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/research"&gt;http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/research&lt;/a&gt;

We are looking for highly motivated research students with an  interest in these exciting research areas. Our only requirements are  that the proposed research would be good, we have staff to supervise it,  and that you would be good at doing it. We have up to 6 funded  studentships available for students interested in working towards a PhD.  The studentships offers costs of fees and an annual tax-free  maintenance stipend of about £13,590 per year for 3.5 years.  Exceptionally well qualified and able students may be awarded an  enhanced stipend of an additional £2,000 per year. Students should  normally have or expect at least an upper-2nd class Honours degree or  Masters degree in Computer Science or a related discipline.

For further information on how to apply, see our postgraduate web pages (&lt;a href="http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/prospective-pg"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/prospective-pg&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). The closing date for applications is &lt;strong&gt;March 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; 2012&lt;/strong&gt; and we will make decisions on studentship allocation by &lt;strong&gt;May 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; 2012&lt;/strong&gt;. (Applications after &lt;strong&gt;March 1st&lt;/strong&gt; may be considered, at our discretion.) Informal enquiries can be directed to &lt;a href="mailto:pg-enquiries@cs.st-andrews.ac.uk"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;pg-admin-cs@st-andrews.ac.uk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or to potential supervisors.

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>jobs</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/11/17/funded-studentships/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2011 11:44:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Studentships in wireless sensor networks in Leuven</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/11/07/phd-leuven/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A number of PHD positions are available with Danny Hughes in the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wireless Sensor Networks are expected to play a key role in future  Internet architectures and the Internet of Things. The &lt;a href="http://distrinet.cs.kuleuven.be/" target="_blank"&gt;DistriNet  research group of the Katholieke Universiteit Leuven&lt;/a&gt; wishes to expand  its Wireless Sensor Network (WSN) research team. You will play a key  role in a highly integrated team, which has a strong and growing  research profile in the area of middleware and software development  support for WSN. Three positions are available, starting immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Possible Research Topics:&lt;/em&gt;
• System-level support for realizing WSN applications that are reliable  and reconfigurable from the lowest-levels of the network stack to the  application layer.
• Development-time support for building autonomic and reconfigurable  applications for networked embedded systems and sensor networks.
• Distributed component based software engineering approaches for  networked heterogeneous networked embedded systems such as sensors,  smart phones and web pads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Profile &amp;amp; Skills:&lt;/em&gt;
• The student must demonstrate significant enthusiasm for, and knowledge  of the subject area based upon their previous education, work and  research experience.
• A master degree in Computer Science or Informatics with previous  experience in: Distributed Systems, Middleware, Embedded Systems or  related areas.
• A team player with the capability to work in an international research team.
• Proficiency in English and excellent communication skills, both oral and written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;About DistriNet:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DistriNet is an international research group with extensive expertise in  secure and distributed software – obviously including middleware .   Research on software engineering techniques is performed in both domains  on a wide range of topics such as middleware for cloud computing,   internet architectures, network and software security, embedded systems  and multi-agent systems.  Embedded in the department of Computer Science  of the K.U.Leuven, DistriNet has a headcount of over 70 researchers of  which 9 professors and 15 Post-Docs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DistriNet has a tradition of application driven research often in close  collaboration with industry partners. Currently DistriNet is actively  involved in about 35 national and international research projects,  ranging from fundamental over strategic-basic  to applied research. More  information on projects and publications can be found at the  IBBT-DistriNet web pages:  http://distrinet.cs.kuleuven.be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three open positions are situated within a team that has been  established to provide software development support for Wireless Sensor  Networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key words: &lt;/strong&gt; Internet of Things (IoT), Networked Embedded Systems, Wireless Sensor Networks (WSN), Middleware, Component Based Softwa&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Latest application date: &lt;/strong&gt; 2011-12-31&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Financing: &lt;/strong&gt; available&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type of  Position: &lt;/strong&gt; scholarship&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source of Funding: &lt;/strong&gt; IWT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duration of the Project : &lt;/strong&gt; 4  years&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link: &lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://distrinet.cs.kuleuven.be/" target="_blank"&gt; http://distrinet.cs.kuleuven.be&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research group: &lt;/strong&gt;Department of Computer Science&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remarks:&lt;/strong&gt;
To apply you should send your:
• Curriculum Vitae
• Motivation
• Relevant research experience
• Study curriculum with rankings
• English proficiency (for foreign students)
• Pdf of diploma and transcripts (translation if necessary)
• Names (and e-mail) of 2 reference persons and the nature of contact with them
By e-mail to Danny Hughes: danny.hughes  at  cs.kuleuven.be&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Informal inquiries: Danny Hughes (danny.hughes  at cs.kuleuven.be)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start date&lt;/strong&gt;
Between 2011-11-01 and 2012-31-04&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>jobs</category><category>sensor networks</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/11/07/phd-leuven/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2011 11:39:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Research fellowship in sensor networks</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/10/03/research-fellowship-sensor-networks/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have a three-year postdoc available immediately to work on programming languages and platforms for sensor networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Research Fellow – CD1060&lt;/h3&gt;
School of Computer Science,  £32,751 - £35,788 per annum. Start: As soon as possible, Fixed Term 3 years
&lt;p&gt;We seek a  Research Fellow to design and implement an integrated software platform  based on mission specifications and evolution operators. The work will  be evaluated based on case study deployments in the context of  real-world large-scale WSANs.  You will specifically focus on generative programming techniques to  integrate the overall design, and will work with Professors Dearle and  Dobson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project involves re-architecting WSAN systems so that system-wide  behaviour is defined using explicit mission specifications. These allow  top-level constraints and trade-offs to be captured directly and used to  inform software deployment and evolution in a well-founded manner. We  compile mission-level components to collections of node-level components  connected using network overlays. We maintain both mission constraints  and management interfaces through to run-time where they can be  manipulated by evolution and recomposition operators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should have a good honours degree in Computer Science or a related  discipline, and preferably have, or be about to obtain, a PhD in  Computer Science. You will have strong software  development/OS/programming language skills. Experience in generative  programming, compilers, operating systems, component deployment and/or  sensor networks would be advantageous.  You should be a highly motivated  individual and be able to lead the day-to-day work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a fixed-term post for 3 years, starting as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a href="https://www.vacancies.st-andrews.ac.uk/ViewVacancy.aspx?enc=mEgrBL4XQK0+ld8aNkwYmO99IkxqH9eijvsCHvh08k+ze95XIC1eOev5uSd2OdKptmQ+WLedl2A+Qx1I/0DsdA==" target="_blank"&gt;university's job page&lt;/a&gt;. You can also email &lt;a href="mailto:alan.dearle@st-andrews.ac.uk"&gt;Al&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="mailto:simon.dobson@st-andrews.ac.uk"&gt;myself&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>jobs</category><category>sensor networks</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/10/03/research-fellowship-sensor-networks/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2011 10:36:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Funded PhD studentship in adaptive service ecosystems</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2010/09/09/sapere-phd/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have an opening for someone interested in doing a PhD in adaptive services.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;University of St Andrews
School of Computer Science
&lt;a href="http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk"&gt;http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funded PhD studentship in adaptive service ecosystems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The opportunity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have an opening for a talented and well-motivated individual to investigate mechanisms for the design and implementation of long-lived, responsive and adaptive ecosystems of distributed services. This work will take place in the context of the &lt;a href="http://www.sapere-project.eu/"&gt;SAPERE project&lt;/a&gt;, funded by the EU Seventh Framework  Programme. SAPERE seeks to develop both the theory and practice of "self-aware" component technology, able to orchestrate and adapt to changing requirements, constraints, conditions and technologies. The University of St Andrews is leading the strand of research into describing and identifying opportunities for adaptation, building on past work in sensor fusion and situation identification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The successful applicant will work closely with the other St Andrews staff (Prof Simon Dobson and Dr Juan Ye), as well as with the other SAPERE consortium partners. An interest in one or more of the fields of adaptive systems, pervasive computing, sensor-driven systems, uncertain reasoning and software engineering would be desirable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The studentship is funded for three years, including a stipend and all tuition fees. Please note that the conditions of funding restrict this opportunity to applicants who are nationals of an EU/EEA country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of St Andrews is the oldest university in Scotland (founded around 1410) and the third-oldest in the English-speaking world. Situated in a small town on the east coast of Scotland, it has a student population of around 8000 and an active research programme in a wide range of disciplines across the sciences and humanities. It has been consistently ranked in the top-10 universities in the UK by a number of recent league table exercises, and has been described by the Sunday Times as "now firmly established as the leading multi-faculty alternative to Oxford and Cambridge."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The School of Computer Science had 60% of its staff rated at 4&lt;em&gt; ("world-leading in terms of originality, significance and rigour," the highest available) or 3&lt;/em&gt; in the most recent UK Research Assessment Exercise. The School's academic staffing consists of 22 academics and over 25 post-doctoral fellows. There are also around 150 undergraduate full-time equivalent students and 30 PhD students. To stimulate a dynamic high-quality research environment, the School's research strategy concentrates on three research groups, each incorporating a number of key research topics pursued independently and in collaboration. The three research groups work in the areas of Artificial Intelligence and Symbolic Computation, Networks and Distributed Systems, and Systems  Engineering. Each group attracts a large amount of external funding from both the traditional research grant agencies (EPSRC, EU, etc.) and from  companies such as SUN Microsystems, ICL, Data Connection, Microsoft and BAe. The School is also a leading member of &lt;a href="http://www.sicsa.ac.uk"&gt;SICSA&lt;/a&gt;, a research alliance of leading computer science Schools across Scotland, with members of the School leading a number of core strategic activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the School, the Networks and Distributed Systems group is a world-class research centre, not only for software artefacts such as programming languages, object stores and operating systems but also in adaptive, pervasive and autonomic systems engineering and in the composition technologies used in such large-scale distributed systems such as peer-to-peer overlay mechanisms, distributed mediation, distributed termination and distributed garbage collection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Application&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To apply, please send a CV and statement of research interests by email to Prof Simon Dobson (&lt;a href="mailto:sd@cs.st-andrews.ac.uk"&gt;sd@cs.st-andrews.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;), to whom informal inquiries can also be directed. The closing date for applications is 11 October 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>adaptive systems</category><category>Blog</category><category>jobs</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2010/09/09/sapere-phd/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2010 14:09:41 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>