<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about medicine)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/medicine.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:simon.dobson@computer.org"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 15:47:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Fully-funded PhD scholarship available</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2015/02/03/phd-cs-med/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have a fully-funded PhD scholarship available, tenable from September 2015, to work on data science in medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;University of St Andrews&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;School of Computer Science&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;School of Medicine&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funded PhD studentship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Schools of Computer Science and Medicine are looking to recruit a talented student to work on improving clinical trials of tuberculosis and other conditions using computational techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TB and related conditions are extremely costly in human and financial terms, and trials of new drugs and therapies are complicated by difficult environmental conditions and other factors. Improvements to the trials process will potentially translate directly into improved interventions, and so will help save lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We seek to apply data-driven techniques to the design, analysis, and management of such trials. These techniques might include complex networks, computational epidemiology, machine learning, Bayesian analysis, and other cutting-edge approaches to data analytics. The ideal candidate will have an interest in data science applied to medical and biological problems, and an enthusiasm for working as part of a challenging multi-disciplinary project within St Andrews' new &lt;a href="http://www.idir.st-andrews.ac.uk" target="_blank"&gt;Institute for Data-Intensive Research (IDIR)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The studentship will be held jointly between the two Schools, with supervisors from Computer Science (Prof Simon Dobson, &lt;a href="https://risweb.st-andrews.ac.uk/portal/en/persons/tom-kelsey%28289c44af-c861-4f85-a604-6be4e43855f1%29.html" target="_blank"&gt;Dr Tom Kelsey&lt;/a&gt;) and Medicine (&lt;a href="https://risweb.st-andrews.ac.uk/portal/da/persons/stephen-henry-gillespie%28ce4435fa-8cee-4e25-92fe-30f18dfec159%29.html" target="_blank"&gt;Prof Stephen Gillespie&lt;/a&gt;, Dr Ruth Bowness).  We offer a stimulating and supportive environment within a small and intimate university in a beautiful setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scholarship is fully funded to cover tuition fees and stipend for a registration period normally expected to be three-and-a-half years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Informal inquiries can be made in the first instance to &lt;a href="mailto:simon.dobson@st-andrews.ac.uk"&gt;Prof Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt;. Applications will be considered until mid-March.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>data science</category><category>medicine</category><category>phd</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2015/02/03/phd-cs-med/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2015 12:12:18 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>