<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about networking)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/networking.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 19:17:42 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Call for papers on managing federated networks</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2010/10/25/manfed-cf/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;We are seeking papers on the issues involved in managing federations of systems, those that cross enterprise boundaries.

&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.manfed.com"&gt;ManFED.COM 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="blog-description"&gt;1st IFIP/IEEE Workshop on Managing Federations and Cooperative Management&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="manfed-location-header"&gt;Co-located with IM 2011 in Dublin, Ireland.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="manfed-date-header"&gt;May 23, 2011&lt;/div&gt;
Management approaches that can be applied across  organisational boundaries are increasingly important in a wide range of  application areas. These range from algorithmic approaches which adapt  to the observed behaviour of third-party systems, based on  game-theoretic approaches or other predictive models, to explicit  organisational federations which adopt coherent solutions and management  models to facilitate interoperability among multiple independent  organisations.

There are a number of significant, common, complex issues which must  be addressed in all technologies and applications that involve federated  organisations – how to enable secure governance in the absence of a  single, central point of authority; how to achieve semantic  interoperability in the absence of common schema; how to provide  effective access control in the absence of common user and role models;  how to provide analytics and support for effective decision making;  how  to adapt to environments that can be highly dynamic as well as highly  heterogeneous; how to construct and maintain a common inter-domain  governance model in the presence of highly diverse local governance  infrastructures .

This workshop will, for the first time, bring together researchers  from a broad array of application and technical areas who are concerned  with cross-domain management. It will draw out common themes, problems  and issues encountered, and the solutions being designed to deal with  the problems of managing information systems that span autonomous  domains. It will aim to provide the basis for a common understanding and  common approaches to inter-domain management and governance that  synthesises the insights and best of breed solutions being developed in  the diverse areas in which these problems are encountered.
&lt;h5&gt;TOPICS TO BE ADDRESSED, BUT NOT LIMITED TO:&lt;/h5&gt;
Cross Domain and Federated Management Issues in the following areas:
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Governance mechanisms for federated environments, e.g. Policy Based Management&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Collaborative management, algorithmic adaptation, game theoretic approaches, predictive modeling.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Modelling cross-domain relationships, i.e. Information models, formal specifications, languages for federation&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Distributed trust management and federated security systems&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Data federation&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Semantic technologies, semantic mapping and linked data&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Information security in federated environments&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Cloud &amp;amp; grid computing management&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Software engineering for federated systems, i.e. tool chains, design by contract, model driven engineering and design patterns&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Model driven approaches for the generation of adaptive inter-domain relationships&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Adaptive analytics for the support of managing complex, dynamic multi-domain solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;PAPER SUBMISSION&lt;/h5&gt;
Authors are invited to submit full papers (8 pages) describing the  original work. All manuscripts must be written in English and should be  prepared in IEEE style. All submitted papers will be reviewed by the  ManFed.CoM Technical Program Committee.

For the review, all the papers should be submitted in PDF format through the ManFed.Com page on the JEMS system (&lt;a href="https://jems.sbc.org.br/manfed2011"&gt;https://jems.sbc.org.br/manfed2011&lt;/a&gt;), filling every item and uploading the respective papers.

The contributed papers, after being reviewed and accepted by  ManFed.CoM referees, will be published in the Conference Proceedings  that will be included in the IEEE Conference Publication of IM 2011 and  will be available on IEEE Xplore. The papers will also be indexed and  abstracted by several databases such as INSPEC, Engineering Index (EI),  SCOPUS, Conference Proceedings Citation Index (CPCI), etc.

Finally, the organizing committee are currently in discussions with  the editors of leading network and service management journals regarding  the publication of a special issue to include best submissions from the  workshop.
&lt;h5&gt;DEADLINES FOR PAPERS&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Full Paper Submission: 15th December 2010 (midnight GMT)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Acceptance Notification: 30th January 2011 (midnight GMT)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Camera-Ready Manuscripts Due: 15th February 2011 (midnight GMT)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;TECHNICAL CO-CHAIRS&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Kevin Feeney, TCD&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Joel Fleck, HP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;GENERAL CO-CHAIRS&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Rolf Stadler, KTH&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Brendan Jennings, TSSG&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;FURTHER INFORMATION&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;ManFed.Com submissions: &lt;a href="https://jems.sbc.org.br/manfed2011"&gt;https://jems.sbc.org.br/manfed2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;IM 2011 website: &lt;a href="http://www.ieee-im.org/"&gt;http://www.ieee-im.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>conference</category><category>networking</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2010/10/25/manfed-cf/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2010 12:03:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Call for panels in integrated network management</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2010/09/24/im11-panels/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;We're looking for expert panels to be run at the IFIP/IEEE International Symposium on Integrated Network Management in Dublin in May 2011.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IFIP/IEEE International Symposium on Integrated Network Management (IM 2011)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
Dublin, Ireland, 23-27 May 2011
&lt;a href="http://www.ieee-im.org/"&gt;http://www.ieee-im.org/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Call for panels&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
IM is one of the premier venues in network management, providing a forum for discussing a broad range of issues relating to network structure, services, optimisation, adaptation and management. This year's symposium has a special emphasis on effective and energy-efficient design, deployment and management of current and future networks and services.
We are seeking proposals for expert discussion panels to stimulate and inform the audience as to the current "hot topics" within network management. An ideal panel will bring the audience into a discussion prompted by position statements from the panel members, taking account of both academic and industrial viewpoints. We are interested in panels on all aspects of network management, especially those related to the theme of energy awareness and those discussing the wider aspects of networks and network management. This would include the following topics, amongst others:
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Multi-transport and multi-media networks&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Network adaptation and optimisation&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Co-managing performance and energy&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The uses and abuses of sensor networks&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The science of service design and implementation&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Programming network management strategies&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Tools and techniques for network management&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Socio-technical integration of networks&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Energy-efficiency vs equality of access&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Network-aware cloud computing&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The future of autonomic management&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Coping with data obesity&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Managing the next-generation internet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to propose a panel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
Please send a brief (1-page) proposal to the panel chairs, &lt;a href="mailto:sd@cs.st-andrews.ac.uk"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="mailto:gp.parr@ulster.ac.uk"&gt;Gerard Parr&lt;/a&gt;. Your proposal should indicate the  relevance of the panel to the broad audience of IM, and include the names of proposed panel members.
&lt;h3&gt;Important dates&lt;/h3&gt;
Submission of panel proposals: 20 October 2010
Notifications of acceptance: mid-November 2010
Conference dates: 23-27 May 2011</description><category>conference</category><category>internet</category><category>ireland</category><category>networking</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2010/09/24/im11-panels/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 24 Sep 2010 09:32:59 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>