<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about pervasive systems)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/pervasive-systems.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:simon.dobson@computer.org"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 15:47:05 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Doctoral Symposium on Foundations and Applications of Self-* Systems (FAS*W)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2016/06/02/fasw/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a doctoral symposium at the SASO  conference this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Call For Doctoral Symposium Submissions Doctoral Symposium on Foundations and Applications of Self-&lt;em&gt; Systems (FAS&lt;/em&gt;W)&lt;/h3&gt;
Augsburg, Germany, September 12 &amp;amp; 16, 2016
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EXTENDED DEADLINES:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Submission due: June 12, 2016
Paper Submission due: June 20, 2016
&lt;a class="moz-txt-link-freetext" href="http://fasstar2016.informatik.uni-augsburg.de/"&gt;http://fasstar2016.informatik.uni-augsburg.de/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a class="moz-txt-link-freetext" href="http://iccac2016.se.rit.edu/"&gt;http://iccac2016.se.rit.edu/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="moz-txt-link-freetext" href="http://uni-augsburg.de/saso2016"&gt;http://uni-augsburg.de/saso2016
&lt;/a&gt;@SASO2016Conf&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foundations and Applications of Self&lt;em&gt; Systems (FAS&lt;/em&gt;) is the umbrella for two closely related but independent conferences, the International Conference on Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Systems (SASO) and the International Conference on Cloud and Autonomic Computing (ICCAC). The FAS&lt;em&gt; Doctoral Symposium provides an international forum for PhD Students working in research areas addressed by FAS&lt;/em&gt;. In this forum, PhD students will get unique opportunities to subject their research to the scrutiny of external experts, gain experience in the presentation of research, connect to peers and experts addressing similar problems, and get advice from a panel of internationally leading researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different from the technical tracks of the conference, the FAS* Doctoral Symposium focuses on the specific needs of young researchers at the beginning of their career. As such, particular emphasis will be placed on a critical and constructive feedback that shall help participants to successfully conclude their PhD studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PhD students working in any area addressed by the FAS&lt;em&gt; conferences are invited to submit a Doctoral Symposium paper in which they describe the key motivation and objectives of their research project, and reflect on the methodology as well as the current status of their PhD studies. Complementing the thematic focus of FAS&lt;/em&gt;, we particularly solicit contributions in the following areas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Engineering of self-organizing and self-adaptive systems.&lt;/em&gt; We solicit theoretical and applied works addressing fundamental principles underlying self-organizing systems, as well as methods that allow to quantify, model and reproduce the self-&lt;em&gt; characteristics of complex systems in biological, social, physical and technical systems. Examples include mechanisms underlying distributed decision- making and collective intelligence, software engineering challenges in self-adaptive systems, as well as general application of self-&lt;/em&gt; principles in the engineering of technical systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Complex Cyber-physical and socio-technical systems.&lt;/em&gt; We welcome contributions that apply self-* principles to address challenges in the design of complex cyber- physical and socio-technical systems. Particular examples include smart grid infrastructures, sensor networks, opportunistic networking scenarios, as well as large-scale social information systems. Works addressing challenges such as the security, privacy and anonymity of users, or mechanisms to prevent censorship, manipulation or unfairness in socio-technical systems are especially welcome. We further solicit works on socio- technical and socio-economic challenges in P2P systems, such as the design of incentive, trust and reputation mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Self-&lt;em&gt; approaches in Massive-Scale Decentralized Systems.&lt;/em&gt; Works in this area use self-&lt;/em&gt; approaches to address challenges in the design and operation of massive scale decentralized systems. Examples include Peer-to-Peer technologies, as well as overlay topology management schemes. We are further interested in decentralized data mining and machine learning approaches, as well as decentralized approaches to monitor, model and adapt distributed systems. Works using self-* principles to address the inherent challenges in the design of massive-scale systems with unreliable and heterogeneous are of particular interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Autonomic Computing.&lt;/em&gt; Systems Here we are interested in all works addressing the self-configuration, self-optimization and self-adaptation of cloud computing services, data centers and general distributed computing systems. Examples for questions addressed in this area include the monitoring and modeling of cloud services, the design of efficient resource allocation mechanisms, the application of data mining and machine learning techniques to analyze and predict the behavior of technical systems, as well as the characterization of distributed computing workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Application of Self-&lt;em&gt; in Robotics and Spatial Computing.&lt;/em&gt; Finally, we welcome contributions using self-&lt;/em&gt; principles in the areas of robotics, swarm robotics and spatial computing. Here, examples for works of interest include environmental modeling and perception, machine vision, and self-adaptation mechanisms in robotics, distributed coordination and collective intelligence in multi- robot systems, as well as novel paradigms for the programming of autonomous, spatially distributed entities.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Submission Instructions&lt;/h4&gt;
Submissions should have a length of max. six pages and be formatted according to the IEEE Computer Society Press proceedings style guide. Authors should submit their papers using the EasyChair installation of the main conference, which is available at:
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="moz-txt-link-freetext" href="https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=saso2016"&gt;https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=saso2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that only single-author submissions are accepted, which focus on the topic of the doctoral work. The name of the supervisor (« supervised by ... ») should be clearly marked below the author’s name in the paper. Submissions should further adhere to the following structure:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Motivation: motivate the open problem that you want to address and briefly summarize existing approaches along with their deficiencies.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Objectives: describe the key objectives of your PhD project and argue how achieving them will solve the open problem outlined in the motivation.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Methodology: outline what methodology you will adopt to meet the objectives of your project. Clearly state on what existing works your work will build.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Research Plan: describe what preliminary results – if any – you have already achieved and summarize your plans for future work. Please add a rough schedule that allows to judge whether your research plan is feasible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
Authors of accepted papers shall prepare a final, camera ready version of the paper, taking into account all feedback from reviewers, and formatted according to the IEEE Computer Society Press proceedings style guide. Doctoral Symposium papers will be advertised in the final program, and will be submitted to IEEE Xplore as part of the SASO proceedings. Papers will also be made available in the IEEE Digital Library.
&lt;h4&gt;Review Process&lt;/h4&gt;
Each submission will be reviewed by at least two Doctoral Symposium experts (see list below) that cover the different areas of interest of the conference. Submissions will be evaluated based on their relevance to FAS*, the motivation and quality of the proposed research, as well as the suitability of the chosen methodology.
&lt;p&gt;Authors of accepted papers will have different opportunities to present their project at the conference. Besides a full presentation during the PhD Symposium session, an “Elevator Pitch Session” will be organized during the main conference, where authors get the chance to briefly showcase their research. In addition, the Best Doctoral Symposium paper will be selected and the award will be presented during the main conference. Finally, selected authors will have the additional chance to present their work via a poster in the poster session of the main conference.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Invited Talk&lt;/h4&gt;
To be announced
&lt;h4&gt;Doctoral Symposium Experts&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Ozalp Babaoglu – University of Bologna, IT&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Jacob Beal – BBN Technologies, USA&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Kurt Geihs – Universitaet Kassel, DE&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Tom Holvoet – KU Leuven, BE&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Manish Parashar – Rutgers University, USA&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Jeremy Pitt – Imperial College London, UK&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Mark Jelasity – University of Szeged, HU&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Burkhard Stiller – University of Zurich, CH&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Giuseppe Valetto – Fondazione Bruno Kessler, Trento, IT&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Salim Hariri – University of Arizona, USA&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Simon Dobson – University of St Andrews, Scotland, UK&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Antonio Bucchiarone - Fondazione Bruno Kessler, Trento, IT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Important Dates (Extended)&lt;/h4&gt;
Abstract Submission due (extended): June 12, 2016
Paper Submission due (extended): June 20, 2016
Notifications due: July 10, 2016
Camera ready version due: July 24, 2016
Conference date: September 12-16, 2016
&lt;h4&gt;Contact Information&lt;/h4&gt;
For any further information, please contact the Doctoral Symposium chairs:
&lt;p&gt;Pradeep Murukannaiah Department of Computer Science North Carolina State University Raleigh, NC, 27606, USA
&lt;a class="moz-txt-link-abbreviated" href="mailto:pmuruka@ncsu.edu"&gt;pmuruka@ncsu.edu&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="moz-txt-link-freetext" href="http://www4.ncsu.edu/%7Epmuruka/"&gt;http://www4.ncsu.edu/~pmuruka/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Ingo Scholtes Chair of Systems Design ETH Zurich CH-8092 Zurich Switzerland
&lt;a class="moz-txt-link-abbreviated" href="mailto:ischoltes@ethz.ch"&gt;ischoltes@ethz.ch&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="moz-txt-link-freetext" href="http://www.ingoscholtes.net"&gt;http://www.ingoscholtes.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>cfp</category><category>conference</category><category>doctoral symposium</category><category>pervasive systems</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2016/06/02/fasw/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2016 15:56:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>CfP: Spatial and Collective Awareness workshop at SASO'15</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2015/06/17/spatial-collective-awareness/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first workshop on Spatial Awareness is being held in Boston in September as part of the &lt;a href="http://saso2015.mit.edu/" target="_blank"&gt;SASO conference&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;First International Workshop on Spatial and COllective PErvasive Computing Systems (SCOPES) Workshop&lt;/h3&gt;
Co-located with IEEE SASO 2015, located at MIT, Cambridge, USA
&lt;p&gt;September 21, 2015&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="moz-txt-link-freetext" href="http://www.spatial-computing.org/scopes"&gt;http://www.spatial-computing.org/scopes&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Overview&lt;/h4&gt;
This workshop aims at combining three distinct, yet closely related areas of research, which will likely together play a major role in producing the key technical results needed to develop large-scale adaptive distributed systems of future networked scenarios.
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Spatial computing: Spatial computing systems are systems of individual entities, typically situated in a physical environment, in which the “functional goals” of the system are generally defined in terms of the system's spatial structure. Typically, such systems are developed following a self-organisation approach, making spatial patterns arise by emergence.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Collective adaptive systems: Collective computing systems are systems of tightly entangled components, achieving an overall goal through widespread cooperation, typically relying on self-adaptation techniques and collective/social intelligence.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Pervasive computing: Pervasive computing systems and the “Internet of Things” deal with current and emerging scenarios in which humans, sensors, mobile, and embedded devices engage in complex interactions in a shared environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
The goal of this workshop is to foster the creation of general-purpose solutions for supporting the development of these kinds of systems, particularly as regards generalizable techniques and architectures. Topics of interest include:
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Foundational models of spatially embedded collective systems, exhibiting resilience, robustness and scalability properties as required by emerging pervasive computing scenarios.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Tools and tool-chains targeting large-scale situated systems: programming or specification languages, compilers and proof-checking techniques, simulators, tools for property verification, libraries and APIs, supporting platforms, whole infrastructures.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Innovative methods and techniques for system development, including design patterns, software methodologies, best practices, and practical experience reports.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Applications contexts and scenarios of general interest to foster the identification of new problems and solutions, taking inspiration from cyber-physical systems, the Internet of things, sensor networks, smart-cities, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Paper submission&lt;/h4&gt;
Papers should present original work and be no longer than 6 pages in the standard IEEE two-column format. All manuscripts should be submitted in PDF form through the submissions system for SCOPES at EasyChair. Papers will be peer reviewed on the basis of originality, readability, relevance to themes, soundness, and overall quality. Workshop proceedings will be published on IEEE Xplore in parallel with the main conference proceedings. Post-proceedings publication in a journal is planned. Questions should be addressed to &lt;a class="moz-txt-link-abbreviated" href="mailto:saso.scopes2015@easychair.org"&gt;saso.scopes2015@easychair.org&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;h4&gt;Important Dates&lt;/h4&gt;
Workshop paper submission: July 11, 2015
Notification of accepted papers: July 31, 2015
Camera-ready paper deadline: August 10, 2015
Workshop at SASO: September 21, 2015
&lt;h4&gt;Organisers&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Dr. Jacob Beal (Raytheon BBN Technologies, USA)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Prof. Jane Hillson (University of Edinburgh, UK)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Dr. Mirko Viroli (University of Bologna, Italy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Program Committee&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Ezio Bartocci, TU Wien, Austria&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Spring Berman, Arizona State University, USA&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Luca Bortolussi, University of Trieste, Italy&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Sven Brueckner, Axon Connected LLC, USA&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Siobhan Clarke, Trinity College Dublin, IE&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Daniel Coore, University of the West Indies&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Jamaica Ferruccio Damiani, Università di Torino, Italy&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Rocco De Nicola, IMT - Institute for Advanced Studies Lucca, Italy&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Giovanna Di Marzo Serugendo, University of Geneve, Switzerland&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Ada Diaconescu, Telecom ParisTech, CNRS LTCI, France&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Simon Dobson, University of St Andrews, UK&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Matt Duckham, University of Melbourne, Australia&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Stefan Dulman, CWI, Netherlands&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Schahram Dustdar, TU Wien, Austria&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Eva Kühn, Vienna University of Technology, Austria&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Mieke Massink, CNR-ISTI, Italy&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Mirco Musolesi, University College London UK&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Silvia Nittel, University of Maine, USA&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Antoine Spicher, LACL University Paris Est Creteil, France&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Katia Sycara, Carnegie Mellon University, USA&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Christof Teuscher, Portland State University, USA&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Martin Wirsing, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universitaet Muenchen, Germany&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Franco Zambonelli, University of Modena and Reggio Emilia, Italy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cfp</category><category>conference</category><category>pervasive systems</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2015/06/17/spatial-collective-awareness/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2015 10:00:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Research fellowships available in Dublin</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2014/05/16/research-fellowships/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two post-doctoral positions in smart cities now available at Trinity College Dublin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research Fellowships in Autonomic Service-Oriented Computing for Smart Cities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applications are invited for two Postdoctoral Research Fellowships at &lt;a href="http://www.dsg.cs.tcd.ie/" target="_blank"&gt;Trinity College Dublin’s Distributed Systems Group&lt;/a&gt; to investigate the provision of a new service-oriented computing infrastructure that provides demand-based composition of software services interacting with a city-wide, dynamic network infrastructure. The project will investigate autonomic adaptation of services and infrastructure, ensuring resilient service provision within an integrated, city-wide system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applicants should have a Ph.D. in Computer Science, Computer Engineering or a closely-related discipline and strong C++/C#/Java development skills. Experience with autonomic computing, service-oriented middleware, and/or smart city technologies is desirable as are strong mathematical skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is supported by Science Foundation Ireland under the Principal Investigator programme between 2014-2018 and will be conducted in collaboration with Cork Institute of Technology, NUI Maynooth, IBM Smarter Cities Research Centre, Intel Intelligent Cities Lab, EMC2 Research Europe, and Arup.  The position is tenable from September 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please apply by email to &lt;a href="mailto:Siobhan.Clarke@scss.tcd.ie"&gt;Siobhan.Clarke@scss.tcd.ie&lt;/a&gt; quoting “Smart Cities Fellowship” in the subject line. Applications should include a curriculum vitae, in PDF format, giving full details of qualifications and experience, together with the names of two referees. The closing date for applications is the 20th June, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trinity College is an equal opportunities employer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>ireland</category><category>jobs</category><category>pervasive systems</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2014/05/16/research-fellowships/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2014 12:39:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Studentship available in Newcastle upon Tyne</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2013/03/07/studentship/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My colleagues in Newcastle (where I did my first degree) have an MRes/PhD position available in computational behaviour analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with colleagues from Agriculture, the &lt;a href="http://www.ncl.ac.uk/computing/" target="_blank"&gt;School of Computing Science in Newcastle&lt;/a&gt; have recently been active in the field of computational behaviour analysis in livestock animals. They have a small grant on which we are currently doing some  pilot work related to food safety and animal wellbeing, which has now given rise to funding for an integrated MRes / PhD studentship to work in this field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group wants to work on a system for automatic tracking of farm pigs (indoor) and on modelling their behaviour (as individuals and in the group) with the goal of early detection of changes therein that might be linked to  certain diseases. The project involves some very strong partners from and connections to agriculture and access to farms and industry.  The topic is extremely relevant for the UK industry and has wider societal impact (food safety, animal welfare). They are looking for strong CS candidates with a background in machine learning, signal processing, or computer vision, and an interest in working in an multi-disciplinary team on a challenging and very interesting topic with substantial societal and economic relevance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The funding covers four years of fees and maintenance. UK home  students (and EU citizens who have been residents for at least three years) are eligible for the full funding, EU students essentially for 50%. Throughout the first year the student will be enrolled into an MRes program with courses and time to get familiar with the topic, which is a fantastic opportunity for students to obtain an interdisciplinary skill-set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More details can be found &lt;a href="http://www.ncl.ac.uk/postgraduate/funding/search/list/CS043"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Application deadline is the 5th April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>pervasive systems</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2013/03/07/studentship/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2013 16:49:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What's new for awareness researchers?: an interview</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2012/09/27/awareness/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was interviewed at &lt;a href="http://saso2012.univ-lyon1.fr/" target="_blank"&gt;SASO&lt;/a&gt; as part of collecting what people thought were the ways forward and important topics for pervasive systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.aware-project.eu" target="_blank"&gt;Aware project&lt;/a&gt; co-ordinates between a collection of EU projects into self-awareness and adaptive systems. As part of its remit it collects the evolving opinions of the research community to try to decide where the research is leading, and in particular what are the emerging questions that might be supported by future EU initiatives. Interviewing researchers is a new departure that I haven't seen before, and they &lt;a href="http://www.aware-project.eu/category/research-agenda-2/video-opinions/" target="_blank"&gt;interviewed several people with diverse backgrounds&lt;/a&gt; to get a broad sweep of the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I focused on how little we understand how to model what people actually do in the course of their lives, and consequently how hard it is to explain these processes to computers and build computer-mediated analysis and support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Sorry about the noise in the background, we were standing in a corridor....)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>pervasive systems</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2012/09/27/awareness/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2012 07:00:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>An issue for smart grids</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/09/09/smart-grids/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unbeknown to her -- until she reads this, anyway -- the other day my mother trashed an idea that's been a cornerstone of a lot of research on smart grids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK the fire services often send people around to check people's smoke alarms and the like. Not usually firemen &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;, but information providers who might reasonably be described as the propaganda department of the fire service, intent on giving advice on how not to burn to death. They also change batteries. Pretty useful public service, all told.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, my mother lives in Cheshire, and recently had a visit from two such anti-fire propagandists.They did the usual useful things, but also got talking about the various risk factors one can avoid beyond the usual ones of having a smoke alarm and not searching for gas leaks with a cigarette lighter. The conversation turned to the subject of appliances, and they revealed that the most dangerous appliances from a fire-causing perspective are washing machines. In fact, they said, the Cheshire fire service gets called to more washing-machine fires than &lt;em&gt;any other kind&lt;/em&gt; of domestic fire. (I don't know if that includes hoaxes, which are a major problem.) Since they have in common (a) lots of current and (b) water, I would guess that dishwashers are a similar problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So their advice was never to run a washing machine or dishwasher overnight or when in bed, as the chances of a fire are relatively high. "Relatively high" probably still means low on any meaningful  scale, but it makes sense to minimise even small hazards when the costs are potentially to catastrophic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mum related this to me to encourage me also not to run appliances at night. But of course this has research consequences as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smart grids are the application of information technology to the provision and management of electricity and (to a lesser extent) gas. The idea is that the application of data science can provide better models of how people use their power, and can allow the grid operators and power generators to schedule and provision their supplies more accurately. It usually involves more detailed monitoring of electricity usage, for example using an internet-connected smart meter to log and return the power usage profile instead of just aggregated power usage for billing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is getting more and more common because of the rise in renewable energy. Most countries have feed-in tariffs for the grid that power generators have to pay. The scheme is usually some variant of the following: at every accounting period (say three hours), each generator  has to present an estimate of the power it will generate in the &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; several accounting periods (say three).  So using these numbers, every three hours an electricity generator has to say how much power it will inject into the grid in the next nine hours. There's a complementary tariff scheme for aggregate consumers (not individuals), and taken together these allow the grid operators to balance supply and demand. The important point is that this exercise has real and quantifiable financial costs: generators are charged if they over- or under-supply by more than an agreed margin of error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this is fine if you run a gas-, oil- or nuclear-powered power station. However, if you run a wind farm or a tidal barrage, it's rather more tricky, since you don't know with any accuracy how much power you'll generate: it depends on circumstances outwith your control. (I did some work for a company making control systems for wind farms, and one of their major issues was power prediction.) The tariffs can be a show-stopper, and can cause a lot of renewable-energy generators to run significantly below capacity just to hedge their tariff risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other side of smart grids is to manage demand. It's well-known that demand is spiky, for example leaping a half-time in a popular televised football match as everybody puts the kettle on. A major goal of smart grids is to smooth-out demand, and one of the ways to do this is to identify power loads than can be time-shifted: they are relatively insensitive to when they occur, and so can be moved so that they occur at times when the aggregate power demand is less. In a domestic setting, some kinds of storage heating work like this and can create and store heat during off-peak hours (overnight). Lights and television can't be time-shifted as they're needed at particular times. So what are the major power loads, other than storage heating, in domestic settings that can apparently be time-shifted?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Washing machines and dishwashers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except we now know that time-shifting them to overnight running runs exactly counter to fire service advice as it increases the dangers of domestic fires. So one of the major strategies for smart grid demand management would, if widely deployed, potentially cause significant losses, of property and even lives. Reducing energy bills will (in time) increase the insurance premiums for anyone allowing time-shifting of their main appliances. In other words, while these risks exist, its a non-starter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some ways this is a good thing: good to learn about now, anyway, before too much investment. There are a lot of things that could be done to ameliorate the risks, for example designing machines explicitly designed for time-shifted operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think a more pertinent observation is the holistic nature of this kind of pervasive computing system. You can't treat &lt;em&gt;any one element&lt;/em&gt; in isolation, as they all interact with each other. It's as though pervasive computing breaks the normal way we think of computing systems as being built from independent components. In pervasive computing the composition operators are non-linear: two independently-correct components or solutions do not always compose to form one that is also correct. This has major implications for design and analysis, as well as for engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks, mum!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>pervasive systems</category><category>sensor networks</category><category>smart grid</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/09/09/smart-grids/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2011 06:30:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Pervasive healthcare</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/06/03/pervasive-healthcare/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This week's piece of shameless self-promotion: a book chapter on how pervasive computing and social media can change long-term healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My colleague &lt;a href="http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/~aquigley/" target="_blank"&gt;Aaron Quigley&lt;/a&gt; and I were asked to contribute a chapter to a book put together by &lt;a href="http://is.gd/8YvE2j" target="_blank"&gt;Jeremy Pitt&lt;/a&gt; as part of &lt;a href="http://www.perada.eu/" target="_blank"&gt;PerAda&lt;/a&gt;, the EU network of excellence in pervasive systems. We were asked to think about how pervasive computing and social media could change healthcare. This is something quite close to both our hearts -- Aaron perhaps more so than me -- as it's one of the most dramatic examples of how pervasive computing can really make an impact on society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of examples of projects that attempt to provide high-tech solutions to the issues of independent living-- some of which we've been closely involved with. For this work, though, we &lt;a href="http://www.thispervasiveday.com/healthcare-pervasive-world-simon-dobson-aaron-quigley.html" target="_blank"&gt;suggest&lt;/a&gt; that one of the most cost-effective contributions that technology can make might actually be centred around social media. Isolation really is a killer, in a literal sense. A lot of research has indicated that social isolation is a massive risk factor in both physiological and psychological illnesses, and this is something that's likely to get worse as populations age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media can help address this, especially in an age when older people have circles of older friends, and where these friends and family can be far more geographically dispersed than in former times. This isn't to suggest that Twitter and Facebook are the cures of any social ills, but rather that the services they might evolve into could be of enormous utility for older people. Not only do they provide traffic between people, they can be mined to determine whether users' activities are changing over time, &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2011/03/situations/" target="_blank"&gt;identify situations that can be supported&lt;/a&gt;, and so provide unintrusive medical feedback -- as well as opening-up massive issues of privacy and surveillance. While today's older generation are perhaps not fully engaged with social media, future generations undoubtedly will be, and it's something to be encouraged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other authors -- some of them leading names in the various aspects of pervasive systems -- have contributed chapters about implicit interaction, privacy, trust, brain interfaces, power management, sustainability, and a range of other topics in accessible form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book has a &lt;a href="http://www.thispervasiveday.com/" target="_blank"&gt;web site&lt;/a&gt; (of course), and is available for &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/This-Pervasive-Day-Potential-Computing/dp/1848167482" target="_blank"&gt;pre-order on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks to Jeremy for putting this together: it's been a great opportunity to think more broadly than we often get to do as research scientists, and see how our work might help make the world more liveable-in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>book</category><category>healthcare</category><category>pervasive systems</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/06/03/pervasive-healthcare/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2011 13:00:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Some data is just too valuable</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/04/27/valuable/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div id="heystaks_preview" style="width: 100%;height: 100%"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
The recent furore over tracking mobile phones is a warning of what happens when sensor data goes too public.
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past week first &lt;a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748703983704576277101723453610.html#ixzz1KD2hkiTa"&gt;Apple&lt;/a&gt; and then &lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2011/apr/21/android-phones-record-user-locations"&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt; have been caught capturing location traces from users' phones without their knowledge or consent. The exposure has been replete with denials and nuanced responses -- and indeed a &lt;a href="http://www.macrumors.com/2011/04/25/steve-jobs-on-ios-location-issue-we-dont-track-anyone/"&gt;not-so-nuanced response purportedly from Steve Jobs&lt;/a&gt;. This is almost certain to end up in court, especially in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The details, both technical and managerial who-knew-what, are still unclear. It's just about possible that one or both cases were caused by over-enthusiastic engineers without management approval, and we should of course suspend judgment until more details emerge. We can, however, explore possible motives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Apple case involves tracking a phone over a protracted period of time and storing the resulting trace as GPS co-ordinates in an unencrypted file. This is invisible to "normal" users, but is visible when a phone has been "jailbroken," and is sync'ed with the user's desktop. As soon as the story broke there was an application available for Macs to overlay the trace onto a map. We did this with a colleague's phone, and the trace goes back around a year. In places it's surprisingly accurate; in others is shows clear signs of distortion and location artifacts. Apparently Google Android performs similar tracking, but over shorter periods and with the results stored less openly. It's not quite clear whether the tracks recorded in either handset are forwarded back to their respective mother-ships, but that's certainly a risk. In the Apple case, traces are collected even if location-based services have been switched off at the application level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has to be said that this whole affair is something of a disaster, both for the companies concerned and for location-based and pervasive services in general. What the fall-out will be is unclear: will people move back to "dumb" phones to protect their privacy? Experience suggests not: the convenience is too great, and many people will conclude that the loss of privacy they've experienced, though unacceptable &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;, is insignificant compared to the overall benefits of smartphones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, if one were being particularly conspiracy-minded one might suspect that that the whole affair is a set-up. Management (one might argue) must have known that they'd be found out, and so made sure that the tracking they were performing was  benign (no transmission back to base) so that, when the story broke, people would be momentarily offended but afterwards would be inured to the idea of their phones tracking their locations (it happened before and had no bad consequences, so why worry about it?) &lt;em&gt;even if&lt;/em&gt; those traces were later pooled centrally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To a company, some personal data is so valuable that it's worth risking &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; to collect it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason location traces are important has nothing to do with the exposure of the occasional adulterer or criminal, and everything to do with profiling and advertising. &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2010/03/both-ends-of-the-data-intensive-spectrum/"&gt;Big data isn't just lots of small data collected together&lt;/a&gt;: it's qualitatively different and allows very different operations to be performed. A smartphone is a perfect personal-data-collection platform, being ubiquitous, always-on and increasingly used to integrate its owner's everyday life. The Holy Grail of mobile e-commerce is to be able to offer advertisements to people just at the moment when the products being advertised are at their most valuable. Doing this requires advertisers to profile people's activities and interests and respond to subtle cues in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine what a trace of my every movement does. It can show, to first order, how often I travel (and therefore my annual travel spend), what I see, and how I see it. Combined with other information like my travel history, booking references and internet search history, it can show what I'm interested in and when I'm likely to be doing it to a surprisingly high accuracy. It can identify that I commute, my home and work locations, my commute times and other routines. If I travel with other smartphone users it can identify my friends and colleagues simply from proximity -- and that's before someone mines my social network explicitly using Facebook or LinkedIn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now consider what this profile is worth to an advertiser. Someone with access to it, and with access to the platform on which I browse the web, can inject advertisements tailored specifically to what I'm doing at any particular moment, and to what I may be doing in the future. It can offer distractions when I'm commuting, or offers for my next holiday before I leave, and group discounts if I persuade my friends to join in with some offer. Basically a location trace is &lt;em&gt;almost incalculably valuable&lt;/em&gt;: certainly worth an initial bout of injurious comment and lawsuits if it leads to getting hands legitimately on that kind of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With spam email one needs response rates in the fractions of percent to make a profit: with access to a detailed user profile one could get massively better responses and make a quite astonishing amount of money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Location tracing, like &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2011/03/disloyalty-cards/"&gt;loyalty cards&lt;/a&gt;, gains most of its value from information asymmetry: the data provider thinks that a few vouchers is good value for the data being given away, even though the actual value is enormously more than that. If you're not paying for the product, then you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; the product. It's not necessarily dystopian, may lead to better services, and may in  fact be the price we pay for keeping basic services free on the web  given the unexpected lack of many other business models. But it's not  something to be given away for free or without consideration of where and to whom  the benefits accrue, and what a properly constituted fair trade-off would be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>android</category><category>apple</category><category>Blog</category><category>pervasive systems</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/04/27/valuable/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2011 08:02:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The next challenges for situation recognition</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/03/23/situations/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a pervasive systems research community we're doing quite well at  automatically identifying simple things happening in the world. What is  the state of the art, and what are the next steps?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pervasive  computing is about letting computers see and respond to human activity.  In healthcare applications, for example, this might involve monitoring  an elderly person in their home and checking for signs of normality:  doors opening, the fridge being accessed, the toilet flushing, the  bedroom lights going on and off at the right times, and so on. A  collection of simple sensors can provide the raw observational data, and  we can monitor this stream of data for the "expected" behaviours. If we  don't see them -- no movement for over two hours during daytime, for  example -- then we can sound an alarm and alert a carer. Done correctly  this sort of system can literally be a life-saver, but also makes all  the difference for people with degenerative illnesses living in their  own homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The science behind these systems is often referred to as &lt;em&gt;activity&lt;/em&gt; and situation &lt;em&gt;recognition&lt;/em&gt;, both of which are forms of &lt;em&gt;context fusion&lt;/em&gt;.  To deal with these in the wrong order: context fusion is the ability to  take several streams of raw sensor (and other) data and use it to make  inferences; activity recognition is the detection of simple actions in  this data stream (lifting a cup, chopping with a knife); and situation  recognition is the semantic interpretation of a high-level process  (making tea, watching television, in a medical emergency). Having identified the situation we can then provide an appropriate &lt;em&gt;behaviour&lt;/em&gt; for the system, which might involve changing the way the space is  configured (dimming the lights, turning down the sound volume), providing information ("here's the recipe you chose for tonight") or taking some external action (calling for help). This sort of &lt;em&gt;context-aware behaviour&lt;/em&gt; is the overall goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The state of the art in context fusion uses some sort of  uncertain reasoning including machine learning and other techniques that  are broadly in the domain of artificial intelligence. These are  typically more complicated than the complex event processing techniques  used in financial systems and the like, because they have to deal with  significant noise in the data stream. (Ye, Dobson and McKeever.  &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/softcopy/situation-recognition-pmc11.pdf"&gt;Situation recognition techniques in pervasive computing: a review&lt;/a&gt;.  Pervasive and Mobile Computing. 2011.) The results are rather mixed,  with a typical technique (a naive Bayesian classifier, for example)  being able to identify some situations well and others far more poorly:  there doesn't seem to be a uniformly "good" technique yet. Despite this  we can now achieve 60-80% accuracy (by &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/F1_score"&gt;F-measure&lt;/a&gt;, a unified measure of  the "goodness" of a classification technique) on simple activities and  situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That sounds good, but the next steps are going to be far harder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To  see what the nest step is, consider that most of the systems explored  have been evaluated under laboratory conditions. These allow fine  control over the environment --&lt;em&gt; and that's precisely the problem&lt;/em&gt;. The next challenges for situation recognition come directly from the &lt;em&gt;loss&lt;/em&gt; of control of what's being observed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's break down what needs to happen. Firstly, we need to be able to &lt;em&gt;describe&lt;/em&gt; situations in a way that lets us capture human processes. This is easy  to do to another human but tricky to a computer: the precision with  which we need to express computational tasks gets in the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For  example we might describe the process of making lunch as retrieving the  bread from the cupboard, the cheese and butter from the fridge, a plate  from the rack, and then spreading the butter, cutting the cheese, and  assembling the sandwich. That's a good enough description for a human,  but most of the time isn't exactly what happens. One might retrieve the  elements in a different order, or start making the sandwich (get the  bread, spread the butter) only to remember that you forgot the filling,  and therefore go back to get the cheese, then re-start assembling the  sandwich, and so forth. The point is that this isn't programming: people  don't do what you expect them to do, and there are so many variations  to the basic process that they seem to defy capture -- although no human  observer would have the slightest difficulty in classifying what they  were seeing. A first challenge is therefore &lt;em&gt;a way of expressing the real-world processes and situations we want to recognise&lt;/em&gt; in a way that's robust to the things people actually do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Incidentally,  this way of thinking about situations shows that it's the dual of  traditional workflow. In a workflow system you specify a process and  force the human agents to comply; in a situation description the humans  do what they do and the computers try to keep up.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second  challenge is that, even when captured, situations don't occur in  isolation. We might define a second situation to control what happens  when the person answers the phone: quiet the TV and stereo, maybe. But  this situation could be happening at the same time as the lunch-making  situation and will inter-penetrate with it. There are dozens of possible  interactions: one might pause lunch to deal with the phone call, or one  might continue making the sandwich while chatting, or some other  combination. Again, fine for a human observer. But a computer trying to  make sense of these happenings only has a limited sensor-driven view,  and has to try to associate events with interpretations &lt;em&gt;without knowing what it's seeing ahead of time&lt;/em&gt;.  The fact that many things can happen simultaneously enormously  complicates the challenge of identifying what's going on robustly,  damaging what is often already quite a tenuous process. We therefore  need techniques for describing &lt;em&gt;situation compositions and interactions&lt;/em&gt; on top of the basic descriptions of the processes themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The  third challenge is also one of interaction, but this time involving  multiple people. One person might be making lunch whilst another watches  television, then the phone rings and one of them answers, realises the  call is for the other, and passes it over. So as well as  interpenetration we now have multiple agents generating sensor events,  perhaps without being able to determine exactly which person caused  which event. (A motion sensor sees movement: it doesn't see who's  moving, and the individuals may not be tagged in such a way that they  can be identified or even differentiated between.) Real spaces involve  multiple people, and this may place limits on the behaviours we can  demonstrate. But at the very least we need to be able to &lt;em&gt;describe processes involving multiple agents&lt;/em&gt; and to &lt;em&gt;support simultaneous situations in the same or different populations&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for me the next challenges of situation recognition boil down to how we describe what we're expecting to observe in a way that reflects noise, complexity and concurrency of real-world conditions.  Once we have these we can explore and improve the techniques we use to  map from sensor data (itself &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2010/02/216/"&gt;noisy and hard to program with&lt;/a&gt;) to identified situations, and thence  to behaviour. In many ways this is a real-world version of the  concurrency theories and process algebras that were developed to  describe concurrent computing processes: process languages brought into  the real world, perhaps. This is the approach we're taking in a  European-funded research project, &lt;a href="http://www.sapere-project.eu/"&gt;SAPERE&lt;/a&gt;, in which we're hoping to understand how to engineer smart, context-aware systems on large and flexible scales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>context</category><category>pervasive systems</category><category>programming</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/03/23/situations/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 09:45:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Call for papers: Formal methods for Pervasive Systems</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/01/31/fmps-cfp/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are looking for papers on the application of formal methods to pervasive computing, for a workshop at FM'11. (Full disclosure: I'm the keynote speaker.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Formal Methods for Pervasive Systems [Pervasive@FM2011]&lt;/h2&gt;
A workshop held as part of &lt;a href="http://fm2011.lero.ie"&gt;FORMAL METHODS 2011&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DEADLINE:&lt;/strong&gt; 20th March 2011
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;WORKSHOP TOPICS&lt;/h3&gt;
Logics, Process calculi, Automata, Specification languages, Probabilistic analysis, Model checking, Theorem-proving, Tools, Automated deduction
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;FOR THE&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;privacy, behaviour, security, reliability, interoperability, context-aware, mobility, resource requirements, temporal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;ASPECTS OF&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;pervasive healthcare systems, sensor networks, e-commerce, cloud computing, MANETs/VANETs, telephony, device swarms, electronic tags, human-device interaction, etc.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;SUBMISSIONS&lt;/h3&gt;
Our aim is to have productive discussions and a true workshop "feel". Thus, we invite two kinds of submission:
&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; Original research papers concerning any of the above topics; or&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; Survey papers providing an overview of some of the above topics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
Submissions should be written in English, formatted according Springer LNCS style, and not exceed 20 pages in length. Submissions must be made via &lt;a href="http://www.easychair.org/conferences/?conf=pervasivefm2011"&gt;Easychair&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;Our aim is for an informal proceedings based on these submissions to be available during the workshop. Depending upon the success of the workshop, we intend to produce an edited book based (at least in part) upon the contributions or develop a special issue of a journal.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;IMPORTANT DATES&lt;/h3&gt;
Submission deadline:          20th March 2011
Notification of acceptance:    1st May 2011
Pre-proceedings version due:  20th May 2011
Workshop:                     20th or 21st June, 2011
&lt;h3&gt;INVITED SPEAKER&lt;/h3&gt;
Simon Dobson (School of Computer Science, University of St. Andrews)
&lt;h3&gt;WORKSHOP CO-CHAIRS&lt;/h3&gt;
Michael Fisher    (University of Liverpool, UK)
Brian Logan       (University of Nottingham, UK)
&lt;h3&gt;PROGRAMME COMMITTEE&lt;/h3&gt;
Natasha Alechina    (Nottingham, UK)
Myrto Arapinis      (Birmingham, UK)
Mohamed Bakhouya    (Belfort, FR)
Doina Bucur         (INCAS3, NL)
Michael Butler      (Southampton, UK)
Muffy Calder        (Glasgow, UK)
Antonio Coronato    (CNR, IT)
Soren Debois        (Copenhagen, DK)
Giuseppe De Pietro  (CNR, IT)
Marina De Vos       (Bath, UK)
Simon Dobson        (St Andrews, UK)
Michael Fisher      (Liverpool, UK)
Michael Harrison    (Newcastle, UK)
Savas Konur         (Liverpool, UK)
Brian Logan         (Nottingham, UK)
Alessio Lomuscio    (Imperial, UK)
Ka Lok Man          (XJTLU, CN)
Julian Padget       (Bath, UK)
Anand Ranganathan   (IBM, USA)
Alessandro Russo    (Imperial, UK)
Mark Ryan           (Birmingham, UK)
Chris Unsworth      (Glasgow, UK)
Kaiyu Wan           (XJTLU, CN)
&lt;h3&gt;STEERING COMMITTEE&lt;/h3&gt;
Natasha Alechina    (University of Nottingham, UK)
Muffy Calder        (University of Glasgow, UK)
Michael Fisher      (University of Liverpool, UK)
Brian Logan         (University of Nottingham, UK)
Mark Ryan           (University of Birmingham, UK)&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>conference</category><category>formal methods</category><category>pervasive systems</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/01/31/fmps-cfp/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2011 11:34:52 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>