<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about privacy)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/privacy.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 17:16:11 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Too many numbers</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2013/11/14/numbers/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I've never really noticed before how over-indexed even common documents are.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

Maybe it's just that we've become more sensitive to these things recently, but when I recently renewed my car's tax disc (for non-UK readers: the document that shows your car is legally on the road) that I realised exactly how much numeric information appears on the document:

&lt;a href="http://blogs.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/simondobson/files/2013/11/too-many-numbers.png"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3735" alt="too-many-numbers" src="http://blogs.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/simondobson/files/2013/11/too-many-numbers-300x161.png" width="300" height="161"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

There's some "expected" information that really has to appear: names, addresses, car registration numbers, fee, and the like (which I've blurred). But the real action is on the counterfoil -- a document you don't have to keep, are never asked to produce, and will basically never be seen by anyone again.

Let's start with the long sequence of numbers (1)  at the top left. Two groups of these numbers are repeated bottom right as (3) and (4); three groups are distinct and don't appear anywhere else. There's a long issue number for this document bottom-left (2). At the bottom right, (6) also appears on the disc itself as (8) -- in fact the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; number  that makes it onto the tax disc itself, although there's also a barcode in the centre.

As if this wasn't enough, and despite all the numbers being printed in what is clearly a machine-readable font, there are two QR code. In the interests of science I scanned them both. (6) repeats (5) (and therefore (8)), but (7) was too small to scan with a cellphone QR code reader: it's visibly different to (6), though.

So this is eight distinct pieces of information, in the main all dutifully recorded only to be discarded when one detaches the tax disc from the counterfoil to fit it. What &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; it all? Since we don't have ID numbers in the UK, none of the numbers relate to me directly. I can understand a single registration number for the tax disc -- although even that's a bit redundant when you can query the tax status of a vehicle online to check whether the disc is genuine or not -- but the rest mystifies me, as does the use of three machine-readable formats on one document.

I'm not worried about the volume of information &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;, as it's being discarded and -- more especially -- it doesn't seem to relate to me or my identity in any way, but I am curious as to why it all appears in the first place and what purpose any of it serves.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>privacy</category><category>society</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2013/11/14/numbers/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2013 10:00:05 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Disloyalty cards</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2011/03/02/disloyalty-cards/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I seem to be carrying a lot of loyalty cards at the moment. Given my  complete lack of loyalty to any particular brand, is there some way to  lose most of the cards and still get the benefits?

&lt;!--more--&gt;

Most  large stores have loyalty cards these days: swipe them at the till and  receive some small but non-zero reward at a later date. There are all  sorts of variations: &lt;a href="http://www.tesco.com/clubcard/clubcard/"&gt;Tesco UK&lt;/a&gt; has a very generous rewards programme;  &lt;a href="http://www.starbucks.co.uk/en-GB/_Card/"&gt;Starbucks' card&lt;/a&gt; is also a debit card that you can load-up with cash to  pay for coffee; &lt;a href="http://www.costa.co.uk/card/"&gt;Costa&lt;/a&gt; has a more traditional "buy ten, get one free"  approach; &lt;a href="http://www.waterstones.com/waterstonesweb/pages/waterstones-card/1614/"&gt;Waterstone's&lt;/a&gt; collects points to put towards later book  purchases.. (You can already see where a lot of my disposable income  goes...)

What the store gets from this, of course, is market  intelligence at the level of the individual and group. Tesco (to use one  example) can use my loyalty card to match purchases to me, in a way  that's otherwise impossible. Using this information they can tailor  offers they make to me: give me cash vouchers to spend on anything, but  also targeted vouchers for individual products that I don't normally  buy, but which my purchasing history says I &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt;, if offered.  The supermarket can also group the purchases of people in a particular  neighbourhood and use it to stock local stores in ways that appeal to  the actual shoppers who frequent the place: if you doubt this, go to a  downtown Tesco and then a suburban one, and compare the variation in  stock.

The fact that loyalty cards are so common tells you how  valuable stores find this kind of market intelligence, and it's  purchased from customers for a very small price. We reveal an enormous  amount about our lifestyles and activities from our everyday purchases.  Once you have a really huge amount of data, you can &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2010/04/computer-microscope/"&gt;extract information  from it in ways that are by no means obvious&lt;/a&gt;. You can also be more  speculative in how you process the data, since the penalties for being  wrong are so low. A traditional pervasive computing system is real-time  and has a high penalty for inaccuracy; a loyalty card operates on a  slower timescale and only has opportunity costs for incorrect  recommendations. Thought about from this perspective, I could even see  ways of testing hypotheses you formed about individuals, and using this  to refine the situation recognition algorithms: if their habits suggest  they have a baby, offer them a &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; good deal for baby products and use their future actions to confirm or refute the hypothesis.

These  approaches work both in the real world and online, of course. &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; gets all your profile information without offering a loyalty card,  simply by the way e-commerce works. Tesco online links e-shopping to  real-world shopping, and so can compare your long-term trend purchases  against your "impulse" (or just forgetfulness) buys in the local shop, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; correlate this against your home address.

None of this is necessarily bad, of course. I &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; Amazon profiling me: they introduce me to books I might not otherwise  read, and that's an unmitigated good thing (for me). But it's important  to realise that these things are happening, their good and bad effects.

If  you care about your privacy, don't carry a loyalty card. On the other  hand, if you value personalised service, carry a load of them and help  them classify you.

It's also important to realise where the  breaks in the coverage are. If Tesco knew I frequented Starbucks, for  example, they might offer me a different kind of coffee to someone who  doesn't. (Don't offer a coffee snob a deal on cheap instant.) There are  lots of correlations between different areas of people's lives that  could be exploited -- "exploited" in a nice way, at least in principle,  but also profitably for the companies involved. What's needed is a way  to tie together more aspects of individuals' lives, either &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; individuals or in bulk.

One  way to do this might be to get rid of per-store loyalty cards and  replace them with a single profiling card: a "disloyalty" card. The  disloyalty card acts as a hub for collecting details of what an  individual buys where. The individual stores signing-up to the card  offer points according to their normal practices, but the points can be  spent at &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; store that participates in the disloyalty card  scheme. For the consumer, this means that they collect points faster and  can therefore spend them on more valuable goods and services.

What's  in it for the stores. More market intelligence, across an individual's  entire purchasing profile. One could do this individually, to allow  stores to see what customers buy in other stores and cross-sell to them.  Alternatively one could anonymise the data at an individual level but  allow correlations across groups: everyone who lives in Morningside, or  everyone who buys coffee early in the morning on a week-day at Haymarket  station. If the disloyalty card operator acted as a trusted third  party, individual stores could even cross-sell to individuals without  ever knowing to whom they were making the offer: that way the stores  still "own" their own customers, but can access more data about them &lt;em&gt;en masse&lt;/em&gt;, online and offline, across a range of businesses.

I'm  not necessarily suggesting this would be a good thing for the  individual  or indeed for the operation of the retail market as a whole  -- it provides enormous opportunities for profiling and severely and  increasingly disenfranchises people who choose to sit outside the scheme  -- but it's a commercial possibility that should be considered both by  commercial interests and by regulators.

Like many ideas,  there's precedent. Back in the 1970's we all used to collect &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Green_Shield_Stamps"&gt;Green  Shield stamps&lt;/a&gt;, which were given out by a range of shops and could be  redeemed collectively at special stores. (My grandfather, who was  particularly methodical and assiduous in all he did, was amazingly  effective at collecting his way to what he wanted in the Green Shield stores.) This scheme has the group-collecting aspect of disloyalty cards  without the market intelligence aspect, which brings the whole scheme  into the 21st century and gives is a measurable monetary value for all  concerned.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>innovation</category><category>privacy</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2011/03/02/disloyalty-cards/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 16:00:53 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>