<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about research)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/research.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 14:51:05 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Me and my research</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2022/11/28/me-and-my-research/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org4d94af9" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org4d94af9"&gt;Me and my research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org4d94af9"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've recently been thinking about my research directions, making use
of some advice I came across years ago.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2022/11/28/me-and-my-research/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>research</category><category>strategy</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2022/11/28/me-and-my-research/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2022 19:45:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>"Epidemic modelling" added to the executable books gallery</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2021/06/04/epidemic-modelling-added-to-the-executable-books-gallery/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://simondobson.org/images/posts/20210604-em-book-cover-small.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt; &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/introduction-to-epidemics/"&gt;"Epidemic modelling: Some notes, maths, and
code"&lt;/a&gt;, my book
about using network science to model epidemics, is now featured in the
gallery of the Executable Books project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2021/06/04/epidemic-modelling-added-to-the-executable-books-gallery/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>epidemic spreading</category><category>python</category><category>research</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2021/06/04/epidemic-modelling-added-to-the-executable-books-gallery/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jun 2021 07:24:05 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Re-starting "Complex networks, complex processes"</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2021/05/07/re-starting-complex-networks-complex-processes/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I re-started work on my &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2021/05/07/re-starting-complex-networks-complex-processes/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>complex networks</category><category>research</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2021/05/07/re-starting-complex-networks-complex-processes/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 May 2021 16:23:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>"Epidemic modelling" published</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2020/07/22/em-book-published/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://simondobson.org/images/posts/20200722-cover.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt; &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;My book "Epidemic modelling -- Some notes, maths, and code" is now available
from &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/1838535659/"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;
as well as &lt;a href="https://simoninireland.github.io/introduction-to-epidemics"&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2020/07/22/em-book-published/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>complex networks</category><category>epidemic spreading</category><category>research</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2020/07/22/em-book-published/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>First outing of "Epidemic modelling"</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2020/06/17/i-to-e-first/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;My lockdown project is now ready for its first outing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2020/06/17/i-to-e-first/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>complex networks</category><category>epidemic spreading</category><category>research</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2020/06/17/i-to-e-first/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 09:31:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why I research</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2011/02/23/why-i-research/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I came across George Orwell's 1946 essay &lt;em&gt;Why I write&lt;/em&gt;. Some of his reasons for writing resonate with some of my reasons for doing research.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

I wasn't expecting that. Research involves writing, of course, and reading too -- enormous amounts of both -- but it's not the same kind of writing as a &lt;em&gt;writer&lt;/em&gt; writes. While it's good to have a clear style in science, it's the clarity of the science and not the turn of phrase that's the most prized element of scientific writing.

Orwell, writing in 1946 (which is post &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Animal_Farm"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Animal farm&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, incidentally), sets out the forces that led him to become a writer. Specifically, he identifies "four great motives for writing" that will drive each writer in different proportion depending on who he is, when and what he's writing about. Reading these, it struck me how close they are to the reasons I (and I suspect others) have for doing research:

&lt;strong&gt;Sheer egoism. &lt;/strong&gt;That's one any academic &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; to agree with. A desire to be thought clever, talked about, and be remembered. For some, in some fields, there's a seduction towards popular commentary. For others it's a more academic draw, to be the centrepoint of conferences or to be head-hunted into bigger and better (and better-paid) jobs. As long as the pleasure of recognition doesn't get in the way of the science I don't think it does any harm, although we always need to keep in mind that it's really all about the research and not about the researcher -- a little &lt;em&gt;memento mori&lt;/em&gt; for the honest scientist.

&lt;strong&gt;Aesthetic enthusiasm. &lt;/strong&gt;It might surprise some people to hear about aesthetics applied to science, but it's certainly an aspect of the experience: the pleasure in thoughts well-set-down, of an elegant and complete explanation of something. Especially in mathematics there's a clear and well-recognised link between simplicity and the perception of beauty, a feeling that the &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; approach is the one that captures all the essence of a problem as simply as possible. It's surprising how often such simplicity works, and how often it leads directly to unexpected complexity and interactions.

&lt;strong&gt;Historical impulse. &lt;/strong&gt;Orwell uses this in the sense of "a desire to see things as they are, to find out true facts and store them up for the use of posterity." In sciences I think one can also see in this a desire to bring together strands of past work (your own and others'), and again to make a clean and elegant synthesis of whatever field one works in. I think it also encompasses the need we have to share science, to have papers in durable venues like journals as well as in live conference events.

&lt;strong&gt;Political purpose. &lt;/strong&gt;The desire to push the world in a particular direction. Scientists are often accused of being remote from the real world, although a lot of what we do &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2010/05/grey-philistines/"&gt;is increasingly influencing public policy&lt;/a&gt;. This element of writing also led Orwell to the most famous line of the whole essay: "The opinion that art should have nothing to do with politics is itself a political attitude." Few senior scientists would disagree nowadays.

It's surprising to me that a writer and a scientist could agree on their driving purposes to this extent. I suspect it's simply because of the need for creativity that underlies both spheres, and the fact that both are essentially self-motivated and self-driven. You become a writer because it's who you are, not because of what you'll get out of it, although you also obviously hope that the rewards will flow somehow; similarly for science.

What I &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt; have, of course -- and I'm  grateful for it -- is the equivalent of the trauma Orwell suffered in the Spanish Civil War, which shaped his subsequent writing and give him a lifelong cause against totalitarianism. It certainly makes me want to read &lt;a href="http://www.george-orwell.org/Homage_to_Catalonia/index.html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Homage to Catalonia&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; again, though, and I'll read it with a new view on how it came about.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>research</category><category>writing</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2011/02/23/why-i-research/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2011 08:00:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why I don’t sign NDAs</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2011/01/17/no-ndas/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Non-disclosure agreements (NDAs) are something I try not to sign, for various reasons. For one thing, they give a false sense of security; for another, they interfere with me doing my job.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

An increasing amount of academic research is supported in one way or another by companies, either directly or through co-funding agreements. This trend is only likely to increase as State funding becomes less common. As well as this, academics are sometimes approached to do consultancy or development work for companies on a more close-to-market basis. This can be great for all concerned: the companies get access to (hopefully) unbiased expert advice that can perhaps take a longer-term view, while the academics get real-world problems to work on and a reality check on some of their ideas.

Despite all this, there are still some problems. Chief among them, I've found, are non-disclosure agreements (NDAs) whereby one or both sides agree not to disclose proprietary information to third parties. Some NDAs are one-way, so (for example) the university agrees not to disclose company information; many are symmetrical and protect both sides, which is obviously more desirable. (Interestingly it's often university-led NDAs that are asymmetric, implying that the companies have no intellectual input...) Although they sound like they're used for competitive reasons -- and sometimes they are -- it's more likely that they used to protect information for use in later patent applications, where discussion with a third party might be regarded as "publication" and so endanger the patent. Anyone who works in commercial research has to be sensitive to this, and since I used to run a company myself I'm conscious of protecting others' intellectual property.

So why does this cause a problem? Mainly because of the bluntness of the instrument by which the protection happens.

In my job, I have a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of discussions that involve half-formed ideas. Many of these seem pretty much to condense out of the ether into several people's heads simultaneously: it's in no way uncommon to have two or three people discuss the same "novel" idea within days of each other. I suppose it's just that there's nothing really new under the sun, and people who share a common technical milieu will often see the same problems and arrive at similar solutions. Often the people involved are students: either undergraduates looking for projects, or PhD students with ideas for theses or papers. These people are my "core constituency" in the sense that my main job is to teach and supervise them in a research-led way.

You can probably see where this is going. Suppose a student comes to me with an idea, and that this idea is related in some way to an idea presented by a company with whom I've signed an NDA. What do I do? Refuse to discuss the matter with the student, even though they're fired-up about it? Try to re-focus them onto another area, even though it might be a great idea, because I can't discuss it? Send them to someone else, even though I might be the right person to supervise the work?

What I &lt;em&gt;can't&lt;/em&gt; do is get involved, because however hard I try, I'll never be able to &lt;em&gt;prove&lt;/em&gt; that information covered by the NDA had no effect on what I said or did -- or didn't say or do, for that matter. That leaves both me and the university open to legal action, especially if by some chance the student's work got a high profile and damaged the company, for example by developing an open-source solution to something they were working on.

This is something of a dilemma. I like working with companies; I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; working with students; and I don't like the feeling that my freedom to discuss technology and ideas is being legally constrained.

I therefore minimise my exposure to NDAs and confidentiality agreements. It's sometimes unavoidable, for example as part of EU project consortium agreements. But as a general rule I don't think NDAs sit well with academics, and there's too much danger of damaging the general openness of research within a university: too much of a sacrifice just to get a single funded project. I'll happily agree to keep information confidential, but the risks of signing a blunt and broad agreement to that effect are just too great.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>innovation</category><category>research</category><category>university</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2011/01/17/no-ndas/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2011 09:00:27 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>