<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about reviews)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/reviews.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 09:20:01 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>A New Kind of Science</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/a-new-kind-of-science/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1386925097l/238558._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Stephen Wolfram
	  (1997)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      I have very mixed feelings about this book. On the one hand it's a triumph of computational experimental technique, taking an idea that was well-known (cellular automata) and subjecting it to rigorous exploration. This uncovers a lot of new science, not least showing that complex systems can arise from even the simplest set of rules, but also that this complexity falls into classes that show graded complexity depending purely on the fine structure of the initial conditions. That's a massively important discovery.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;On the other hand.... It's hard to describe this as a "new kind" of science. "New science," yes, but not indicative of a new paradigm or &lt;i&gt;way&lt;/i&gt; of doing science, other than by emphasising the structured use of simulation. Wolfram completely over-sells what he's achieved, making claims he can't substantiate to aggrandise his own contributions. And that's a shame, not least because it's so &lt;i&gt;unnecessary&lt;/i&gt;: Wolfram has made some important discoveries, both here and to several other branches of physics and computer science, as well as popularising computational methods and tools. It's tragic that he doesn't seem to be able to appreciate himself as being sufficient.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The book is also quite terribly written, being almost half-composed of footnotes, meaning a reader is constantly skipping forwards and back: difficult in print, and I suspect impossible in a digital edition unless it's been very carefully hyperlinked. And the footnotes are often important! – indeed, they often provide evidence to back-up a claim in the main text that's entirely unsupportable from what's been presented. So it can be seen as both excessively long and insufficiently detailed, which is quite an achievement.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	3/5.
	  Finished Sunday 7 July, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4934435584?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/a-new-kind-of-science/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Shikasta: Canopus Dans Argos: Archives</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/shikasta-canopus-dans-argos-archives/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1516764001l/38189412._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Doris Lessing
	  (1979)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      Why is modern civilisation so self-destructive and complicated? The answer from this alternative history is that a previously time of happiness and long lives was subverted by a change in the universal forces to induce the current malaise.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I did enjoy this book, but it does live up to its sub-title: &lt;i&gt;Personal, psychological, historical documents relating to visit by Johor (George Sherban) Emissary (Grade 9) 87th of the Period of the Last Days&lt;/i&gt;. It's told in a very disjointed form using purported reports and other documents, much of the time from the diary of a young girl who doesn't really know what's going on, and so can't really advance the plot very effectively. That makes it hard work, even though the writing and the overall premise are excellent.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	2/5.
	  Finished Sunday 7 July, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5723914316?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/shikasta-canopus-dans-argos-archives/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ultra-Processed People: The Science Behind Food That Isn't Food</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/ultra-processed-people-the-science-behind-food-that-isnt-food/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1679715862l/62586003._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Chris van Tulleken
	  (2023)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      Food &lt;i&gt;versus&lt;/i&gt; food-shaped industrial products.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Ultra-processed food (UPF) is pervasive in modern diets, and with it comes a litany of actual, conjectured, and supposed harms. UPF itself is a strange beast, taking food crops and turning them into pure components that can then be re-mixed to construct new products. This has some perverse consequences, such as flavours being removed from purified and "modified" oils and starches in order to make them more broadly usable – and then having &lt;i&gt;those same flavours&lt;/i&gt; re-introduced later in the process, again in "modified" form. That sounds insane – how can it be cheaper than using the original oil? – but in fact it makes perfet commercial sense for companies wanting fungible raw materials to produce unvarying, known-ahead-of-time tastes and textures. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The resulting products (I'm now reluctant to call them foods), being created in labs, can be re-worked in pursuit of particular commercial goals, for example by adding powdered soya when looking to create a "high-protein" snack. They can also be re-engineered to be far more pleasurable and addictive for consumers, for example by hacking the body's responses to food (which are themselves coming to be understood as far more subtle and complicated than we used to think).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;van Tulleken has a science background, and it shows in the writing: most of the claims are carefully framed and evidenced. His background also saves him from falling for the industry's faux-refutations about there not being definitive causal links to specific harms: randomised controlled trials &lt;i&gt;aren't&lt;/i&gt; the "scientific gold standard" in situations where they're impossible to conduct in the real world, and epidemiological evidence coupled with some knowledge of the possible harm pathways can provide sufficient evidence. Having said that, he does sometimes deviate from this careful path, and there are a few instances of words like "may" and "could" doing a lot of heavy lifting.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;One of the most powerful elements of the book is that it simultaneously doesn't preach or prescribe, but does offer suggestions for ways forward. UPF is very difficult to precisely define, and is therefore difficult to legislate for or avoid. Does a single stabiliser in a product render it UPF? – because if so literally &lt;i&gt;anything in a packet&lt;/i&gt; would be included. van Tulleken also takes aim at some of the wider social drivers of UPF, notably its cheapness and ease of preparation compared to "real" food, reinforcing poor diet as a consequence of poverty. He also suggests some interesting policy options, while also taking aim at a policy infrastructure that's heavily co-opted by the UPF industry. Regulators and the food industry are &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; partners and have goals that are mutually irreconcilable within the current framework of pre-eminent shareholder value.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	5/5.
	  Finished Thursday 4 July, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6565805510?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/ultra-processed-people-the-science-behind-food-that-isnt-food/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sandworm: A New Era of Cyberwar and the Hunt for the Kremlin's Most Dangerous Hackers</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/sandworm-a-new-era-of-cyberwar-and-the-hunt-for-the-kremlins-most-dangerous-hackers/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1567555830l/41436213._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Andy Greenberg
	  (2019)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A history of cybersecurity with an emphasis on attacks against critical infrastructure.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Rather than bomb a power plant or dam, why not have its own IT systems turn on it? That's the premise of a lot of modern cyberattacks, and they can be run with all the same sophistication as more conventional attacks against purely digital targets – but with the proviso that a lot of the targets don't think of themselves as IT organisations and haven't interalised the importance of their digital control systems. Since they don't emphasise security at board level, it gets neglected and becomes a weak spot that can be exploited from anywhere on the globe.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The remedies aren't always trivial. Many attacks detailed in this book are almost incredibly elongated, involving the compromise of several servers and softwate packages on the way to the target. Keeping industrial control systems up-to-date can be difficult (or impossible): physical infrastructure exists on far longer timescales than the digital systems than control it. (I've had personal experience of laboratory equipment with control software that can &lt;i&gt;only&lt;/i&gt; run on Windows 95, which isn't being upgraded. Keeping that secure needs dedicated changes in the network architecture, and has a lot of knock-on consequences for efficiency and data management.)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The value of such hacking for criminals is easy to understand, but it's also the ultimate technique of asymmetric warefare, letting an attacker deny responsibility and avoid counterattacks. Even the most powerful countries have an incentive to stop responses going kinetic, after all. But the asymmetry works both ways, with the US as one of the primary developers of sophisticated cyberweapons and so having an incentive not to push for international controls even while at the same time the US critical infrastructure is more vulnerable than others' to those weapons.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Greenberg is a long-time student of cyberwarfare, and writes with a lot of insight into both the politics and the technology. He highlights the impacts of many short-sighted decisions made in the interests of national security advantage, culminating in the Shadow Brokers' release of a cache of NSA tools that form the basis for a new generation of cyberweapons. This is a great book to pair with &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/49247043.This_Is_How_They_Tell_Me_the_World_Ends_The_Cyberweapons_Arms_Race" title="This Is How They Tell Me the World Ends The Cyberweapons Arms Race by Nicole Perlroth" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;This Is How They Tell Me the World Ends: The Cyberweapons Arms Race&lt;/a&gt; for a broad-ranging and highly technically literate exploration of the new arms frontier.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Friday 28 June, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6337793870?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/sandworm-a-new-era-of-cyberwar-and-the-hunt-for-the-kremlins-most-dangerous-hackers/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Mathematician's Apology</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/a-mathematicians-apology/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1348629338l/154060._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	G.H. Hardy
	  (1940)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A short dispatch from another world. It's hard to recognise the academia portrayed by Hardy, and I'm not sure that's a bad thing. One has to admire its purity, though: a principled neglect of everything outside a particular field of study, and the deeply interwoven social life that goes with it. It sounds at once attractive and claustrophobic, inspiring and shallow.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Hardy is a perfect narrator and exemplar, being so diffident about his own accomplishments as to characterise them as having worked with one excellent mathematician (Littlewood) and discovered another (Ramanujan). He was a lot more than that within the small world of number theory in which he worked, including being a foundational contributor to computational complexity theory (although not in the exact definition currently used).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Reading this book sometimes feels like an intellectual making a trip to the world of &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/58045504.Brideshead_Revisited_The_Sacred_and_Profane_Memories_of_Captain_Charles_Ryder" title="Brideshead Revisited The Sacred and Profane Memories of Captain Charles Ryder by Evelyn Waugh" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Brideshead Revisited&lt;/a&gt;, and that may be the right way to think of academia in the inter-war years: tied-up in upper-class privilege, class-consciousness, and repression.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	3/5.
	  Finished Friday 24 May, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2907726884?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/a-mathematicians-apology/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sideshow: Kissinger, Nixon &amp; the Destruction of Cambodia</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/sideshow-kissinger-nixon-the-destruction-of-cambodia/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1172210282l/150092._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	William Shawcross
	  (1979)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A shocking tale of aggression and duplicity, where a country whose only fault is to be too weak to resist incursions by another is attacked and undermined by a third country still claiming the moral high ground.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Alost every character comes out badly from this story – but especially Henry Kissinger, whose willingness to sacrifice foreign lives while protecting his own reputation and influence are quite breathtaking. It's troubling that Nixon's fall was for reasons &lt;i&gt;other&lt;/i&gt; than his orders to bomb Cambodia and his willingness to lie to Congress (whom he was constitution-bound to consult and inform). The fact that the Cambodian leadership of Lon Nol and Sihanouk were also corrupt and self-serving offers no excuse. The US Joint Chiefs stood behind him because it suited them to extend the Vietnam War rather than end it, even after the point that they knew it was un-winnable and were extracting their own ground forces. Together these people all opened the door for the Khmer Rouge and the killing fields that followed, and did so knowing the risks they were running.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Saturday 18 May, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6051760452?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/sideshow-kissinger-nixon-the-destruction-of-cambodia/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>How to Win an Information War: The Propagandist Who Outwitted Hitler</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/how-to-win-an-information-war-the-propagandist-who-outwitted-hitler/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1698420610l/182761575._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Peter Pomerantsev
	  (2024)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      Part biography and part assessment of the modern media landscape in the face of prolonged and well-funded disinformation. Sefton Delmer crafted a lot of British propaganda against the Nazis, drawing on his own childhood in Germany.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As with &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/52382865.How_to_Lose_the_Information_War_Russia__Fake_News_and_the_Future_of_Conflict" title="How to Lose the Information War Russia, Fake News and the Future of Conflict by Nina Jankowicz" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;How to Lose the Information War: Russia, Fake News and the Future of Conflict&lt;/a&gt; – another take on the same issues, with less of an historical driver – Pomerentsev focuses on the importance of the perceived messenger as well as the message: the idea that "truth will prevail" simply isn't true when untruth is being cleverly promoted. Delmer pioneered this approach by creating radio-based characters crafted to appeal to particular segments of German society and seed disquiet amongst them.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;(I was reminded at one point of a character in &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/530965.The_Day_of_the_Triffids" title="The Day of the Triffids by John Wyndham" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;The Day of the Triffids&lt;/a&gt; who works as a professional agitator able to meet anyone on their own ground, changing his voice, dress, and presentation style to suit the audience, and arguing that the way you deliver a message is at least as important as its content. Delmer would have approved.)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;One can see Delmer as the origin of the modern approach to "flood the zone" and undermine belief in &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; media and information. He was constantly criticised by his opponents (both those making moral arguments and those simply wanting to be in control) to demonstrate the efficacy of his techniques. That misses the point somewhat. He wasn't looking to bring about concrete, short-term changes, but rather was trying to influence the medium-term attitudes his listeners had to their information sources: marketing rather than sales. It's hard to measure the successes of this, other than to point out that now, eighty years later, his approach seems to have been refined and re-applied by people who are, in many cases, closely aligned to the politics he himself fought against.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Friday 3 May, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6149473453?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/how-to-win-an-information-war-the-propagandist-who-outwitted-hitler/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Beyond</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/beyond/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1639479657l/58849383._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Stephen Walker
	  (2021)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      The space race from the American perspective is well-known: this book presents the same race from the Soviet perspective.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The differences are profound, of course, mainly driven by the Soviet programme occurring in complete secrecy to duck the risks that failure would have on the programme's image. The American programme by contrast was conducted in the open at least as far as the actual "shots" were concerned – and their public failures did indeed endanger their ability to continue, at least in part because neither public nor politicians understood the process of engineering or just how &lt;i&gt;hard&lt;/i&gt; each shot was. The deep irony is that the Soviet successes appeared so sudden and dramatic they led directly to the deepening of the American programme and commitment or more money and effort than the Soviets seemed able to maintain to capitalise on their early lead.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There are plenty of revelations even for those with a detailed interest in space history. I remember hearing all through the 1970s that the Soviet spacecraft landed on land, but it turns out that in many cases the cosmonauts were bailing-out and parachuting to earth instead, with this being intensively covered-up even to the extent of falsifying reports to the international organisation responsible for certifying "firsts" in space.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;While the achievements of both programmes were profound, they were perhaps doomed in the long term by a lack of vision for what they were actually &lt;i&gt;for&lt;/i&gt;. The benefits of space technology are now obvious; those of exploration perhaps less so, although it doesn't (in my opinion) require much suspension of disbelief to feel that science-driven activities lead almost inevitably to enormously valuable spin-offs. The fact that we can't quantify these &lt;i&gt;a priori&lt;/i&gt; shouldn't (in my opinion, again) stop us keeping the faith in the value of experiments that advance our science &lt;i&gt;and&lt;/i&gt; engineering in ways that wouldn't otherwise happen.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	5/5.
	  Finished Sunday 21 April, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6395477584?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/beyond/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Emergence of Numerical Weather Prediction: Richardson's Dream</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-emergence-of-numerical-weather-prediction-richardsons-dream/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1348662620l/275229._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Peter   Lynch
	  (2006)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A very technical examination of the world's first numerical weather "prediction" – although in fact it was really a "postdiction", taking detailed data and using it to compute a scenario that could be compared against a known ground truth. It was an incredible achievement anyway, performing manually and at low resolution the calculations now routinely performed by computers.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Richardson was the person who saw that this would be possible, realising that the physics and mathematics could be solved even though the computational capabilities didn't exist. In this he foresaw the emergence of the modern power of data, where the existence of more and better data transforms both the way we do science and the sciene that we do. It's something that should put him alongside Turing and Von Neumann as visionaries of what computation could achieve.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Sunday 21 April, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6326779093?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-emergence-of-numerical-weather-prediction-richardsons-dream/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Great Post Office Scandal: The fight to expose a multimillion pound IT disaster which put innocent people in jail</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-great-post-office-scandal-the-fight-to-expose-a-multimillion-pound-it-disaster-which-put-innocent-people-in-jail/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1636495053l/59581993._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Nick Wallis
	  (2021)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      The history of what is still as I write this an ongoing scandal: perhaps the greatest miscarriage of justice in UK history, when the Post Office turned on and prosecuted its own operators for fraud on the basis of flawed evidence from its Horizon IT system.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The scandal came from a series of interlocking arrangements. The Post Office could mount prosecutions in its own right (something that its management now claims to have been unaware of), with its own investigators able to interview under caution but seemingly not required to record interviews or allow legal representation. The contracts under which postmasters operated were mis-represented to turn any discrepancies into the postmasters' fault, while simultaneously denying them the data they'd need to investigate themselves unless they were exceptionally careful and persistent – and the few who &lt;i&gt;were&lt;/i&gt; were prosecuted and driven out anyway. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As a computer scientist I have to say that the most ridiculous part of the story is the presumption in law that a computer system works properly absent explicit to the contrary, that – when coupled with an asymmetry of who can access to software and its logs – makes it impossible to fight against computer-generated evidence. No system of this size &lt;i&gt;ever&lt;/i&gt; works flawlessly, and a careful designer would add features on that assumption, such as paper-trails or detailed logs that can then be forensically analysed. Equally, no such system would ever be constructed without remote access to terminal endpoints to allow problems to be remotely fixed, and again a careful designer would ensure that such interventions were logged so as to be auditable. This is so self-evident that I find it hard to believe that Horizon &lt;i&gt;wasn't&lt;/i&gt; designed that way, which makes the repeated denials even more suspicious.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But there's a social commentary here too. The justice system, juries, and the communities of the prosecuted postmasters were almost eager to believe their guilt. Part of that was the lack of proper media scrutiny to bring the extent of prosecutions into the public eye, and part due to obfuscation by the Post Office itself – but it surely there should be systemic oversight of such things, given the massive consequences. And surely communities should have been less ready to believe accusations made against their own members that went against the evidence of their own eyes.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Sunday 7 April, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5897614552?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-great-post-office-scandal-the-fight-to-expose-a-multimillion-pound-it-disaster-which-put-innocent-people-in-jail/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>