<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about reviews)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/reviews.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 17:41:20 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Herding Hemingway's Cats: Understanding how our genes work</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/herding-hemingways-cats-understanding-how-our-genes-work/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Herding Hemingway's Cats: Understanding how our genes work&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1456091835l/25663760._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Kat Arney&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2016
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A masterful telling of modern genetics.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Everything you know about genetics is wrong: what's how it feels, anyway. The simple story about mutation and inheritance is ... well, not wrong exactly, but woefully incomplete. I think part of the problem is that we lack the right analogies. Genetics is &lt;i&gt;in no way&lt;/i&gt; a blueprint that's simply read when creating life, nor is it &lt;i&gt;in any way&lt;/i&gt; constructed like engineering. Instead it operates at the boundary of chaos, with multiple redundant (and often conflicting) mechanisms finding an uneasy hoeostasis. Genes aren't elementary packets of information, nor does most of the genome consist of them: nor, indeed, is there any well-agreed notion of what a gene actually &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt;. The basic mechanism of RNA reading DNA and then being used to create proteins comes with a set of baroque extensions, as does the supposedly clear notion of heritable characteristics being frozen in the DNA itself.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;All in all it's amazing that any of it is understood at all – let alone well enough to perform modifications and other feats of modern biotechnology. Arney in many ways achieves the impossible in this book, not hiding the complexity of dumbing it down for a popular audience, but also never getting lost or adding to the inevitable confusion that all this complexity induces even in a scientifically literate reader. I learned a huge amount and had several confusions sorted out for me (to the extent that they are understood at all).
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  5/5.
	    Finished 27 November 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5039953329?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/herding-hemingways-cats-understanding-how-our-genes-work/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2022 13:31:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Suez: The Double War</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/suez-the-double-war/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Suez: The Double War&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1580814308l/23081781._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Fullick Roy Powell Geoffrey&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2014
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A history of a war without a purpose.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The Suez invasion by Britain and France ostensibly took place to separate two warring armies: the Egyptians defending Sinai, and the Israelis who had invaded it. In this is succeeded, in the sense that it stopped the fighting and led to a UN resolution that introduced a more international force to keep the peace.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Except that's not what happened at all. In reality the British, who allegedly took the initiative, followed the French, who had persuaded the Israelis (or been persuaded by them, it's not entirely clear) to provide a pretext to take over the Canal Zone and oust Egyptian President Nasser. The whole enterprise unwound as a result of the USA not supporting, and indeed actively frustrating, its two former allies – much to their surprise. Neither country was strong enough to go it alone.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Reading this book it's clear that there never was a clear war aim, or at least not one that was remotely plausible. The intiial plan called for taking Cairo, although no-one was sure that this would accomplish the aim of destroying Nasser's popularity. The revised plan called for occupying the Canal Zone only, which of course had the effect of &lt;i&gt;strengthening&lt;/i&gt; Nasser's hand. Neither the military nor the political leaders seemed to think this through at the time, although many did in the aftermath.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Fullick and Powell were semi-eyewitnesses on the ground, and are scathing of everything to do with the operation, going so far as to say that it both destroyed British trust in their own government and contributed directly to the fall of the French Fourth Republic. They point out how far the world of Eden and Suez seems to be from the late 1980s when the Suez papers were largely declassified: a world where the solemn work of a Minister was simply accepted, as was the notion that invading Egypt (because it had nationalised the canal) constituted a "just" war.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  3/5.
	    Finished 19 November 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5104294357?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/suez-the-double-war/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2022 17:26:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What If? 2: Additional Serious Scientific Answers to Absurd Hypothetical Questions (What If?, #2)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/what-if-2-additional-serious-scientific-answers-to-absurd-hypothetical-questions-what-if-2/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;What If? 2: Additional Serious Scientific Answers to Absurd Hypothetical Questions (What If?, #2)&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1643644004l/60190659._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Randall Munroe&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2022
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A &lt;i&gt;tour de force&lt;/i&gt; of creative scientific answers. It's perhaps less enjoyable than the original &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/21413662.What_If__Serious_Scientific_Answers_to_Absurd_Hypothetical_Questions__What_If____1_" title="What If? Serious Scientific Answers to Absurd Hypothetical Questions (What If?, #1) by Randall Munroe" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;What If? Serious Scientific Answers to Absurd Hypothetical Questions&lt;/a&gt; – but only because it &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; a sequel, and so lacks the novelty of the first. It's still a rush, ranging from cosmology down to particle physics, with enough black holes to satisfy anyone. And I also learned about the &lt;a href="https://mybestplace.com/en/article/ussuri-bay-the-most-beautiful-glass-beach-in-the-world" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Glass beach of Vladivostok&lt;/a&gt;, which is a place I'd never imagined existed and made the book worthwhile all on its own, just as Randall said it would.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  5/5.
	    Finished 14 November 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4988400587?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/what-if-2-additional-serious-scientific-answers-to-absurd-hypothetical-questions-what-if-2/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 21:36:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Secret War: The Story of SOE</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/secret-war-the-story-of-soe/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Secret War: The Story of SOE&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1435116256l/1772013._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Nigel West&lt;/h2&gt;
	    1993
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	The sub-title is more accurate than the title. This isn't an official history – but it reads like one, being much ore concerned with who ran which sections, the committees and organograms of SOE than with the actual secret war it prosecuted so well.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Some of the in-fighting described is inevitable, such as the tensions between SOE and MI6. An intelligence service needs quiet; a sabotage service is devoted to exactly the opposite, and so tends to disrupt intelligence-gathering by attracting the attentions of counter-intelligence services. This explains, but doesn't excuse, the hostility and machinations of MI6, which created a bureaucratic war weakening the abilities of both services to fight the &lt;i&gt;actual&lt;/i&gt; war. It's an interesting case study in how hard it is to create organisations, even when involved in an existential fight.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  2/5.
	    Finished 14 November 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5083494406?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/secret-war-the-story-of-soe/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 21:32:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Painful Truth: The New Science of Our Aches, Agonies and Afflictions</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-painful-truth-the-new-science-of-our-aches-agonies-and-afflictions/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;The Painful Truth: The New Science of Our Aches, Agonies and Afflictions&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1628874970l/55539729._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Monty Lyman&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2021
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A book about pain, and why it isn't what we think.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The conventional wisdom is that pain is caused by damage, but it's more subtle than that. Pain is a &lt;i&gt;signal&lt;/i&gt; that can be triggered by damage, but can also be caused in response to less physical causes such as fear and a memory of past damage – and can be suppressed by activity or positive thinking, at least to a degree. This is awkward ground, as Lyman recognises: it's close to saying that "it's all in the mind", which is both literally true and deeply offensive to those suffering persistent pain. But it also offers hope that enormously dangerous pharmaceuticals can – sometimes – be replaced or complemented with cognitive therapies that might be effective.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Everyone has had the experience of being deeply engaged in some activity, incurring damage, and not noticing until afterwards. Soldiers frequently report it: they also sometimes feel significantly less pain from their injuries than civilians, because an injury that takes you off the battlefield makes you &lt;i&gt;safer than you were&lt;/i&gt;. The signals get mixed, and the pain felt changes accordingly. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's much to like in this book, not least a very thorough treatment of placebos. It does sometimes get lost in reporting yet another clinical trial, or yet another insight into neurochemistry. It sometimes feels a little too long and too well-referenced for a popular science take on the issues.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  3/5.
	    Finished 03 November 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5012548665?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-painful-truth-the-new-science-of-our-aches-agonies-and-afflictions/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 22:44:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Chessboard and the Web: Strategies of Connection in a Networked World</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-chessboard-and-the-web-strategies-of-connection-in-a-networked-world/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;The Chessboard and the Web: Strategies of Connection in a Networked World&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1488446839l/34446808._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Anne-Marie Slaughter&lt;/h2&gt;
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A book on grand strategy and its application to less-grand challenges in a world dominated by networks.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The central thesis of this book is that the world of hierarchies and direct state-to-state diplomacy – the chessboard – is giving way to a much more nuanced world in which state and non-state actors interact and co-operate in far ore complex ways – the web. The network effects change everything, from the nature of power and how it's used to the nature of leadership and how one can actually get things done.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's interesting to see the concepts of network science being applied to social and political science in a way that doesn't trivialise them. The applications range from analysis of interaction patterns to trying to engineer particular interactions such as improving information sharing.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's an obvious comparison to &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26245038.The_Seventh_Sense_Power__Fortune__and_Survival_in_the_Age_of_Networks" title="The Seventh Sense Power, Fortune, and Survival in the Age of Networks by Joshua Cooper Ramo" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;The Seventh Sense: Power, Fortune, and Survival in the Age of Networks&lt;/a&gt;, with which Slaughter contrasts her work, she being a "Wilsonian" humanist &lt;i&gt;versus&lt;/i&gt; Joshua Ramo's "Kissingerian" realist. Slaughter's view is that there is a need for more understanding of how small-scale interactions can happen – contrasting with Ramo's desire for aggressive "gatekeeping" of a US-led networked order. I can't help thinking that her view is more realistic and democratic.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 27 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4611651217?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-chessboard-and-the-web-strategies-of-connection-in-a-networked-world/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2022 18:51:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Atoms and Ashes: A Global History of Nuclear Disasters</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/atoms-and-ashes-a-global-history-of-nuclear-disasters/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Atoms and Ashes: A Global History of Nuclear Disasters&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1645247265l/59011975._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Serhii Plokhy&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2022
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	A history of nuclear energy in six disasters: five civilian and one military.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Competition seems to lie at the heart of all the problems: a lack of willingness to share details of accidents and near-accidents, and an unwillingness to learn if this requires changes in procedure. Collaboration seems lacking even within organisations and with regulators, while governments treat these matters as merely part of larger strategic concerns (even when they threaten to overwhelm them). It's also clear that the commercial operation of nuclear power is impossible without state subsidy, and acquiring this opens-up possibilities from regulatory capture – weakening requirements to make them attainable within a fixed cost – to outright bribery.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The science and engineering also seem lacking. The Castle Bravo (and other) nuclear tests massively under-estimate the weapons' yields, and this seems to be more the case the larger the bomb (culminating in the apocalyptic &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tsar_Bomba" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Tsar Bomba&lt;/a&gt;, which isn't covered in this book as it somewhat miraculously &lt;i&gt;wasn't&lt;/i&gt; actually an accident). But all the systems described make use of technology little changed since the 1930s: imagine if we were still driving cars from that era!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I find Plokhy's conclusions nuanced but weak. He decides that nuclear and renewable energy sources are both risky approaches to tackling climate change, but with completely different risk profiles: the former perhaps being too slow to start up and with huge accident risks; the latter relying on technologies as yet untested at the necessary scale. But in coming to his conclusion backing renewables and the phasing-out of nuclear stations (with which I entirely agree) he devotes &lt;i&gt;exactly two sentences&lt;/i&gt; to the problem of nuclear waste and spent fuel, which should surely be one of the major deciding factors. It's a strange omission at the end of a book that revolves around radiation hazards.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  3/5.
	    Finished 21 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4939077454?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/atoms-and-ashes-a-global-history-of-nuclear-disasters/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2022 11:47:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>We Are Bellingcat: Global Crime, Online Sleuths, and the Bold Future of News</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/we-are-bellingcat-global-crime-online-sleuths-and-the-bold-future-of-news/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;We Are Bellingcat: Global Crime, Online Sleuths, and the Bold Future of News&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1596434293l/54680228._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Eliot Higgins&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2021
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	The history of a still-evolving open-source intelligence collective.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Intelligence collection and analysis used to be limited to governments and a handful of companies. Not any longer: the tools are available on the open internet. Eliot Higgins realises that he can use them to investigate news stories, including the shooting-down of MH-17 over Ukraine. It's this investigation, in which he and his volunteer analysts manage to argue convincingly that the culprits were Russian-backed separatists using Russian anti-aircraft missiles, that really demonstrates how much information can now be found and cross-corollated. The result is for formation of Bellingcat, an amorphous group of international investigators organised in a way that closely resembles that of an open-source software project, where all that matters is an individuals' ability and willingness to share findings, and to have them challenged and possibly refuted in the search for the best explanations.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The book was written before the Russian attack on Ukraine, and so will demand a follow-up given Bellingcat's deep involvement in tracking the conflict and digging-into the details of individual incidents.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  5/5.
	    Finished 16 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4688233164?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/we-are-bellingcat-global-crime-online-sleuths-and-the-bold-future-of-news/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 14:40:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Childhood's End</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/childhoods-end/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Childhood's End&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1320552628l/414999._SY160_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Arthur C. Clarke&lt;/h2&gt;
	    1953
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	An entirely unexpected take on alien invasion. The aliens come, take over – and then allow humanity to proceed as its wants, without revealing themselves or really taking much control at all. Why? What are they hiding? And how is it that, when they &lt;i&gt;do&lt;/i&gt; reveal themselves, they look so familiar?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The reasons are all thought out with the rigour and open-endedness you'd expect from Arthur C. Clarke. The very fact that he can build such a narrative is a testament to his abilities as a world-creator, with an ability to pose questions and then not answer them definitively without this spoiling the enjoyment of the story.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 16 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2902185066?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/childhoods-end/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 14:33:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Spike: The Virus vs. The People - the Inside Story</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/spike-the-virus-vs-the-people-the-inside-story/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Spike: The Virus vs. The People - the Inside Story&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
	&lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1626896615l/57095247._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
	  &lt;h2&gt;Jeremy Farrar&lt;/h2&gt;
	    2021
	  &lt;p&gt;
	    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
	I wonder if this book was too early: were we sufficiently out of the coronavirus pandemic to assess it and our healthcare systems' abilities to deal with it? Perhaps. But this is a good look at the early days from the perspective of the Wellcome Trust, one of the world's biggest medical charities.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  4/5.
	    Finished 16 October 2022.
	  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	    (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4145716114?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/spike-the-virus-vs-the-people-the-inside-story/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 14:29:20 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>