<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about review)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/review.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 17:41:21 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Dancing with a Lenovo Duet</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2021/04/08/dancing-with-a-lenovo-duet/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Chromebook that behaves like a proper tablet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2021/04/08/dancing-with-a-lenovo-duet/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>android</category><category>chromebook</category><category>hardware</category><category>review</category><category>tablet</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2021/04/08/dancing-with-a-lenovo-duet/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 08:02:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Impressions of Pervasive 2010</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2010/05/21/impressions-pervasive-2010/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've spent this week at the &lt;a href="http://www.pervasive2010.org"&gt;Pervasive 2010 conference&lt;/a&gt; on pervasive computing, along with the &lt;a href="http://www.pmmps.org"&gt;Programming Methods for Mobile and Pervasive Systems&lt;/a&gt; workshop I co-arranged with &lt;a href="http://www.dominicduggan.org/"&gt;Dominic Duggan&lt;/a&gt;. Both events have been fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PMMPS workshop is something we've wanted to run for a while, bringing together the programming language and pervasive/mobile communities to see where languages  ought to go. We received a diverse set of submissions: keynotes from Roy Campbell and Aaron Quigley, talks covering topics including debugging, software processes, temporal aspects (me), context collectionvisual programming ang a lot more. Some threads emerge quite strongly, but I think they'll have to wait for a later post after I've collected my thoughts a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main conference included many  papers so good that it seems a shame to single any out. The following are simply those that spoke most strongly to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Panorama and Cascadia.&lt;/strong&gt; The University of Washington presented work on a "complex" events system, combining lower-level raw events. Simple sensor events are noisy and often limited in their coverage. Cascadiais an event service that allows complex events to be defined over the raw event stream, using Bayesian particle filters to interpolate missing events or those from uncovered areas: so it's possible in principle to inferentially  "sense" someone's location even in places without explicit sensor coverage, using a model of the space being observed. This is something that could be generalised to other model-based sensor streams. The Panorama tool allows end-users to specify complex events by manipulating thresholds, which seems little unsatisfactory: there's no principled way to determine the thresholds, and it still begs the question of how to program with the uncertain event stream. Still, I have to say this is the first complex event system I've seen that I actually believe could work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eyecatcher.&lt;/strong&gt; How do you stop people hiding from a camera, or playing-up to it? Work from Ochanomizu University in Japan places a small display on top of the camera, which can be used to present images to catch the subject's attention and to suggest poses or actions. (Another version barks like a dog, to attract your pet's attention.)I have to say this research is very Japanese, a very unusual but perceptive view of the world and the problems appropriate for research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emotion modeling&lt;/strong&gt;. Jennifer Healey from Intel described how to monitor and infer emotions from physiological data. The main problem is that there is no common language for describing emotions -- "anxious" is good for some and bad for others -- so getting ground truth is hard even given extensive logging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indoor location tracking for non-experts&lt;/strong&gt;. More University of Washington work, this time looking at an indoor location system simple enough to be used by non-experts such as rehabilitation therapists. They used powerline positioning, injecting different frequencies into a home's power network and detecting the radiated signal using what are essentially AM radios. Interestingly one of the most important factors was the aesthetics of the sensors: people don't want ugly boxes in their home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transfer learning&lt;/strong&gt;. Tim van Kasteren of the University of Amsterdam has generated one of the most useful smart-home data sets, used across the community (including by several of my students). He reported experiences with transfering machine-learned classifiers from one sensor network to another, by mapping the data into a new, synthetic feature space. He also used the known distribution of features from the first network to condition the learning algorithhm in the second, to improve convergence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Common Sense&lt;/strong&gt;. Work from UC Berkeley on a platform for participative sensing: &lt;a href="http://www.communitysensing.org/"&gt;CommonSense&lt;/a&gt;. The idea is to place environmental sensors onto commodity mobile devices, and give them to street cleaners and others "out and about" in a community. The great thing about this is that is gives information on pollution and the like to the communities themselves, directly, rather than mediated through a (possibly indifferent or otherwise) State agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Energy-aware data traffic management&lt;/strong&gt;. I should add the disclaimer that is work by my colleague, Mirco Musolesi of the University of  St Andrews. Sensor nodes need to be careful about the energy they use to transmit data back to their base station. This work compares a range of strategies that trade-off the accuracy of returned data with the amount of traffic exchanged and so the impact on the nodoe's battery. This is //really// important for environmental sensing, and makes me think about further modifying the models to account for what's being sensed to trade-off information content as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tutorials&lt;/strong&gt; AJ Brush did a wonderful tutorial on how to do user surveys. This is something we've done ourselves, and it was great to see the issues nailed-down -- along with war stories of how to plan and conduct a survey for greatest validity and impact. Equally, John Krumm did a fantastic overview of signal processing, particle filters, hidden Markov models and the like that make the maths &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; more accessible than it normally is. Adrian Friday heroically took the graveyard slot with experiences and ideas about system support for pervasive systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first large conference I've attended for a while, for various reasons, and it's been a great week both scientifically and socially. The organisers at the University of Helsinki deserve an enormous vote of thanks for their efforts. Pervasive next year will be in San Francisco, an I'll definitely be there -- hopefully with a paper to present :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>conference</category><category>pervasive computing</category><category>programming</category><category>review</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2010/05/21/impressions-pervasive-2010/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2010 05:00:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The only computer science book worth reading twice?</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2010/05/14/cs-book-worth-reading-twice/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was talking to one of my students earlier, and lent him a book to read over summer. It was only after he'd left that I realised  that -- for me at any rate -- the book I'd given him is probably the most seminal work in the whole of computer science, and certainly the book that's most influenced my career and research interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what's the book? &lt;em&gt;Structure and interpretation of computer programs&lt;/em&gt; by Hal Abelson and Jerry Sussman &lt;span&gt; (MIT Press. 1984. ISBN 0-262-01077-1), also known as &lt;em&gt;SICP&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;The book's still in print, but -- even better -- is &lt;a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/"&gt;available online in its entirety&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;OK, everyone has their favourite book: why's this one so special to me? The first reason is the time I first encountered it: in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cs.newcastle.ac.uk/"&gt;Newcastle upon Tyne&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;span&gt;the second year of my first degree. I was still finding my way in computer science, and this book was a recommended text after you'd finished the first programming courses. It's the book that introduced me to programming &lt;em&gt;as it could be&lt;/em&gt; (rather than programming &lt;em&gt;as it was&lt;/em&gt;, in Pascal at the time). What I mean by that is that SICP starts out by introducing the elements of programming -- values, names, binding, control and so on -- and then runs with them to explore a quite dazzling breadth of issues including:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;lambda-abstraction and higher-order computation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;complex data structures, including structures with embedded computational content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;modularity and mutability&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;streams&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;lazy evaluation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;interpreter and compiler construction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;storage management, garbage collection and virtual memory
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;machine code
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;domain-specific languages&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;span&gt;...and so forth. The list of concepts is bewildering, and only stays coherent because the authors are skilled writers devoted to their craft. But it's also a remarkable achievement to handle all these concepts within a single language framework -- Scheme -- in such a way that each builds on what's gone before.
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The second reason is the way in which Hal and Jerry view everything as an exercise in language design:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;We have also obtained a glimpse of another crucial idea about languages and program design. This is the approach of stratified design, the notion that a complex system should be structured as a sequence of levels that are described using a sequence of languages. Each level is constructed by combining parts that are regarded as primitive at that level, and the parts constructed at each level are used as primitives at the next level. The language used at each level of a stratified design has primitives, means of combination, and means of abstraction appropriate to that level of detail.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Layered abstraction of course is second nature to all computer scientists. What's novel in this view is that each level should be &lt;em&gt;programmable&lt;/em&gt;: that the layers are all about computation and transformation, and not simply about hiding information. We don't see that in the mainstream of programming languages, because layering doesn't extend the language at all: Java is Java from top to bottom, with class and libraries but no new control structures. If a particular domain has concepts that would benefit from dedicated language constructs, that's just tough. Conversely (and this is something that very much interests me) if there are constructs it'd be desirable &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to have in some domain, they can't be removed. (Within the language, anyway: Java-ME dumps some capabilities in the interests of running on small devices, but that's not something you can do without re-writing the compiler.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third influential feature is the clear-sighted view of what computer science is actually about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The computer revolution is a revolution in the way we think and in the way we express what we think.  The essence of this change is the emergence of what might best be called &lt;em&gt;procedural epistemology&lt;/em&gt; -- the study of the structure of knowledge from an imperative point of view, as opposed to the more declarative point of view taken by classical mathematical subjects. Mathematics provides a framework for dealing precisely with notions of "what is."  Computation provides a framework for dealing precisely with notions of "how to."&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've taken a view before about &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2010/04/computer-microscope/"&gt;computers being the new microscopes&lt;/a&gt;, opening-up new science on their own as well as facilitating existing approaches. The "how to" aspect of computer science re-appears everywhere in this: in describing the behaviours of sensor networks that can adapt while continuing the reflect the phenomena they've been deployed to sense; in the interpretation of large-scale data mined and mashed-up across the web; in capturing scientific methods and processes for automation; and so forth. The richness of these domains mitigates against packaged software and encourages integration through programming languages like &lt;a href="http://www.r-project.org"&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;, so that the interfaces and structures remain "soft" and open to experimentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;When I looked at my copy, the date I'd written on the inside was September 1988. So a book I bought nearly 22 years ago is still relevant. &lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;In fact, I'd go further and say that it's the only computer science book of that age that I'd happily and usefully read again without it being just for historical interest: the content has barely aged at all. That's not all that unusual for mathematics books, but it's almost unheard of in computer science, where the ideas move so quickly and where much of what's written about is ephemeral rather than foundational. It goes to show how well SICP nailed the core concepts. In this sense, it's certainly one of the very few  books on computer science that it's worth reading twice (or more). SICP is to computer science what Feynman's &lt;em&gt;Lectures on Physics&lt;/em&gt; are to physics: an accessible distillation of the essence of the subject that's stood the test of time.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>book</category><category>programming</category><category>review</category><category>scheme</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2010/05/14/cs-book-worth-reading-twice/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2010 05:00:35 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>