<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about reviews)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/reviews.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 15:51:18 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>SS-GB</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/ss-gb/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1689536758l/63326204._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Len Deighton
	  (1979)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      An alternative history that has aged well. The premise is quite common: what if Nazi Germany had invaded Britain in the Spring of 1941, and succeeded? The plot revolves around rescuing the King and retrieving atomic secrets, both to be sent to America.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But it's the politics of a Nazi occupation that clearly most fascinated Deighton, because he build a labyrinth of plots and counter-plots between Army, SS, British Resistance, and American isolationism. These internecine struggles are actually quite familiar from the actual history of Nazi occupations, so it's quite fascinating to see them transplanted to a fictional Britain. It's so well done that it's a shame it isn't part of a series (of which Deighton wrote several).
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Saturday 3 August, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6432286432?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/ss-gb/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Islands of Abandonment</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/islands-of-abandonment/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1645656810l/41830657._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Cal Flyn
	  (2021)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A book one perhaps shouldn't enjoy as much as I did, but as an exploration of what happens when humans leave a landscape – whether one they've polluted or simply one they've abandoned – it's actually quite reassuring even in the midst of it's being shocking.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There is alost nowhere that's so polluted that life of some kind can't regain a hold, given enough time. That (as Flyn herself is at pains to point out) is not an excuse or a invitation to more spoliation, or to not prosecuting polluters; but it is a reminder that we avoid pollution and climate change &lt;i&gt;for ourselves&lt;/i&gt;, not because the natural world will be irretrievably damaged if we don't: the climate emergency is about saving ourselves, not about saving the planet.&lt;br&gt;
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Saturday 1 April, 2023.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4954082332?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/islands-of-abandonment/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Dawn of Everything</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-dawn-of-everything/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1656329733l/59603245._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	David Graeber
	  (2021)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A book with an amazign ambition: to re-visit and re-interpret the whole of political theory from a basis in modern anthropology and archaeology.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The authors have done a deep dive into not only modern archaeological evidence but also into the nearly-forgotten thinkers of the early Enlightenment. And they make some startling discoveries. Wehn we think of the Enlightenment, we think of something unique to a particular moment in European history when the rights of god and kings were being questioned for the first time. But many of the thinkers didn't see it that was at all: they were responding to critiques of the European system by Native American observers, who – far from being overawed and impressed by modernity – were disgusted by the poverty and arbitrary violence they saw: so different to their own societies. This re-discovery leads to further re-considerations: of the linear flow of development, the occurrance of an agricultural revolution as a particular turning-point moment (and whether it persisted), the emergence (or not) of hierarchies and kings, all backed up evidentially from recent sources.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Graeber and Wengrow take issue with the narrative of inevitability in the route to modern civilisation. In part this is based on the observation that many "events", such as the adoption of agriculture, weren't "events" at all, but happened over a period of centuries, were unevenly adopted and frequently rolled-back. Their central theme is that it's a mistake to think of early civilisations as blank canvases in which nothing political happened: that's an assumption, and not one supported in any way by the physical or even the literary evidence.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;They frame their ideas of liberty around three freedoms: freedom to move, freedom to disobey the orders of others, and freedom to re-imagine society. (The last is obviously very different and more abstract than the first two.) They contend that modern societies have become "stuck" without these freedoms as a matter of choice, not of historical inevitability.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's a persuasive narrative, impeded slightly by the very wealth of detail they marshall in its support. And there are some crious omissions: no consideration of anarchy or Kropotkin's &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/51306.Mutual_Aid" title="Mutual Aid by Pyotr Kropotkin" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Mutual Aid&lt;/a&gt;, and (more surprisingly) no reference to Isiah Berlin's &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/36551865.Two_Concepts_of_Liberty_An_Inaugural_Lecture_delivered_before_the_University_of_Oxford_on_31_October_1958" title="Two Concepts of Liberty An Inaugural Lecture delivered before the University of Oxford on 31 October 1958 by Isaiah Berlin" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Two Concepts of Liberty&lt;/a&gt;, although his ideas are clearly part of their intellectual background. Still, this is an intensely political book that deserves a wide reading, if only to defeat the notion that we've somehow arrived at a civilisational peak from which there's no sense in deviating.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Sunday 5 February, 2023.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4931822228?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-dawn-of-everything/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Painful Truth: The New Science of Our Aches, Agonies and Afflictions</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-painful-truth-the-new-science-of-our-aches-agonies-and-afflictions/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1628874970l/55539729._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Monty Lyman
	  (2021)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A book about pain, and why it isn't what we think.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The conventional wisdom is that pain is caused by damage, but it's more subtle than that. Pain is a &lt;i&gt;signal&lt;/i&gt; that can be triggered by damage, but can also be caused in response to less physical causes such as fear and a memory of past damage – and can be suppressed by activity or positive thinking, at least to a degree. This is awkward ground, as Lyman recognises: it's close to saying that "it's all in the mind", which is both literally true and deeply offensive to those suffering persistent pain. But it also offers hope that enormously dangerous pharmaceuticals can – sometimes – be replaced or complemented with cognitive therapies that might be effective.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Everyone has had the experience of being deeply engaged in some activity, incurring damage, and not noticing until afterwards. Soldiers frequently report it: they also sometimes feel significantly less pain from their injuries than civilians, because an injury that takes you off the battlefield makes you &lt;i&gt;safer than you were&lt;/i&gt;. The signals get mixed, and the pain felt changes accordingly. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's much to like in this book, not least a very thorough treatment of placebos. It does sometimes get lost in reporting yet another clinical trial, or yet another insight into neurochemistry. It sometimes feels a little too long and too well-referenced for a popular science take on the issues.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	3/5.
	  Finished Thursday 3 November, 2022.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5012548665?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-painful-truth-the-new-science-of-our-aches-agonies-and-afflictions/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Munros in Winter: Experience Scotland's Most Exhilerating Mountains in the Company of a Master Climber</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-munros-in-winter-experience-scotlands-most-exhilerating-mountains-in-the-company-of-a-master-climber/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1181116396l/1114998.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Martin Moran
	  (1986)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      This book tells part of the amazing story of an amazing man, who came back from serious injury to first climb all the Scottish Munros in a single winter season. It's a stunning accomplishment by any measure, and set Moran up for a future as a mountaineering guide before his tragic death.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'm sorry that it's not a better book. The prose is quite wooden, lacking all the flourish and power that one finds in, for example, &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/19294505.Savage_Arena" title="Savage Arena by Joe Tasker" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Savage Arena&lt;/a&gt;. As just one example amongst many:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;"Only with sadness did we leave the lovely Etive, thinking with regret of those roads and glens of Argyll that our journey would not traverse again."&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's a shame that the writing doesn't live up either to the country being described or the challenge being successfully attempted.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	2/5.
	  Finished Wednesday 23 February, 2022.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4611654406?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-munros-in-winter-experience-scotlands-most-exhilerating-mountains-in-the-company-of-a-master-climber/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Appeasing Hitler: Chamberlain, Churchill and the Road to War</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/appeasing-hitler-chamberlain-churchill-and-the-road-to-war/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1590337332l/49568828._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Tim Bouverie
	  (2019)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      The history of the not-out-finest-hour that preceded our finest hour.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This is a very balanced treatment of a period that it's difficult to treat fairly. It manages this by keeping a clear focus on what the protagonists know and believe at the time, without losing sight of whether those beliefs were reasonable: often they weren't, and in the final analysis the idea that appeasement could &lt;i&gt;ever&lt;/i&gt; have succeeded is well and truly exploded. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The use of extensive quotes from private correspondence is extremely revealing of the inner motivations of many, not least Chamberlain. But it also reveals something that I'd not noticed before: the subtle change in the meaning of the word &lt;i&gt;appeasement&lt;/i&gt; over the course of the period. In the early years it comes across as simply a way of re-introducing equity into international relations, and only later acquires the sub-text of surrender and cowardice that it now has.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;My only minor criticism is that there are a few places where a little more clarity as to the deceptions going on could have been welcome. The "Polish provocations" used by the Nazis to ramp-up the tensions prior to the attack, for example, were almost entirely imagined propaganda, culminating in the staged "incidents" used as the final justification.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	5/5.
	  Finished Sunday 30 January, 2022.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3237527205?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/appeasing-hitler-chamberlain-churchill-and-the-road-to-war/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 30 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Covent Garden Ladies</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-covent-garden-ladies/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1597761814l/54869220._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Hallie Rubenhold
	  (2005)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      An entertaining dive into a part of 18th-century society that's too often only considered voyeuristically. The survival of "Harris' List" provides a starting point, but it's the detailed archival study and the willingness to dig into the histories of the three main protagonists that really sets this book apart. In doing so it also gets to uncover some of the grimier realities of living on (or close to) the streets in a period when money was all that really counted in terms of life chances.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Rubenhold is very sympathetic to the Covent Garden ladies. "Prostitutes" (or "harlots" in the TV adaptation) is a too-harsh judgement: many adopted sex work only because society gave them no other options, or adopted it only periodically when forced to by poverty, or as a semi-acceptable companion to stage-work. She is also unforgiving of the male customers, who avoided most social sanctions or consequences.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The fact that "Harris' List" ran for nearly four decades (and that we have examples of most of them) also makes it a revealing social document as the mores and morals of society change across the 18th century. The descriptions become less straightforward, more ornate and (one would imagine) less useful as time goes by and the publishers become more susceptible to legal action for obscenity (even as the underlying social conditions remain largely unaddressed).
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Saturday 22 January, 2022.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4399838387?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-covent-garden-ladies/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Cosmogramma</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/cosmogramma/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1636392585l/59482526._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Courttia Newland
	  (2017)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A great collection of new science fiction. Some new premises, and older ones deftly handled.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	3/5.
	  Finished Saturday 15 January, 2022.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4339491572?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/cosmogramma/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Nation to Nation: Scotland's Place in the World</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/nation-to-nation-scotlands-place-in-the-world/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1615952365l/57437918._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Stephen Gethins
	  (2021)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A former MP discusses Scotland's now and future foreign policy.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;(Full disclosure: Gethins is a Professor in Practice of International Relations at the University of St Andrews, where I also work.)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This is a detailed and wide-ranging work, exploring the past, present, and potential future of Scotland's foreign policy "footprint". It's quick to point out that even sub-State actors have such a footprint, and show how the Scottish government is able to work with (and sometimes against) the wider UK government in liaison with other international players, and the tensions and missed opportunities that arise. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Gethins is SNP (as am I), and as such has a clear preference for an independent Scotland. He tries valiantly to consider the potential future without independence, and how Scotland might in that case contribute more effectively to the UK's efforts. This doesn't quite succeed as an approach, perhaps because Gethins can't imagine that the UK can execute what would be needed to make such a future happen, for example as set out in &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/56902903.How_Britain_Ends_English_Nationalism_and_the_Rebirth_of_Four_Nations" title="How Britain Ends English Nationalism and the Rebirth of Four Nations by Gavin Esler" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;How Britain Ends: English Nationalism and the Rebirth of Four Nations&lt;/a&gt; – and I have to say I agree with him on that. He quotes many influential Europeans (and others) who welcome Scotland's policy stance, and would welcome independence were it to come, which is clearly set out to address some of the uncertainties that doomed the "indyref" of 2014. It does a good job of this, as well as of showing how much Scotland as a region has to offer in the foreign policy sphere, and how little is being made of it so far.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	3/5.
	  Finished Saturday 8 January, 2022.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3940634960?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/nation-to-nation-scotlands-place-in-the-world/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ten Days that Shook the World</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/ten-days-that-shook-the-world/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1328863932l/52042._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	John   Reed
	  (1919)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      An eye-witness account of the Bolshevik takeover of the Russian Revolution. Perhaps too detailed for anything except reference, but fascinating as a counterpoint to the more accepted (and Bolshevik-defined) history of their rise as a steady, inevitable, unanimous undertaking by the people. Here there are disagreements, armed struggles, and dissent from within the workers' Soviets and unions.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's also notable that there's (as far as I can tell) exactly one mention of Stalin, as People's Commissar for Nationalities, again underlining the degree of re-writing of history that took place later. Stalin is far from being a prominent individual, or even a serious leader in the early days of what became the Soviet Union, and his later ascendancy is entirely unheralded in his early actions.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	3/5.
	  Finished Saturday 1 January, 2022.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2367720516?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/ten-days-that-shook-the-world/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>