<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about reviews)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/reviews.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2024 12:47:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Romanovs: 1613-1918</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-romanovs-1613-1918/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1435023227l/21094391._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Simon Sebag Montefiore
	  (2016)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      When complimented on his armies capturing Berlin at the end of the Second World War, Stalin famously replied that "Tsar Alexander made it to Paris." This book describes how, and why, that happened – and why it meant to much to Stalin, on whom Sebag Montefirore is of course a recognised expert.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The sweep of Romanov history is epic in all senses. It's impossible not to realise how deeply &lt;i&gt;personal&lt;/i&gt; their rule was, identifying their own reigns absolutely with Russia and its greatness. The main characters are all flawed in tragic ways, sometimes grotesque but equally often brilliant and self-aware within the limitations of their eras – which none ever really managed to trascend, with the possible exception of Peter and later Catherine, each known as "the Great" for that reason.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The story is made powerful by recent research in the Russian archives and access to previously-unkown letters between Alexander II and his mistress, and later between Nicholas II and Alexandra. They highlight the impact of extra-marital affairs on high policy right across the Romonov era: it's often hard to keep track of who is related to (or sleeping with) whom, or to understand the true importance of some of the less well-known characters in the story who may have have had an advisory impact far beyond what their "official" position might suggest.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's a book that's hard on autocracy – but also quite hard on the alternatives that came after. Sebag Montefiore sees a continuity between the tsars, Lenin, Stalin, and Putin, and almost seems to regard it as inevitable that Russia will need strongman leadership. One can perhaps hope not.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	5/5.
	  Finished Saturday 23 March, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1522092865?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-romanovs-1613-1918/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Escape from Model Land: How Mathematical Models Can Lead Us Astray and What We Can Do About It</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/escape-from-model-land-how-mathematical-models-can-lead-us-astray-and-what-we-can-do-about-it/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://s.gr-assets.com/assets/nophoto/book/111x148-bcc042a9c91a29c1d680899eff700a03.png" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Erica Thompson
	  (2022)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A thoughtful look at modelling by an experienced climate modeller.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;What are models &lt;i&gt;for&lt;/i&gt;? The most common answer would be "to predict the future behaviour of some system," but Thompson argues a far more subtle line: that the most important models often &lt;i&gt;fail&lt;/i&gt; to be predictive in any real sense. Much of this is down to problems of validation, especially in climate models for which we have no experience of the world the models are trying to predict.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;An even more subtle mistake is regarding all models as "cameras" that simply observe the world. That's true for the more abstract kinds of modelling, where one is trying to understand possible behaviours of systems in general without tying them to specific circumstances. But the models with which most people are familiar act ore like "engines" that can perturb the system they're purporting simply to observe by baing used as drivers for policy. Climate and epidemic models seek to warn as well as predict and understand, but this exacerbates the problems of validation: if the model's predictions &lt;i&gt;don't&lt;/i&gt; come to pass, perhaps this is because policy-makers took corrective actions in response, or maybe bacause they didn't intervent effectively enough. This isn't a reason to give up on modelling altogether: how else are we to understand complex systems, and how else are we to respond rationally to them? But it does mean that the notion of "following the science" problematic.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Thompson also wrestles with the problem of groupthink amongst modellers, who often share a common overallping background. I agree this is a problem, but the idea that we can increase diversity in the community easily seems flawed to me. Modellers share a scientific viewpoint and a belief in modelling, and no-one who doesn't will ever be able to effectively engage with the models or their arguments. Perhaps it's enough that scientists are always advisors and never decision-makers, and allow politicians to deal with the integration of different choices and values – although that split isn't always appreciated by the public, and is often (as in the covid-19 pandemic) deliberately blurred to allow less-trusted politicians to draw credibility from more-trusted scientists and doctors.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Overall I think this is a lucid and valiant attempt to summarise and explore the benefits and limitations of models, and science in general, when it impacts directly on the wider world. It deserves to be widely read in the scientific community so that we can better understand our place in policies that we often unavoidably have to influence.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Friday 22 March, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5150032848?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/escape-from-model-land-how-mathematical-models-can-lead-us-astray-and-what-we-can-do-about-it/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Diary of an MP's Wife: Inside and Outside Power</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/diary-of-an-mps-wife-inside-and-outside-power/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1599934352l/55310315._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Sasha Swire
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      An insight into the British politics of the 2010s. And not a pretty sight.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The pitch for this book is that, as a political wife, the author had a unique ringside seat from which to observe the goings-on the (mostly male) politicians. And it's true that she has plenty of insight into them and into her own position in the circle.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But she also exposes herself as almost a caricature of a Tory. She accepts the misogyny and crudeness of the male MPs as just how it is, and utterly lacks any understanding of why anyone would disagree with her own positions. She can't accept, for example, that Remainers were sincere and their misgivings might be valid, or that the EU is anything other that fascinated with the idea of humiliating Britain. She constantly refers to the Labour party as "Marxists" and trots-out the usual tropes of how they would bankrupt the country, despite the fact that their "extreme left-wing" positions would be entirely mainstream in many European countries. She's clear-eyed and unenthusiastic about Boris Johnson as Prime Minister, but then fawns over him when he wins his election landslide and glides over the time-bomb he planted on the Irish border issue, even though this was evident at the time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The overwhelming theme, returned to again and again, is how self-interested the political class is, focused entirely on who's up, who's down, and how if affects their own careers. Lots of dinner parties, gentlemen's clubs, and holidays: one is left amazed by how shallow everyone is.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's not a bad book, and an enjoyably light read. But politically insightful it isn't, other than to highlight the trivial nature of politicians.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	3/5.
	  Finished Friday 23 February, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6052150109?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/diary-of-an-mps-wife-inside-and-outside-power/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Death of Grass</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-death-of-grass/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1486838846l/941731._SY160_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	John Christopher
	  (1956)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      Post-apocalyptic fiction of a determinedly British kind. It's not a bad book, and has a certain complexity to it in exploring how people's attitudes might change when faced with the destruction of normal civilisation.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A deadly virus destroys all grass-like plants, thereby eliminating almost all food crops and the cattle that they feed. Worried the government might atom-bomb the major population centres, a small group leave London to make their way to a Lake District valley. On the way they encounter looters, towns gone feral to protect themselves – and become feral themselves, willing to kill to survive. In some ways it reads like &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/7624.Lord_of_the_Flies" title="Lord of the Flies by William Golding" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Lord of the Flies&lt;/a&gt; with adults and a more pervading sense of long-term doom.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But it's also very much a novel of its time, full of racism, sexism, classism, deference, stiff upper lips, and a sense of self-justification wrapped-up as duty. That makes it a hard read, and it doesn't really have enough force to balance that out. Manu similar points are made elsewhere, for example in &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/93269.Earth_Abides" title="Earth Abides by George R. Stewart" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Earth Abides&lt;/a&gt;, without the 1950s baggage.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	2/5.
	  Finished Sunday 11 February, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4779364492?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/the-death-of-grass/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>This Is How They Tell Me the World Ends: The Cyberweapons Arms Race</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/this-is-how-they-tell-me-the-world-ends-the-cyberweapons-arms-race/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1610927353l/49247043._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Nicole Perlroth
	  (2021)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A hugely detailed and deeply researched history of the market for "zero-day: exploits, the faults and technologies underlying computer viruses and ransomware. It's a hugely complicated and technical field which Perlroth does an amazing job of making accessible to a non-technical audience. (I should probably say here that I teach computer security.)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Most of the book is a real page-turner, deeply embedded with the government agencies, companies, and hackers who compose the zero-day market. It's scathing of the US' trying to play both sides of the street, developing and buying zero-days in order to collect intelligence while weakening the security of ordinary users in the process by not informing the software developers of the problems they've found. They clearly knew this was dangerous, and even developed a doctrine for us: "NOBUS", bugs that "no-one but us" would be smart enough to find or develop. This idea goes wrong spectacularly, as other nations realise how cheaply they too can have cyberweapons programmes: ironically they're encouraged by the deployment of the Stuxnet virus to damage the Iranian nuclear programme. The leaks of the NSA's zero-day stockpile by the Shadow Brokers – an event that's somewhat under-explored – and their later use in hacks against US elections, are payback for hubris.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Perlroth is scathing of the Trump presidency's neglect of cybersecurity and unwillingness to sanction Russia for known attacks – in part because it might cast doubt on Trump's legitimacy as an elected president, but also seemingly from willful blindness and a mistrust of the professionals (including the military) tasked with protecting US networks. She was writing during the pandemic and before Trump conceded the 2020 election (to the extent that he ever did), and so if anything she understated the impacts of disinformation spreading.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The conclusions are a little breathless, but well-intentioned and technically appropriate, if a little US-centric – and in fairness the US has at least attempted to set up a more transparent approach to managing cyberweapons, even though the approach is drastically compromised by the desire to keep intelligence-gathering capabilities. Cybersecurity is an area where offence and defence are closely intertwined, and there's a strong argument that the costs to society of the former mandate a focus on the latter. We need to accept that many cyberweapons that are used (or leaked) can be reverse-engineered and re-used against their original developers with little real up-front financial investment.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's some editing. including a repeated mis-use of "affect" rather than "effect", and a really disastrous throw-away reference to the book &lt;i&gt;Dune&lt;/i&gt;, the description of which is almost entirely wrong: surely an editor should have picked that up?
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Sunday 21 January, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4691376169?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/this-is-how-they-tell-me-the-world-ends-the-cyberweapons-arms-race/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Edible Economics: A Hungry Economist Explains the World</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/edible-economics-a-hungry-economist-explains-the-world/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1656314692l/61030740._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Ha-Joon Chang
	  (2022)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A book that combines food with economics? Not really.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'm torn by this book. I enjoyed the food parts, especially the author's anecdotes about his move to the UK from Korea, and how he's observed the UK's food scene change from incredibly insular and conservative to amazingly open and dynamic over the course of a couple of decades. It's a change I also lived through and remember well.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I also enjoyed the economics. Chang is an eclectic collector of economic theories – all the more surprising because he's an academic. He has an appropriate degree of scepticism for ideology and single explanation of complex questions, which is refreshing. He skewers some of the common myths, such as the "explanation" that poor countreis stay poor because their people don't work hard enough, ingoring the massive structural factors in play. He's equally scathing about the other "explanation" about the free-trade roots of the successes of the US and UK economies, given that they were actually massively protectionist during their main periods of growth. And he makes several policy suggestions for modern economies.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But.... as a book, I don't think it works at all. The conceit of explaining economics through food remains just that: a conceit that's not really threaded through the narrative in a meaningful way. The links are often just too tenuous. To give one example, a chapter that leads with anchovies ends up talking about natural-resource extraction economics using the example of bird guano – well, birds eat anchovies, so... Most of the chapters are basically diviided between food and economics with an often desperate attempt to tie them together. The economics is accessible, and a writer who can do that probably doesn't need a gimmick to structure his work.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	3/5.
	  Finished Saturday 20 January, 2024.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6013201080?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/edible-economics-a-hungry-economist-explains-the-world/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>They Called It Passchendaele</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/they-called-it-passchendaele/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1412445742l/1623876._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Lyn Macdonald
	  (1978)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A military and social history of the Third Battle of Ypres, heavily supported by material from the soldiers who were there – the Allied soldiers only, which is a shame, as it would have been nice to hear the defenders' perspective too.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's trite to say that the story is horrific. Were it not that it's so well-known in outline, it would be unbelievable that anyone could live through such a battle, or survive at all on the moonscape that Flanders was reduced to by then. The soldiers' own stories, which Macdonald both quotes from memoirs and obtains from interviews, emphasise the sheer &lt;i&gt;randomness&lt;/i&gt; of the deaths. There are so many stories of one man being killed when the man standing right next to him survives, or leaving a trench or shell-hole only for a shell to immediately kill everyone else who remained.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's a common trope aboutthe unfeelingness of senior officers towards their own men, but that isn't on show here – with the possible exception of Douglas Haig, who adopted a deliberate strategy of attrition that accepted casualities as long as the other side was taking them too. The divisional commanders, however, are shown to have protested many times about the timing and purpose of attacks, with one (in charge of the Canadian divisions who eventually took the Passchendaele ridge) refusing to attack at all until he had positioned all the supports and artillery he needed – and then succeeded when others had failed.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's terrible irony to the whole campaign. At the end of the battle, the Allies were left in possession of ground that they'd lost in the &lt;i&gt;First&lt;/i&gt; Battle of Ypres when the defenders had been Belgian and French (and some of their bodies, still in fine uniform, are surfaced by the shellfire). And later, when the final German attack of 1918 happens, the troops are pushed back to a line that had first been proposed by their own commander in 1915 – for which suggestion he was cashiered. It's a fitting summary of the pointlessness (in hindsight) of much of the First World War.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Sunday 31 December, 2023.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6100813932?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/they-called-it-passchendaele/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Around the World in Eighty Games: From Tarot to Tic-Tac-Toe, Catan to Chutes and Ladders, a Mathematician Unlocks the Secrets of the World's Greatest Games</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/around-the-world-in-eighty-games-from-tarot-to-tic-tac-toe-catan-to-chutes-and-ladders-a-mathematician-unlocks-the-secrets-of-the-worlds-greatest-games/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1680592896l/123204511._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Marcus du Sautoy
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A world tour of the world's board (and other) games. All the usual ones are here, plus others that I guarantee will be new to everyone. The games of Africa remain under-known.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;"Unlocking the secrets" is an overblown description of how maths comes into the story. There's a focus on game theory and decision theory, as one would expect, with a lot of consideration of symmetry (du Sautoy's own research area) and some autobiographical details too. There's &lt;i&gt;too little&lt;/i&gt; maths in many ways, but perhaps &lt;i&gt;too much&lt;/i&gt; for a non-mathematician.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The most interesting application comes from silence: two people are asked the same question three times, but it is answerable only on the third asking (the first two having provided information by the fact that neither could answer previously). Very clever.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Two entirely imaginary games also put in an appearence: Azad from &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18630.The_Player_of_Games__Culture___2_" title="The Player of Games (Culture, #2) by Iain M. Banks" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;The Player of Games&lt;/a&gt;, and the (unnamed) game from &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/16634.The_Glass_Bead_Game" title="The Glass Bead Game by Hermann Hesse" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;The Glass Bead Game&lt;/a&gt;. Both are conceived as world-spanning games that model an entire culture's activities and concerns – but unfortunately aren't described in enough detail in their source books to admit much analysis. It's fascinating to think what such an analysis might look like, though.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There is as usual a focus on whether a game has been "solved", as in whether an optimal strategy is known to exist. Many do, of course, and for others such a Go there are "solutions" using machine learning so that a machine can win – but can't explain &lt;i&gt;how&lt;/i&gt;, which is very unsatisfactory. du Sautoy is clearly exicited by the applications of machine learing to games and other mathematical applications: an excitement I, as a computer scientist, don't really share.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Having said that, this is an interesting complement to other science-driven games books such as &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/58085257.Seven_Games_A_Human_History" title="Seven Games A Human History by Oliver Roeder" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Seven Games: A Human History&lt;/a&gt;, with more depth to the undelying maths.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Sunday 24 December, 2023.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5998737768?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/around-the-world-in-eighty-games-from-tarot-to-tic-tac-toe-catan-to-chutes-and-ladders-a-mathematician-unlocks-the-secrets-of-the-worlds-greatest-games/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Estates: An Intimate History</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/estates-an-intimate-history/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1328840856l/912517._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Lynsey Hanley
	  (2007)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A social history of segregated housing in Britain, how thw dream of a more equal approach died, and the consequences for those who lived through it.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Mass social (or council) housing was intended, in the immediate aftermath of the Second World War, to act as a social glue by mixing all sorts of people together so as to break down the walls of class that blighted British society. It failed: Aneurin Bevin's vision was diluted, as were the building standards, resulting in housing that was both inferior to private stock and immediately identifiable as such, making it stigmatic to live there. The result has been to enhance the blight, erecting what Hanley refers to as "a wall in the head" of people whose self-image is poisoned by poor housing, poor neighbours, and poor (or indeed non-existent) services.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The wall in the head exists in many forms, and one doesn't have to have grown up on a council estate to have one. But however tall it is, the wall is easy to build when young and hard to climb when older, and it'll affect you all your life in some way or other. Housing and class have a lot to do with forming the wall.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's impossible to miss the connection with &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25489625.Between_the_World_and_Me" title="Between the World and Me by Ta-Nehisi Coates" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Between the World and Me&lt;/a&gt;, not least because of the catchy and often-repeated phrasing. &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/1214964.Ta_Nehisi_Coates" title="Ta-Nehisi Coates" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Ta-Nehisi Coates&lt;/a&gt; was more concerned with physical violence rather than social class, but the parallels are there: different people from different circumstances have completely different perceptions of the country in which they live and what it's supposed to do for them. I see this all the time with different student cohorts. It's to some extent a matter of expectations of others, but also of the ability to see opportunities beyond the present. An inward-looking social environment absolutely stunts people's vision of what's possible for them.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The book ends on quite q positive note: the willingness of housing providers to renovate (rather than simply dispose of) social housing stock, and the availability of cash to do so. Whether this is sufficient is an open question, and certainly we still see developers skirting-round the requirement to provide "affordable" housing, in some cases literally walling-off the social from the private units, just as happened with the first estates built in the 1940s.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	4/5.
	  Finished Tuesday 19 December, 2023.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6013200590?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bonanza</category><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/estates-an-intimate-history/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Technofeudalism: What Killed Capitalism</title><link>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/technofeudalism-what-killed-capitalism/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1684846614l/75560036._SX98_.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 10px"&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;
	Yanis Varoufakis
	  (2023)
      &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      A penetrating analysis of where we are and why.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Varoufakis has form with analysing current political affirs, of course: he wrote about his short time as Greek finance minister during the 2008 financial crisis in &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/34673467.Adults_in_the_Room_My_Battle_with_Europe_s_Deep_Establishment" title="Adults in the Room My Battle with Europe's Deep Establishment by Yanis Varoufakis" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Adults in the Room: My Battle with Europe's Deep Establishment&lt;/a&gt;. In this book he tackles a bigger subject: how has the economic system we are now experiencing diverged from the capitalism we've known for over a century? Varoufakis' take is that the torrent of government money that followed the crisis, and increased during the pandemic, was used by the owners of internet-based cloud providers and major platforms – the "cloudalists" – to build-up their capital stock risk- and cost-free, and used this to grab (and then sell) the attention of everyone. Moreover it allowed them to charge rents to everyone else looking to sell on the internet, since network effects made their platforms unavoidable. This return to rentier economics is what Varoufakis terms &lt;i&gt;technofeudalism&lt;/i&gt;, and claims this is a better term that the other terms such as &lt;i&gt;late-stage capitalism&lt;/i&gt; or &lt;i&gt;hypercapitalism&lt;/i&gt; that fail to capture the return to rents as the major source of corporate income – to the point that the cloudalists don't &lt;i&gt;need&lt;/i&gt; to be selling profitable commodities any more.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Varoufakis has a keen eye for anecdotes and corners of the economy in which to test his hypotheses, such as how General Motors turned into a hedge fund with a sideline in cars, or the irony of capitalism being defeated by ... more efficient capitalism. But the major point is that technofeudalism &lt;i&gt;isn't&lt;/i&gt; capitalism, and emerged largely because of government largesse leading to unintended consequences followed by significant political capture to keep the new &lt;i&gt;status quo&lt;/i&gt; in place and without meaningful regulation. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This is a book about economics, but there's a computer science perspective that's perhaps worth taking too. Cloud systems may be inefficient in economic terms, because they extract rents from all users and service providers. But technically they're almost always &lt;i&gt;more&lt;/i&gt; efficient than owning and running your own computers to provide services, as well as reducing costs and risks for start-ups and being a lot more flexible and (potentially) energy-efficient. That's not to say that there's no evidence of rentier behaviour: the cloud providers segment the market to charge premium rates for not-very-different services, which in turn changes technical decisions in ways that might not benefit service providers, and they're notorious for making their charging structures as opaque as possible.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's the network effects in terms of access to users' attention where the rents really become too significant to ignore and almost entirely negative in their effects. We're also seeing the platforms seek regulation to stifle competition, notably in AI, which will re-inforce their ownership of the most important means of computation.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Another thing to consider is that the cloudalists' rents make offerings progressively worsen. &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/12581.Cory_Doctorow" title="Cory Doctorow" rel="nofollow noopener"&gt;Cory Doctorow&lt;/a&gt; terms this process &lt;i&gt;enshittification&lt;/i&gt;, where platform-based services inevitably try to suck-in all the surplus value and squeeze-out other stakeholders – turning them into what Varoufakis terms "cloud serfs" living on whatever pittance of value the platforms don't deign to hoover-up.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So far so negative. But Varoufakis doesn't content himself with merely describing the emergence of the current situation. As a former Communist his class-based analysis (which I have to say strikes a chord with me) leads him to try to define an alternative economy that recognises the realities of the techologies we live with. His prescription seems utopian and hard to realise, although not as hard (as he points out) as when trades unions were first formed, or when right-wing dictatorships were defeated – and he provides possible strategies and rallying cries for us to fight back against the return of feudalism in a more pernicious form than anyone ever expected.&lt;br&gt;
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	5/5.
	  Finished Saturday 9 December, 2023.
	&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
	  (Originally published on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5871145853?utm_medium=api&amp;amp;utm_source=rss"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;.)
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>reviews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/goodreads/technofeudalism-what-killed-capitalism/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>