<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about s4)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/s4.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 14:42:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Research fellow in verifiable sensor systems</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2018/03/16/s4-glasgow/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.dcs.gla.ac.uk/research/S4/"&gt;Science of Sensor Systems Software&lt;/a&gt; (S4) programme grant (of which I'm a PI) has a vacancy for a research fellow based at the University of Glasgow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.jobs.ac.uk/job/BHZ314/research-assistant-associate-fellow/"&gt;Research Assistant / Associate / Fellow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Glasgow&lt;/strong&gt; - College of Science and Engineering - School of Computing Science&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salary: Grade 6/7/8; £28,098 - £31,604 / £34,520 - £38,833 / £42,418 - £49,149 per annum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The School of Computing Science at the University of Glasgow invites applications for a Post Doctoral Research Associate or Fellow position in the leading-edge research project &lt;a href="http://www.dcs.gla.ac.uk/research/S4/"&gt;Science of Sensor System Software&lt;/a&gt; (S4)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research is focused on delivering new principles and techniques for the development and deployment of verifiable, reliable, autonomous sensor-based systems that operate in uncertain, multiple and multi-scale environments. The S4 programme grant is a collaboration between four universities and you will be expected to work closely with researchers across the four universities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This position offers an exciting opportunity to gain first-hand insights into the development of sensor-based systems and to develop and apply novel modelling and reasoning techniques that contribute to the goals of verifying reliability, robustness, security, etc. Depending on your experience, the role offers considerable intellectual freedom and opportunities for you to take significant initiative, leadership, and responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The job requires expert knowledge in one or more of: formal modelling and specification, stochastic and temporal logics, automated reasoning, sensor networks, run-time verification, real-world applications. Experience of bigraphs and model checking would be an advantage. You must have started to build up a strong publication record, have excellent programming and modelling skills, and be able to quickly integrate software, e.g. for model-checking, simulation, and verification. You should be competent to undertake hands-on work related to modelling and verification of chosen, real-life case-studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You hold, or expect to hold, a PhD in Computer Science or in a closely related field; alternatively, you have a first degree in one of the above-mentioned subjects and substantial experience in a research role in industry. Fresh PhD graduates are also encouraged to apply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For appointment at Grade 8 you will need to meet the additional criteria as per the Job Description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is offered as open-ended contract with funding available for up to 30 months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is anticipated that interviews will be held in March or April 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For further information and to discuss details please contact the Principal Investigator, Professor Muffy Calder (email: &lt;a href="mailto:muffy.calder@glasgow.ac.uk"&gt;muffy.calder@glasgow.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>jobs</category><category>s4</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2018/03/16/s4-glasgow/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Mar 2018 12:29:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>3-year postdoctoral researcher post available</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2017/05/09/s4-postdoc/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of the Science of Sensor Systems Software programme we have a 3-year postdoc post available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.dcs.gla.ac.uk/research/S4"&gt;S4 programme&lt;/a&gt; aims to develop a unifying science, across the breadth of mathematics, computer science and engineering, that will let developers engineer for the uncertainty and ensure that their systems and the information they provide is resilient, responsive, reliable, statistically sound and robust. The vision is smarter sensor based systems in which scientists and policy makers can ask deeper questions and be confident in obtaining reliable answers, so the programme will deliver new principles and techniques for the development and deployment of verifiable, reliable, autonomous sensor systems that operate in uncertain, multiple and multi-scale environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S4 is funded by EPSRC as a five-year, £5.2M Programme Grant. It brings together four of the UK’s leading research teams in sensor systems, their design, analysis, deployment, and evaluation. Led overall by Prof Muffy Calder at the University of Glasgow, the other academic collaborators are the University of St Andrews (Prof Simon Dobson), the University of Liverpool (Prof Michael Fisher), and Imperial College (Prof Julie McCann). S4 also includes a portfolio of industrial partners ranging from start-up SMEs to multinational companies and State agencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;St Andrews leads the work on adaptive systems engineering, especially on how systems need to change as time progresses, the system components fail, and goals change. We are looking for someone to join us to work on how to program adaptive sensor systems. A strong track record in sensor systems, programming languages, data analytics, or another related area is essential, as is an ability to work within a larger team using formal methods, advanced statistics, and novel programming languages and approaches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find full application details &lt;a href="https://www.vacancies.st-andrews.ac.uk/ViewVacancyV2.aspx?enc=mEgrBL4XQK0+ld8aNkwYmIC6qnEzeM4xd5XT+e/5IQxO+OlhRndjgKS6p4BoRNl+UNu83Iiv8J1lWOCFqijDqZx6/oDoGWuUe3/xaL5So5YSmMSr2o2hu+3HhHpd8mWDap8m2c0rxOmXWk95vI/KJw=="&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>jobs</category><category>s4</category><category>sensor networks</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2017/05/09/s4-postdoc/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 13:33:14 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>