<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about saso)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/saso.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2024 13:14:57 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>New paper on collective adaptive systems</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2020/09/28/new-paper-cas/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://simondobson.org/images/posts/20200928-cas-paper.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt; &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our paper "On the social implications of complex adaptive systems" was
just published in IEEE Technology and Society Magazine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2020/09/28/new-paper-cas/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>adaptive systems</category><category>cas</category><category>paper</category><category>saso</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2020/09/28/new-paper-cas/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2020 16:59:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>CfP: SASO 2018</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2018/03/09/cfp-saso2018/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Come and join us in Trento for SASO 2018.

&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="https://saso2018.fbk.eu/"&gt;12th IEEE International Conference on Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Systems (SASO 2018)&lt;/a&gt;
3-7 September 2018, Trento, Italy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Aims and Motivation&lt;/h4&gt;
The aim of the Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Systems conference series (SASO) is to provide a forum for the presentation and discussion of research on the foundations of engineered systems that self-adapt and self-organize. The complexity of current and emerging networks, software, and services can be characterized by issues such as scale, heterogeneity, openness, and dynamics in the environment. This has led the software engineering, distributed systems, and management communities to look for inspiration in diverse fields (e.g., complex systems, control theory, artificial intelligence, chemistry, psychology, sociology, and biology) to find new ways of designing and managing such computing systems in a principled way. In this endeavor, self-organization and self-adaptation have emerged as two promising interrelated approaches. They form the basis of many other so-called self-* properties, such as self-configuration, self-healing, or self-optimization. SASO aims to be an interdisciplinary meeting, where contributions from participants with different backgrounds leads to the fostering of a cross-pollination of ideas, and where innovative theories, frameworks, methodologies, tools, and applications can emerge.
&lt;h4&gt;Scope&lt;/h4&gt;
The twelfth edition of the SASO conference embraces this interdisciplinary nature, and welcomes novel contributions to both the foundational and application-focused dimensions of self-adaptive and self-organizing systems research. We are looking for contributions that present new fundamental understanding of self-adaptive and self-organizing systems and how they can be engineered and used. The topics of interest include, but are not limited to:
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self-* Systems theory&lt;/strong&gt;: nature-inspired and socially-inspired paradigms and heuristics; inter-operation of self-* mechanisms; theoretical frameworks and models; control theory;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self-* System properties&lt;/strong&gt;: robustness; resilience; stability; anti-fragility; diversity; self-reference and reflection; emergent behavior; computational awareness and self-awareness;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self-* Systems engineering&lt;/strong&gt;: reusable mechanisms and algorithms; design patterns; architectures; methodologies; software and middleware development frameworks and methods; platforms and toolkits; multi-agent systems;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theory and practice of self-organization&lt;/strong&gt;: self-governance, change management, electronic institutions, distributed consensus, commons, knowledge management, and the general use of rules, policies, etc. in self-* systems;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theory and practice of self-adaptation&lt;/strong&gt;: mechanisms for adaptation, including evolution, logic, learning; adaptability, plasticity, flexibility;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Socio-technical self-* systems&lt;/strong&gt;: human and social factors; visualization; crowdsourcing and collective awareness; humans-in-the-loop; ethics and humanities in self-* systems;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data-driven approaches to self-* systems&lt;/strong&gt;: data mining; machine learning; data science and other statistical techniques to analyze, understand, and manage the behavior of complex systems;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self-adaptive and self-organizing hardware&lt;/strong&gt;: self-* materials; self-construction; reconfigurable hardware;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self-* Systems Education&lt;/strong&gt;: experience reports; curricula; innovative course concepts; methodological aspects of self-* systems education;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applications and experiences with self-* systems&lt;/strong&gt;: smart grid, smart cities, smart homes, adaptive industrial plants, cyber-physical systems; autonomous vehicles and robotics; traffic management; self-adaptive cyber-security; Internet of Things; fog/edge computing; etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Important Dates&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Abstract submission&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;April 16, 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Paper submission&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;April 23, 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Notification&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;June 4, 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Camera ready copy due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;July 2, 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Conference&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;September 3-7, 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Submission Instructions&lt;/h4&gt;
Submissions can have up to 10 pages formatted according to the standard IEEE Computer Society Press proceedings style guide (&lt;a href="https://www.ieee.org/conferences_events/conferences/publishing/templates.html"&gt;see templates here&lt;/a&gt;). Please submit your papers electronically in PDF format using the SASO 2018 conference management system:
&lt;a href="https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=saso2018"&gt;https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=saso2018&lt;/a&gt;.

The proceedings will be published by IEEE Computer Society Press, and made available as a part of the IEEE Digital Library. Note that a separate Call for Poster and Demo Submissions will also be issued. As per the standard IEEE policies, all submissions should be original, i.e., they should not have been previously published in any conference proceedings, book, or journal and should not currently be under review for another archival conference. We would like to also highlight IEEE’s policies regarding plagiarism and self-plagiarism (&lt;a href="http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/ID_Plagiarism.html"&gt;http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/ID_Plagiarism.html&lt;/a&gt;).

Where relevant and appropriate, accepted papers will also be encouraged to participate in the Demo or Poster Sessions.
&lt;h4&gt;Review Criteria&lt;/h4&gt;
Papers should present novel ideas in the cross-disciplinary research context described in this call, motivated by problems from current practice or applied research. Both theoretical and empirical contributions should be highlighted, substantiated by formal analysis, simulation, experimental evaluations, or comparative studies, etc. Appropriate references must be made to related work. Due to the cross-disciplinary nature of the SASO conference, we encourage papers to be intelligible and relevant to researchers who are not members of the same specialized sub-field.

Authors are also encouraged to submit papers describing applications. Application papers should provide an indication of the real-world relevance of the problem that is solved, including a description of the domain, and an evaluation of performance, usability, or comparison to alternative approaches. Experience papers are also welcome, especially if they highlight insights into any aspect of design, implementation or management of self-* systems that would be of benefit to practitioners and the SASO community. All submissions will be rigorously peer reviewed and evaluated based on the quality of their technical contribution, originality, soundness, significance, presentation, understanding of the state of the art, and overall quality.
&lt;h4&gt;Contact Information&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Conference General Chairs&lt;/h5&gt;
Antonio Bucchiarone,
Fondazione Bruno Kessler, IT

Alberto Montresor,
University of Trento, IT
&lt;h5&gt;Programme Chairs&lt;/h5&gt;
Jake Beal,
Raytheon BBN Technologies, USA

Nelly Bencomo,
Aston University, UK

Jean Botev,
University of Luxembourg, LU</description><category>cfp</category><category>conference</category><category>saso</category><category>self-organising systems</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2018/03/09/cfp-saso2018/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 15:46:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Call for papers: 11th IEEE International Conference on Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Systems</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2017/03/01/call-for-papers-11th-ieee-international-conference-on-self-adaptive-and-self-organizing-systems/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;SASO 2017 is now accepting paper submissions. Come and join us in Arizona!

&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://saso2017.telecom-paristech.fr/"&gt;&lt;img class="alignleft size-medium" src="https://saso2017.telecom-paristech.fr/resources/saso_banner_landscape1.png" width="1280" height="302"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id="saso-banner-title"&gt;SASO 2017&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="saso-banner-subtitle"&gt;&lt;a href="https://saso2017.telecom-paristech.fr/"&gt;11th IEEE International Conference on Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="saso-banner-location"&gt;University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ · 18-22 September 2017&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Aims and Scope&lt;/h3&gt;
The aim of the Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Systems conference series (SASO) is to provide a forum for the presentation and discussion of research on the foundations of engineered systems that self-adapt and self-organize. The complexity of current and emerging networks, software, and services can be characterized by issues such as scale, heterogeneity, openness, and dynamics in the environment. This has led the software engineering, distributed systems, and management communities to look for inspiration in diverse fields (e.g., complex systems, control theory, artificial intelligence, chemistry, psychology, sociology, and biology) to find new ways of designing and managing such computing systems in a principled way. In this endeavor, self-organization and self-adaptation have emerged as two promising interrelated approaches. They form the basis for many other so-called self-* properties, such as self-configuration, self-healing, or self-optimization. SASO aims to be an interdisciplinary meeting, where contributions from participants with different backgrounds leads to the fostering of a cross-pollination of ideas, and where innovative theories, frameworks, methodologies, tools, and applications can emerge.

The eleventh edition of the SASO conference embraces this inter-disciplinary nature, and welcomes novel contributions to both the foundational and application-focused dimensions of self-adaptive and self-organizing systems research. The topics of interest include, but are not limited to:
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Systems theory: nature-inspired and socially-inspired paradigms and heuristics; inter-operation of self-* mechanisms; theoretical frameworks and models; control theory;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;System properties: robustness; resilience; stability; anti-fragility; diversity; self-reference and reflection; emergent behavior; computational awareness and self-awareness;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Systems engineering: reusable mechanisms and algorithms; design patterns; architectures; methodologies; software and middleware development frameworks and methods; platforms and toolkits; multi-agent systems;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Theory and practice of organization: self-governance, change management, electronic institutions, distributed consensus, commons, knowledge management, and the general use of rules, policies, etc. in self-* systems&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Theory and practice of adaptation: mechanisms for adaptation, including evolution, logic, learning; adaptability, plasticity, flexibility&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Socio-technical systems: human and social factors; visualization; crowdsourcing and collective awareness; humans-in-the-loop; ethics and humanities in self-* systems;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Data-driven approaches: data mining; machine learning; data science and other statistical techniques to analyze, understand, and manage behavior of complex systems;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Self-adaptive and self-organizing hardware: self-* materials; self-construction; reconfigurable hardware;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Education: experience reports; curricula; innovative course concepts; methodological aspects of self-* systems education;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Applications and experiences with self-* systems in any of the following domains are of particular interest:
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Smart systems: smart grids, smart cities, smart environments, smart homes, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Industrial automation: embedded self-* systems, adaptive industrial plants, Industry 4.0, cyber physical systems&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Transportation: autonomous vehicles, traffic optimization&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Autonomous systems: aerial vehicles, undersea vehicles, autonomous robotics&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Internet of Things: self-* for network management, self-* applied to cyber security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
We are looking for contributions that present new fundamental understanding of self-adaptive and self-organizing systems and how they can be engineered and used, including: novel theoretical or experimental results, novel design patterns, mechanisms, system architectures, frameworks, tools, and practical experiences in building or deploying systems and applications. Contributions contrasting different approaches for engineering a given family of systems, or demonstrating the applicability of a certain approach for different systems, are equally encouraged. Likewise, papers describing substantial innovation or insights in the use and communication of self-* systems in the classroom are welcome.

Where relevant and appropriate, accepted papers will also be encouraged to participate in the Demo or Poster Sessions.
&lt;h3&gt;Important Dates&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table class="dates-table"&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Abstract submission&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="date"&gt;May 1, 2017&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Paper submission&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="date"&gt;May 10, 2017&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Notification&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="date"&gt;June 30, 2017&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Camera ready copy due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="date"&gt;July 12, 2017&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Conference&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="date"&gt;September 18-22, 2017&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Submission Instructions&lt;/h3&gt;
Submissions can be up to 10 pages, formatted according to the standard IEEE Computer Society Press proceedings style guide, and submitted electronically in PDF format. Please submit your papers using the SASO 2017 conference management system:

&lt;a href="https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=saso2017" target="_blank"&gt;https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=saso2017&lt;/a&gt;.

The proceedings will be published by IEEE Computer Society Press, and made available as a part of the IEEE Digital Library. Note that a separate Call for Poster and Demo Submissions will also be issued. As per the standard IEEE policies, all submissions should be original, i.e., they should not have been previously published in any conference proceedings, book, or journal and should not currently be under review for another archival conference. We also highlight IEEE’s policies regarding plagiarism and self-plagiarism (&lt;a href="http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/ID_Plagiarism.html" target="_blank"&gt;http://www.ieee.org/.../ID_Plagiarism.html&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;h3&gt;Review Criteria&lt;/h3&gt;
Papers should present novel ideas in the cross-disciplinary research context described in this call, motivated by problems from current practice or applied research. Both theoretical and empirical contributions should be highlighted, substantiated by formal analysis, simulation, experimental evaluations, or comparative studies, etc. Appropriate references must be made to related work. Because SASO is a cross-disciplinary conference, we encourage papers to be intelligible and relevant to researchers who are not members of the same specialized sub-field.

Authors are also encouraged to submit papers describing applications. Application papers should provide an indication of the real-world relevance of the problem that is solved, including a description of the domain, and an evaluation of performance, usability, or comparison to alternative approaches. Experience papers are also welcome, especially if they highlight insights into any aspect of design, implementation or management of self-* systems that would be of benefit to practitioners and the SASO community. All submissions will be rigorously peer reviewed and evaluated based on the quality of their technical contribution, originality, soundness, significance, presentation, understanding of the state of the art, and overall quality.
&lt;h3&gt;Contact Information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conference General Chair&lt;/h4&gt;
Ada Diaconescu
Telecom Paris-Tech, Paris, FR
&lt;h4&gt;Program Chairs&lt;/h4&gt;
Peter Lewis,
Aston University, Birmingham, UK

Sam Malek,
University of California, Irvine, USA

Hella Seebach,
Augsburg University, Augsburg, DE

&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cfp</category><category>saso</category><category>self-organising systems</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2017/03/01/call-for-papers-11th-ieee-international-conference-on-self-adaptive-and-self-organizing-systems/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 18:33:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>FAS* 2017 Call for Workshops</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2017/02/27/fas-2017-call-for-workshops/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Workshops now open for the  FAS* (ICCAC and SASO) conferences in Arizona in September

&lt;!--more--&gt;

The FAS* 2017 Steering Committee invites proposals for the Workshop Program to be held along with the technical conferences SASO 2017 and ICCAC 2017. FAS*W workshops will provide a meeting for presenting novel ideas in a less formal and possibly  ore focused way than the conferences themselves. Their aim is to stimulate and facilitate active exchange, interaction, and comparison of approaches, methods, and ideas related to specific topics, both theoretical and applied, in the general area of Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Systems as well as Cloud and Autonomic Computing. To motivate the discussion and participation of all the workshop attendants, we encourage organizers to get away of the typical "mini-conference" format of a workshop, and include more discussion sessions, panels, etc. Members from all areas of the SASO and ICCAC communities are invited to submit workshop proposals for review. Workshops on global challenges, applications or on new and emerging topics are particularly encouraged. Workshops can vary in length, but most will be one full day in duration. Optionally, if desired by the organizers, workshop proceedings can be published through IEEE. Attendance of workshops will be included in the registration fee for the main SASO/ICCAC conference.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Important dates&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Workshop proposal submission deadline: April 7, 2017*&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Workshop acceptance notification: April 14, 2017*&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;CfP submission deadline: April 21, 2017&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Workshop paper submission deadline: July 7, 2017&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Workshop paper acceptance notification: July 21, 2017&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Early registration deadline: TBD&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Camera-ready papers due: July 26, 2017&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Workshop notes submission to workshop chairs: July 28, 2017&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Workshops dates: September 18 &amp;amp; 22, 2017&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
* Please submit your workshop proposals as soon as possible (i.e. before April 7)! We will try to decide earlier on workshop acceptance in order to give the organizers more time to solicit papers.
&lt;h3&gt;Requirements for submission&lt;/h3&gt;
Proposals for workshops should be separated in two parts. The first part should be organized as preliminary call for papers or call for participation, depending on the intended format of the workshop, with a maximum of two pages and contain the following information:

PART 1:
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Title of the workshop.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A brief technical description of the workshop, specifying the workshop goals, the technical issues that it will address, and the relevance of the workshop to the main conferences. Please specify, which of the two main conferences the workshop assigned to (if any)!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Description of paper review process (if any) and acceptance standards in order to keep the workshop high in quality. Note that papers must be in the same format as the conference proceedings and may not be more than 6 pages in length.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The names, affiliations, postal addresses, phone numbers, and email addresses of the proposed workshop organizing committee. This committee should consist of three or four people knowledgeable about the technical issues to be addressed. The organizing committee should include individuals from multiple institutions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The primary email address for contacting the organizing committee.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Expected duration of the workshop (half or full day). - A brief description of the workshop format.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;List of potential program committee members (if applicable), including their title and affiliations.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;List of potential invited speakers, panelists, or disputants (if applicable).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
PART 2:

The second part with a maximum of three pages should contain additional information not suitable for a Call for Papers, including:
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A discussion of why and to whom the workshop is of interest.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A list of related workshops held within the last three years, if any, and their relation to the proposed workshop.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Information about previous offerings of the proposed workshop: when and where it has been offered in the past, organizers names and affiliations, number of submissions, acceptances and registered attendees.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;An indication of the envisaged acceptance rate (if applicable).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A description of the qualifications of the individual committee members with respect to organizing a SASO or ICCAC workshop, including a list of workshops previously arranged by any members of the proposed organizing committee, if any.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A list of places (distribution lists, web sites, journals, etc.) where the workshop is planned to be advertised.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
All proposals should be submitted in plain ASCII text or PDF format by electronic mail to the FAS*W 2017 Workshop Chairs, via Christopher Frantz, as described below.
&lt;h3&gt;Selection Criteria&lt;/h3&gt;
The selection of the workshops to be included in the final FAS* 2017 Workshop program will be based upon multiple factors, including:
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;the scientific/technical interest of the topics,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;the quality of the proposal,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;complementarity with the conference topics,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;balance and distinctness of workshop topics, and&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;the capacity of the conference workshop program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
Note that authors of proposals addressing similar and/or overlapping content areas and/or audiences may be requested to merge their proposals.
&lt;h3&gt;Responsibilities of FAS* 2017 Workshop Chairs&lt;/h3&gt;
For all accepted proposals, FAS* 2017 will be responsible for:
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Providing publicity for the workshop series as a whole. - Providing logistical support and a meeting place for the workshops.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Together with the organizers, determining the workshop date and time.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Liaising and coordinating between the workshop chairs and the finance chair, publicity chair, registration chair, and web chair for FAS*.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Arranging for publication of proceedings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Responsibilities of Workshop Organizers&lt;/h3&gt;
Workshop organizers will be responsible for the following:
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Setting up a web site for the workshop.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Advertising the workshop (and the main FAS* conference), and issuing a call for papers and a call for participation.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Collecting and evaluating submissions, notifying authors of acceptance or rejection on a timely basis, and ensuring a transparent and fair selection process. All workshop organizers commit themselves to adopt the deadlines set by the committee.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Making the pdf of the whole workshop notes available to the workshop chair, as well as a list of audio-visual requirements and any special room requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Writing a 1-page organizers' introduction for the workshop proceedings. Ensuring that the workshop organizers and the participants register for the workshop and/or the main conference (at least one author must register for the paper to appear in the proceedings).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
FAS* reserves the right to cancel any workshop if the above responsibilities are not fulfilled, or if too few attendees register for the workshop to support its running costs.
&lt;h3&gt;Submissions and Inquiries&lt;/h3&gt;
Please send proposals (as a PDF document) and inquiries to: Christopher Frantz (&lt;a class="moz-txt-link-abbreviated" href="mailto:cf@christopherfrantz.org"&gt;cf@christopherfrantz.org&lt;/a&gt;) or Jeremy Pitt (&lt;a class="moz-txt-link-abbreviated" href="mailto:j.pitt@imperial.ac.uk"&gt;j.pitt@imperial.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;)

&lt;a class="moz-txt-link-freetext" href="https://saso2017.telecom-paristech.fr/committees.html"&gt;https://saso2017.telecom-paristech.fr/committees.html&lt;/a&gt;</description><category>autonomic systems</category><category>cfp</category><category>iccac</category><category>saso</category><category>self-organising systems</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2017/02/27/fas-2017-call-for-workshops/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 14:24:08 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>