<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about scheme)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/scheme.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 07:54:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The only computer science book worth reading twice?</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2010/05/14/cs-book-worth-reading-twice/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I was talking to one of my students earlier, and lent him a book to
read over summer. It was only after he'd left that I realised that --
for me at any rate -- the book I'd given him is probably the most
seminal work in the whole of computer science, and certainly the book
that's most influenced my career and research interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what's the book? &lt;em&gt;Structure and interpretation of computer
programs&lt;/em&gt; by Hal Abelson and Jerry Sussman &lt;span&gt; (MIT
Press. 1984. ISBN 0-262-01077-1), also known as &lt;em&gt;SICP&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;/span&gt;The book's still in print, but -- even better -- is &lt;a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/"&gt;available online in its
entirety&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, everyone has their favourite book: why's this one so special to
me? The first reason is the time I first encountered it: in &lt;a href="http://www.cs.newcastle.ac.uk/"&gt;Newcastle upon Tyne&lt;/a&gt; in
&lt;span&gt;the second year of my first degree. I was still finding my way
in computer science, and this book was a recommended text after you'd
finished the first programming courses. It's the book that introduced
me to programming &lt;em&gt;as it could be&lt;/em&gt; (rather than programming
&lt;em&gt;as it was&lt;/em&gt;, in Pascal at the time). What I mean by that is
that SICP starts out by introducing the elements of programming --
values, names, binding, control and so on -- and then runs with them
to explore a quite dazzling breadth of issues including:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;lambda-abstraction and higher-order computation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;complex data structures, including structures with embedded computational content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;modularity and mutability&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;streams&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;lazy evaluation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;interpreter and compiler construction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;storage management, garbage collection and virtual memory
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;machine code
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;domain-specific languages&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...and so forth. The list of concepts is bewildering, and only stays coherent because the authors are skilled writers devoted to their craft. But it's also a remarkable achievement to handle all these concepts within a single language framework -- Scheme -- in such a way that each builds on what's gone before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second reason is the way in which Hal and Jerry view everything as
an exercise in language design:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;We have also obtained a glimpse of another crucial idea
about languages and program design. This is the approach of stratified
design, the notion that a complex system should be structured as a
sequence of levels that are described using a sequence of languages.
Each level is constructed by combining parts that are regarded as
primitive at that level, and the parts constructed at each level are
used as primitives at the next level. The language used at each level
of a stratified design has primitives, means of combination, and means
of abstraction appropriate to that level of detail.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Layered abstraction of course is second nature to all computer
scientists. What's novel in this view is that each level should be
&lt;em&gt;programmable&lt;/em&gt;: that the layers are all about computation and
transformation, and not simply about hiding information. We don't see
that in the mainstream of programming languages, because layering
doesn't extend the language at all: Java is Java from top to bottom,
with class and libraries but no new control structures. If a
particular domain has concepts that would benefit from dedicated
language constructs, that's just tough. Conversely (and this is
something that very much interests me) if there are constructs it'd be
desirable &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to have in some domain, they can't be removed.
(Within the language, anyway: Java-ME dumps some capabilities in the
interests of running on small devices, but that's not something you
can do without re-writing the compiler.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third influential feature is the clear-sighted view of what
computer science is actually about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The computer revolution is a revolution in the way we
think and in the way we express what we think. The essence of this
change is the emergence of what might best be called &lt;em&gt;procedural
epistemology&lt;/em&gt; -- the study of the structure of knowledge from an
imperative point of view, as opposed to the more declarative point of
view taken by classical mathematical subjects. Mathematics provides a
framework for dealing precisely with notions of "what is." Computation
provides a framework for dealing precisely with notions of "how
to."&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've taken a view before about &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2010/04/01/computer-microscope/"&gt;computers being the new
microscopes&lt;/a&gt;, opening-up new science on their own as well as
facilitating existing approaches. The "how to" aspect of computer
science re-appears everywhere in this: in describing the behaviours of
sensor networks that can adapt while continuing the reflect the
phenomena they've been deployed to sense; in the interpretation of
large-scale data mined and mashed-up across the web; in capturing
scientific methods and processes for automation; and so forth. The
richness of these domains mitigates against packaged software and
encourages integration through programming languages like &lt;a href="http://www.r-project.org"&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;, so that the interfaces and
structures remain "soft" and open to experimentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I looked at my copy, the date I'd written on the inside was
September 1988. So a book I bought nearly 22 years ago is still
relevant. &lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;In fact, I'd go further and say that it's the only
computer science book of that age that I'd happily and usefully read
again without it being just for historical interest: the content has
barely aged at all. That's not all that unusual for mathematics books,
but it's almost unheard of in computer science, where the ideas move
so quickly and where much of what's written about is ephemeral rather
than foundational. It goes to show how well SICP nailed the core
concepts. In this sense, it's certainly one of the very few  books on
computer science that it's worth reading twice (or more). SICP is to
computer science what Feynman's &lt;em&gt;Lectures on Physics&lt;/em&gt; are to
physics: an accessible distillation of the essence of the subject
that's stood the test of time.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>programming</category><category>review</category><category>scheme</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2010/05/14/cs-book-worth-reading-twice/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2010 05:00:35 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>