<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about sensing)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/sensing.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 14:53:10 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>First installation</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2024/05/19/first-installation/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org374f665" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org374f665"&gt;First installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org374f665"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The BirdNET-Pi system aims to provide out-of-the-box bird
identification. It's slightly more awkward than that, but still
pretty straightforward to get up and running.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My first hardware plan was to use a Raspberry Pi Zero as the
compute host with a &lt;a href="https://www.waveshare.com/wm8960-audio-hat.htm"&gt;Waveshare WM8960 HAT&lt;/a&gt; for the sound capture. It
turns out that BirdNET needs a 64-bit platform – why I'm not sure
– and the Pi Zero only runs 32-bit Linux. I therefore moved to a
Raspberry Pi B that I had lying around, and put a 64-bit "lite"
install on it to run headless.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Basically followed the &lt;a href="https://github.com/mcguirepr89/BirdNET-Pi/wiki/Installation-Guide"&gt;installation guide&lt;/a&gt;. There was an issue with
the installation script when cloning the GitHub repo: I suspect
this was because of limited memory on the Pi. I downloaded
manually, and manually ran the rest of the install script, which
did a &lt;i&gt;lot&lt;/i&gt; of setup of services and a PHP web server.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I compiled the &lt;a href="https://www.waveshare.com/wiki/WM8960_Audio_HAT"&gt;drivers&lt;/a&gt; for the HAT, which worked fine. The new
sound card is recognised but is not the default.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The installed components seem to include:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;icecast2&lt;/code&gt;, a streaming server, used to replay recordings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;caddy&lt;/code&gt; web server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PHP for serving the web pages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;arecord&lt;/code&gt; to actually record audio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;ffmpeg&lt;/code&gt; to extract waveforms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;sqlite for the database&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the actual machine learning model used for recognition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
The recognition models are built with TensorFlow. This is a great
example of how the standard Linux tools and services can be combined
to get a scientific-grade sensor platform. (Caddy doesn't see to be
running over TLS by default, which would be an issue outside a
firewall.)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since the sound card isn't the default, the easiest way to correct
this is to change the device in the "advanced settings" panel: in
my case I changed from "default" to "hw:2,0", reflecting the
output of &lt;code&gt;arecord -l&lt;/code&gt; that shows the sound card devices.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I then deployed the Pi out of the kitchen window.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://simondobson.org/attachments/18/408cf7-5f1f-4b07-81ef-e8f94d1c38d3/screenshot.png" alt="nil"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To start with it wasn't hearing anything, which I think may be
because of the waterfall in the courtyard: turning this off made
things much more effective:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://simondobson.org/attachments/18/408cf7-5f1f-4b07-81ef-e8f94d1c38d3/screenshot-1.png" alt="nil"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's an appropriate set of birds being seen – and we hardly ever
&lt;i&gt;see&lt;/i&gt; magpies, but know they're around. There's actually quite a lot
of background noise even in such a quiet village, but the bird
calls do stand out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I can't see any reason for the manual installation on bare metal:
as far as I can see everything could be containerised, which would
make deployment and management a &lt;i&gt;lot&lt;/i&gt; easier.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>acoustic</category><category>project:acoustic-birds</category><category>raspberry pi</category><category>sensing</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2024/05/19/first-installation/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 14:19:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The parts arrive</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2013/06/21/parts-arrive/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The parts have arrived for the ditch project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first tranche of hardware came (in a small box) today:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Enough parts for four sensors and a base station" src="https://simondobson.org/images/citizen-sensing/2013-06-19-14.14.06.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are parts here for four sensor packages and a base station. The sensor nodes have an Arduino, a 2mW XBee radio, and a digital temperature sensor. The base station has an XBee and a wired ethernet for connecting up to the internet. There are also some prototyping shields to simplify integration, a wall wart power supply for the base station, and some other goodies to support some other development.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>making</category><category>project:ditch</category><category>sensing</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2013/06/21/parts-arrive/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2013 09:00:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sensor mote initial parts list</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2013/06/20/parts-list/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The initial design for a sensor mote puts three temperature sensors together with an Arduino and short-range radio module.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

The following is the parts list for a single sensor mote:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Arduino Uno -- £18.50&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Arduino XBee shield -- £12.10&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Arduino Series 2 2mW XBee radio module -- £17.50&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Arduino prototype shield -- £10.40&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Mini-breadboard -- £2.00&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;3 x DS18B20 one-wire digital temperature sensor -- £11.70&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Battery holder -- £1.20&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Enclosure (waterproof, resealable food box) -- £3.50&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
A total of £76.90 (+ VAT) per sensor, not including assorted wires and resistors.

[UPDATED 11Jul2013: added cost of enclosure]</description><category>hardware</category><category>making</category><category>project:ditch</category><category>sensing</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2013/06/20/parts-list/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2013 13:05:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The ditch project: a motivation</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2013/06/19/ditch-motivation/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Citizen Sensing's first project is to perform environmental monitoring on a small scale with minimally-specification hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Orchids, Co Sligo" src="https://simondobson.org/images/citizen-sensing/120720-0143-web.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have three sets of goals from this project. Firstly, we want a realistic scientific project that's simple enough to accomplish over a summer. Secondly, we want to gain some experience with technologies in the field, what works and what doesn't at this level of sophistication. Finally, we want to develop an initial software platform that can support further experimentation. To deal with these in order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The science will be very simple. Some areas have climates that vary over very short distances, and these variations can affect the flora and fauna that live there. In particular, areas like depressions and ditches often have different temperature profiles than the surrounding areas, with less variation in temperature, that may suit some species. While this is clear in general, the specifics often aren't well-understood, so it's a worthwhile scientific exercise to measure temperature variation around a small area. Specifically, we'll seek to measure temperature variation around a ditch we have access to, in County Sligo in the West of Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technology will be off-the-shelf hardware, using Arduinos for processing and XBee radios for communications. These are extremely cheap commodity items that haven't really been used for experimental environmental science, and it's by no means clear that they're appropriate for building a long-lived, robust sensor network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main software challenges include working the hardware and -- more significantly -- managing the very limited power budget one gets with standard batteries and hardware. In building the software, we're aiming for a re-usable platform that can be packaged in a form so that the experiment can be reproduced or used as the basis or other experiments by other groups of scientists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this a worthwhile project? From a scientific point of view its clearly questionable, but that's not the point: this sort of experiment is representative of a wide range of environmental sensing, both citizen and professional, so making it work opens the door to a wider spectrum of investigations without getting bogged-down initially in the details of a scientific challenge when the computing is so new and uncertain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/development/projects/citizen-sensing/"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; for the project will let you follow all the gory details.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>making</category><category>project:ditch</category><category>sensing</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2013/06/19/ditch-motivation/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 20:02:20 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>