<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about st andrews)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/st-andrews.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:simon.dobson@computer.org"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 16:30:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>2 Lecturer/Senior Lecturer positions at St Andrews</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2017/05/28/academic-positions/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We're looking to recruit new academics as part of a large on-going expansion of our academic staff. We wish to appoint two new &lt;a href="https://www.vacancies.st-andrews.ac.uk/ViewVacancyV2.aspx?enc=mEgrBL4XQK0+ld8aNkwYmLYAYEGVHElLWsnTJgL+CarIHBCM/EiQaeKOsYHKP51KpI3DcpxT/zQcAl/8iq/B+IMGPJwugR63L68sBJUS3+i3hCU7JR/EJv31DirWmhwtDXIz2HSywsmfeey5lSxnIg=="&gt;Lecturers/Senior Lecturers&lt;/a&gt; (depending on experience) to join our vibrant teaching and research community that is ranked amongst the top venues for Computer Science education and research worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The successful candidate will be expected to have a range of interests, to be active in research publication that strengthens or complements those in the School and to be capable of teaching the subject to undergraduate and taught postgraduate students who come to us with a wide range of backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excellent teaching skills and an interest in promoting knowledge exchange are essential. You should also have some familiarity with grant-seeking processes in relation to research councils and other sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More details are available on the &lt;a href="https://www.vacancies.st-andrews.ac.uk/ViewVacancyV2.aspx?enc=mEgrBL4XQK0+ld8aNkwYmLYAYEGVHElLWsnTJgL+CarIHBCM/EiQaeKOsYHKP51KpI3DcpxT/zQcAl/8iq/B+IMGPJwugR63L68sBJUS3+i3hCU7JR/EJv31DirWmhwtDXIz2HSywsmfeey5lSxnIg=="&gt;university vacancies page&lt;/a&gt;. Informal enquiries can be directed to Professor Steve Linton (&lt;a href="mailto:hos-cs@st-andrews.ac.uk"&gt;hos-cs@st-andrews.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;) or Dr Dharini Balasubramaniam (&lt;a href="mailto:dot-cs@st-andrews.ac.uk"&gt;dot-cs@st-andrews.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>jobs</category><category>st andrews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2017/05/28/academic-positions/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2017 15:17:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Graduation address: "Every success is everybody's success"</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2013/11/30/every-success/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was honoured to be asked to give the graduation address at this year's St Andrews Day ceremony. The speech is below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chancellor, Principal, colleagues, friends, ladies and gentlemen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduations are a celebration of hard work and success. And the efforts you've all made to be sitting here today certainly deserve to be celebrated: whatever your course of study, you've shown the determination, dedication, intelligence, creativity, and drive to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But being asked to give this graduation address got me thinking about the nature of success, and I'd like to share a thought with you: that success is not something we can readily ascribe to anyone individually. Rather, it's a jigsaw that assembles itself from the actions of those people you meet and by whom you are influenced. Indeed, when you get right down to it, every success is everybody's success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see what I mean by this, think about how much had to go right for your studies to take place. You had to be born and brought up in a way that made you emotionally able to leave home and thrive on your own, possibly mastering a different language and culture, to become a rounded individual with the skills needed to take on a university such as this. This is no mean feat on the parts of yourselves and your parents, as I hope you appreciate; not to mention your earlier teachers, friends, neighbours, and all the other people who influenced you down the years. When you came to St Andrews, I'm sure you discovered that learning and research don't occur in a vacuum. Most of you will have worked as part of a team, either in a lab or a seminar, where you came together to do something that perhaps none of you could have done individually. If you think back, I'm sure you can remember plenty of things said or done that have contributed directly to your being here today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can cast the net wider. The university is clean, secure, and well-managed, thanks to the efforts of porters, cleaners, secretaries, administrators, and a host of others -- efforts that tend to be hidden away and are easily forgotten, but that contribute to your studies at least as much as the efforts of your lecturers. The lights are on, the labs and seminar rooms are warm (more or less). There are coal miners in eastern Poland whom we will never meet, and who will never know to what they contributed -- but without them the wheels would not have turned, the lights would not have burned, and none of the functions that we perform in this university would have been possible. So every success that happens here is their success too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course we should look through time as well as space. With this graduation we're coming to the end of celebrating the 600th anniversary of the University of St Andrews. Think what has happened over those six hundred years to get us here! All the discovery and learning, all the patient, careful scholarship down through the years, slowly building knowledge, slowly building the reputation of this University, and of Scotland, as a place to come to learn and to teach and to do research -- sparkling at this graduation today before ricocheting off into the future. Any successes any of us have here owe a debt to those who have come before us, who made this (frankly very unlikely) place possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there's any substance to these musings, then it's this: success isn't the singular, individual thing that we sometimes like to think it is; but nor is it an atomised, isolated thing occurring outside a particular place in space and time and the flow of humanity. The modern world tends to focus on measurement, and the corollary that anything that can't be easily measured either didn't happen at all or at least can be safely ignored. But a moment's reflection will convince you that this is nonsense: the successes we're celebrating today have been guided and driven by influences that we would struggle to identify and certainly couldn't quantify in any meaningful way, but without which we would not all be sitting here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has some quite profound implications. It means that whatever you all do from today, whatever successes you enjoy in the years to come, are of real importance, no matter how small they may appear to you. Your research project may not give rise to the next Google: but it might be read by someone, who writes a thesis, that's read by someone else, that gives another person an idea, that someone else uses to change the world for the better. We'll never know the exact details of this process -- we'll certainly never measure it or report it -- but lack of public credit doesn't equate to lack of value, and that's something that can help keep us all motivated and generous with our time and our ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So as well as celebrating your own individual successes today, I hope you'll also celebrate the contributions you've made to the successes of others through friendship, collaboration, advice, mutual support, tutoring -- or just simply being here. Every success really is everybody's success. Thank you, and enjoy the rest of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(And in keeping with this spirit, I'd like to thank &lt;a href="http://blogs.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/al/" target="_blank"&gt;Al Dearle,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/directory/person?id=sal" target="_blank"&gt;Steve Linton,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.linda-rafferty.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Linda Rafferty&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/directory/person?id=lisa" target="_blank"&gt;Lisa Dow&lt;/a&gt;, for their comments that made this speech so much better than when I first wrote it. The official press release version is on the &lt;a href="http://www.st-andrews.ac.uk/news/archive/2013/title,231150,en.php" target="_blank"&gt;university web site&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>st andrews</category><category>talk</category><category>university</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2013/11/30/every-success/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2013 09:00:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Six 600th anniversary PhD scholarships</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2012/12/20/600th-scholarships/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of St Andrews' 600th anniversary, the University is funding six scholarships in computer science (and all our other Schools, for that matter).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details are on &lt;a href="http://blogs.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/csblog/2012/12/20/600th-anniversary-phd-scholarships/" target="_blank"&gt;our web site&lt;/a&gt;. There's no special application process, and the studentships are open to all qualified applicants. You'd be well advised to research potential research supervisors and discuss things with them ahead of applying. Most staff -- including me -- will be accepting students under this scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>st andrews</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2012/12/20/600th-scholarships/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2012 19:22:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Distinguished lecture on artificial life</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2012/08/14/artificial-life/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our most recent distinguished lecture was the best I've heard so far, and on a fascinating topic I'd like to know more about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We run two distinguished lectures each academic year, inviting an academic in to teach a four-hour course on some topic that often we don't really have expertise with in St Andrews. It exposes undergraduates, grad students and staff to new topics and ways of thinking about research. &lt;a href="http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/distinguished-lectures/archive" target="_blank"&gt;The series goes back to 1969&lt;/a&gt; and includes some of the best-known names in computer science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last semester's speaker was Larry Yaeger from the University of Indiana (on sabbatical at the University of Hertfordshire), who talked about artificial life: using computers to study the processes of evolution, speciation and adaptation. It's a topic that sits on the boundary between novel computing and theoretical biology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://blogs.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/simondobson/files/2012/03/2012-03-12-11.38.021-e1335726535605.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-1127 alignnone" title="Larry in full flow" src="http://blogs.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/simondobson/files/2012/03/2012-03-12-11.38.021-e1335726535605-768x1024.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="800"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artificial life sounds too much like science fiction to be "real" computer science: do we understand enough about life to be able to study it in the abstract?, and, if not, can artificial life have any scientific content. If you confine yourself enough, of course, then the answer to both questions is a qualified "yes", but the question then becomes, does it tell you anything meaningful about anything? Larry's talk showed that even quite abstracted artificial life scenarios still give some high-level information about the potential for systems design, especially for very dynamic adaptive systems in changing environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Larry's work has focused on building multi-agent simulations of processes, seeing how simple rule sets can give rise to complex behaviours. This has culminated in a system called &lt;a href="http://www.beanblossom.in.us/larryy/Polyworld.html" target="_blank"&gt;Polyworld&lt;/a&gt;, that lets users set up "genetically" based  behaviours for agents. (There are some very cool &lt;a href="http://www.beanblossom.in.us/larryy/PolyworldMovies.html" target="_blank"&gt;movies&lt;/a&gt; of it all working.) The genetic basis -- completely synthetic and higher-level that real genetics -- means that agents can evolve through mutation and cross-over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The part I found most interesting was the way that these systems -- like the natural systems they're abstractions of -- tend not to do optimisation &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;. Instead they find, and stick with, solutions that are "good enough". You get to a balance between evolutionary pressure not being strong enough, and the benefits not being great enough, for further changes to take place. The difference with traditional engineering is quite profound, both in this satisfaction with the sub-optimal but also in the fact that the selection is dynamic, so if the chosen approach ceases to be "good enough" as the environmental pressures change it will shift to another process as a matter of course. You get this dynamism all over chemistry, too, where chemical equilibrium remains a dynamic process with lots of reactions going on all the time without changing the macroscopic concentrations of the reagents involved. It's easy to mistake this for a static system, which it most definitely isn't: I think this is a mistake a lot of scientists and engineers make, though, and it's something we probably need to address when designing adaptive systems or sensor networks that need to operate against or within a complex environment. To do this we'd need to give up a lot of intuitions we have about design, and the possibility of a single "correct" solution to a problem, and think instead of a design space in which the system is (to some extent) free to explore -- and make this design space, and the exploration of it, concepts that are propagated to run-time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this kind of approach makes sense even if you don't embrace the genetic algorithms style view of the world (which in the main I don't). In some ways this is a measure of the success of artificial life research: it's illuminating concepts that are of general utility outside the context from which they're being drawn, that can be used to influence other approaches to systems design without our having to junk everything we already know, which we're clearly not going to do. These sorts of incremental changes are far more useful than revolutions, in many ways, but they come about from thinking that's more-or-less divorced from mainstream thinking. It's a good illustration of why blue-skies research is important, and that knowledge really is all one piece with interconnections and interactions that we can't predict.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>adaptive systems</category><category>artificial intelligence</category><category>Blog</category><category>lecture</category><category>st andrews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2012/08/14/artificial-life/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2012 07:00:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>5 studentships in Computer Science and St Andrews</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2012/05/17/5-studentships/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have five more PhD scholarships tenable from September, for students interested in any of our areas of research. The details are available &lt;a href="http://www.jobs.ac.uk/job/AEL878/funded-phd-research-studentship/" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Please note that I'm not taking on a PhD student this year, so don't bother applying to work with me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>st andrews</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2012/05/17/5-studentships/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2012 10:42:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Brazilian "Science without Borders" studentships available</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2012/04/26/brazil-science/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The School of Computer Science has a number of opportunities available for Brazilian students through this programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Brazilian government is funding studentships for Brazilian nationals with a range of international universities and disciplines. The studentships are "co-tutelle", being split between an international and a Brazilian host university, and aim to improve international collaboration as well as enhancing the student experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of Schools at St Andrews  are &lt;a href="http://www.st-andrews.ac.uk/scholarships/brazil/"&gt;part of this programme&lt;/a&gt;, ranging across the physical and biological sciences in areas in which we have international-quality research. In Computer Science, we have &lt;a href="http://www.st-andrews.ac.uk/scholarships/brazil/computerscience/"&gt;a wide range of project proposals on offer&lt;/a&gt; covering all our main research activities. Interested students should contact the supervisors offering the proposed projects to check on suitability and availability. All students will be subject to the University's usual rules on quality and eligibility.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>st andrews</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2012/04/26/brazil-science/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2012 12:46:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New MSci degree</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2012/03/15/msci/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are introducing a new MSci degree programme with direct entry to second year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We currently offer two traditional Scottish four-year degrees, in Computer Science and Internet Computer Science. A number of factors have contributed to a desire to change this. We'd like to offer a straight-line programme from undergraduate to masters, more in line with European norms (the "&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bologna_Process"&gt;Bologna process&lt;/a&gt;"). For non-Scottish UK students (also known as "RUKs"), we'd like to offer direct entry into second year so that their more advanced A Level qualifications shorten their degree and reduce fee and accommodation costs accordingly. A straight-through programme will also let us present a more integrated collection of modules and improve our targeting for specialised degrees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this means we're introducing a five-year MSci degree in the next application cycle, for 2013 entry. Details are available &lt;a href="http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/prospective-ug/degrees"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>degree</category><category>st andrews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2012/03/15/msci/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Mar 2012 11:13:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Studentships available</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2012/02/22/studentships/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have around six fully-funded PhD studentships available across computer science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The School of Computer Science at the University of St Andrews has  funding for students to undertake PhD research in any of the School's research areas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/research"&gt;http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are looking for highly-motivated research students with an  interest in these exciting areas. Our only requirements are  that the proposed research would be good, we have staff to supervise it,  and that you would be good at doing it. We have up to six funded  studentships available for students interested in working towards a PhD.  The studentships offer costs of fees and an annual tax-free maintenance  stipend of about £13,590 per year for 3.5 years. Exceptionally well  qualified and able students may be awarded an enhanced stipend of an  additional £2,000 per year. Students should normally have or expect at  least an upper-2nd class Honours degree or Masters degree in Computer  Science or a related discipline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For further information on how to apply, see our  &lt;a href="http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/prospective-pg"&gt;postgraduate web pages&lt;/a&gt;.  The closing date for applications is March 1st 2012 and we will make  decisions on studentship allocation by May 1st 2012. (Applications after  March 1st may be considered, at our discretion.) Informal enquiries can  be directed to &lt;a href="mailto:pg-admin-cs@st-andrews.ac.uk"&gt;pg-admin-cs@st-andrews.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt; or to potential supervisors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>st andrews</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2012/02/22/studentships/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 15:56:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Lectureship in Computer Science at St Andrews</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/06/06/lectureship-computer-science-st-andrews/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The School has an opening for a lecturer (assistant professor) in any discipline that matches our research interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Lectureship at St Andrews&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Lecturer in Computer Science – SK8461&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk" target="_blank"&gt;School of Computer Science&lt;/a&gt; £36,862 – £45,336 per  annum. Starting September 2011 or as soon as possible thereafter. Standard  appointment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Scottish Informatics and Computer Science  Alliance (&lt;a href="http://www.sicsa.ac.uk" target="_blank"&gt;SICSA&lt;/a&gt;) is creating a world-leading Computer Science research  community across the universities in Scotland. As part of this  initiative, we seek lectureship applications from researchers with  expertise in the SICSA themes of Next Generation Internet; Complex  Systems Engineering; Multi-modal Interaction and Modelling &amp;amp;  Abstraction. We are particularly interested in candidates with expertise  in sensor systems, multicore systems, embedded systems, data intensive  systems or wireless communications and especially those who bridge two  or more of these areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should have a PhD and have an outstanding research record as  demonstrated by publications and research funding. You must be willing  to cooperate with other researchers across Scotland and contribute to  the work of SICSA and to teach in any area of computer science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A period of postdoctoral experience and publications that reflect  your experience is essential. Teaching is important to us and we expect  candidates to be committed teachers, with appropriate experience. We  have a growing portfolio of Masters level courses and welcome those who  have an interest in contributing to their development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Candidates interested in this post are welcome to informally contact  the Head of School (&lt;a href="mailto:hos-cs@st-andrews.ac.uk" target="_blank"&gt;Alan Dearle&lt;/a&gt;) to discuss the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ref No: SK8461&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Closing Date: 27 July 2011&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Further Particulars: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a title="SK8461 FPs.doc" href="https://www.vacancies.st-andrews.ac.uk//ViewAttachment.aspx?enc=jmxpV+AcVus8i/wvT3FZXrrCOvCUGNWd9uca/tGZrAKkBI3fS3H34Ak8MaJGauYp16PBGkJvvg6h/76a/tO+eAUYDU8DBMrSRTfYsqNglCZqqkgRQL7X6l5iMefhKkvX" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SK8461 FPs.doc&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>st andrews</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/06/06/lectureship-computer-science-st-andrews/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2011 13:12:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The first year</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2010/10/22/first-year/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today marks the first anniversary of my moving to St Andrews. What have I learned since then?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's a strange feel to be reflecting on a year of my life, not least because it doesn't &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; like a year. Sometimes it feels like a lot less: I still feel very attached to Ireland, and I find that I spend a lot of time comparing the Scottish experience to y experiences of the previous twelve years. But in other ways it feels a lot &lt;em&gt;longer&lt;/em&gt; than a year, in that I think I've found a professional home in St Andrews that's exceptionally well-suited to my way of researching and teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what are the differences? There are several things that spring out. Firstly there's the size of the place -- or lack of it. The university has around 6,000 undergraduate students and maybe 2,000 graduate students, so it's significantly smaller than &lt;a href="http://www.ucd.ie"&gt;UCD&lt;/a&gt; -- about the same size as &lt;a href="http://www.tcd.ie"&gt;Trinity College Dublin&lt;/a&gt;, I suppose. This has a corresponding impact on class sizes, where a 30--40 student second-year class, and maybe 10--15 (or less) in third and fourth years, is considered perfectly normal. That in turn leads to a more individual and interactive style of teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second impact of size is in research, and especially in multi-disciplinary research. St Andrews is so small that one can know &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; (or at least anyone you want to), and can find and gain access to people doing research in whatever topics there are in the university that are of interest. In the past year I've interacted with marine scientists, astronomers, mathematicians, geographers, psychologists, medics and others, on a basis that will probably lead to some sort of proposal for collaboration or funding. One can do that in any full-spectrum university, of course, but size &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; make a difference: the intimacy of St Andrews, the fact that nowhere is more than a fifteen-minute walk away, makes it so much easier to interact. In a larger institution, and one with a larger computer science contingent, there's a strong tendency to remain within a smaller comfort zone that's not conducive to multi-disciplinary collaborations. I think we'll be able to leverage our smallness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, St Andrews takes teaching &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; more seriously than any other university I've worked in (or studied in, for that matter). All universities claim that teaching is a core part of their mission, of course, but it often doesn't get treated with the same urgency or seriousness as research. That's in part a function of how we're evaluated: both individual staff promotions and the most popular global university rankings are heavily biased towards research excellence, and staff and managers inevitably respond to those incentives. But I suspect it's more than that. St Andrews' processes are very focused on teaching, as is the academic culture, in a way that'd uncommon in my experience (which is limited to the UK and Ireland, of course). I do all my own teaching, all my own marking, and participate in small-group tutorials both for and beyond the modules I teach myself. Moreover the processes of assessment, tracking and evaluation of students' progress have tool support and are monitored from both the School and the centre. Other universities I've worked in don't have this degree of monitoring -- or indeed &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; monitoring. That doesn't mean that teaching isn't done well in those places, of course, but it does indicate where a university's priorities lie. (In case this sounds like altruism, it isn't: the National Student Survey results pull St Andrews up the rankings that take account of student satisfaction, and mean that the university can legitimately lay claim to offering an excellent experience to prospective students. It's a good example of the university taking a broader and longer-term view than other institutions.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following on from this, Scottish universities teach degrees with a "broad curriculum" in which students take a rather general two-year sub-honours programme before specialising into a further two-year honours programme. This provides  a broader base for students and avoids too-early specialisation, which I think is a good idea. I hadn't quite appreciated what a difference it makes in practice until earlier this week, when I did a lecture on the history of the internet and what its evolution means for society in terms of publishing, privacy, trust and access to information. I've done technical lectures like this to computer science students before -- I've used the evolution of the internet as a case study of large-scale systems design for software engineering students, for example -- but this was an introductory for first-year students from across the university, both sciences and humanities. That's not something that happens very often these days: in fact, in twelve years as an academic I've &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; lectured a broad-ranging class like that before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's something rather exciting about being able to address broader questions of technology's impact on society, and to set essay-style questions, when one is used to the more technical style of scientific lecturing. Not only does it allow a more far-reaching and questioning style of teaching, and the associated invitation to oneself to think through the broader questions: it also feels like it might have an impact, however small and however subtle, on a wide range of students who'll perhaps never encounter computer science again -- but who will undoubtedly be affected by it profoundly as part of its impact on society. It was particularly nice to bring the &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2010/06/smarter-internet/"&gt;recent discussions about the internet's effects on learning&lt;/a&gt; to their attention, as well as to talk about sensing and its effects on privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are there any things not to like? The lack of a senior common room is a little peculiar in a university of this age, only partially made-up for by a staff dining club that meets only infrequently. There are actually very few social occasions for staff across the university, which is a shame given the effort put in to student societies and the student experience: some more activities targeted at academics and researchers would be welcome. St Andrews itself is also somewhat remote from the rest of Scotland, more so than I first thought from looking on the map, but we've addressed this by moving to Edinburgh, which has everything one could want from a culturally vibrant city. I'm looking forward to what the next year may bring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>st andrews</category><category>university</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2010/10/22/first-year/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2010 08:15:17 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>