<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about studentships)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/studentships.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:simoninireland@gmail.com"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 19:17:45 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>PhD data science studentships available at Trinity College Dublin</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2015/09/18/phd-data-science/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;There are five PhD posts on offer to work with the ADAPT Centre.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

Benefits: Payment of tax-free stipend for 4 years.

In addition, payment of academic fees; fully for EU students and partially for non-EU students.

General enquires concerning this post can be addressed to &lt;a class="moz-txt-link-abbreviated" href="mailto:aoife.brady@adaptcentre.ie"&gt;aoife.brady@adaptcentre.ie&lt;/a&gt;.

Initial deadline is October 7th 2015, but with each position remaining open until filled. This and other positions listed under vacancies at: &lt;a class="moz-txt-link-freetext" href="http://adaptcentre.ie"&gt;http://adaptcentre.ie&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Research Topic&lt;/h4&gt;
Increasingly in data-driven enterprises, organisations are having to cope with a wide variety of information sources and standards, leading to a lack of interoperability and increasing data integration costs. Resulting labour-intensive data integration practices are brittle in the face of accelerating innovation in data-driven applications and growing demand for agile data analytics. At the same time organisations must react to increasing public and legislative focus on privacy and data protection. Empowering users to control the information that flows around them in a privacy-sensitive and personalised manner also offers many challenges.

These 5 PhD positions will advance the state of the art in linked data, semantic web and personalisation technologies to explore new approaches to data integration that are self-managing (towards autonomic), and in addition explore new ways to deliver personalised multimodal information (towards a digital companion).

These posts are part of the new ADAPT Centre (&lt;a class="moz-txt-link-freetext" href="http://www.adaptcentre.ie"&gt;http://www.adaptcentre.ie&lt;/a&gt;). ADAPT has received €50 Million research funding from Industry and Science Foundation Ireland to support 120 researchers across 4 universities in Dublin. The ADAPT Centre’s mission is to produce world class research that delivers disruptive innovations for the digital media and intelligent content industry. These PhD positions will be supervised by a member of the following ADAPT Centre academics; Professor Vincent Wade, Professor Declan O’Sullivan, Professor Dave Lewis, Professor Owen Conlan and Dr Rob Brennan.

ADAPT is Ireland’s global centre of excellence for digital content and media innovation. Led by TCD, it combines the expertise of researchers at four universities (Trinity College Dublin, Dublin City University, University College Dublin, and Dublin Institute of Technology) with that of its industry partners to produce ground-breaking digital content innovation.

ADAPT brings together more than 120 researchers who collectively have won more than €100m in funding and have a strong track record of transferring world-leading research and innovations to more than 140 companies. With EURO 50M in new research funding from Science Foundation Ireland and industry, ADAPT is seeking talented individuals to join its growing research team. Our research and technologies will continue to help businesses in all sectors and drive back the frontiers of future Web engagement.
&lt;h4&gt;Why join ADAPT @ TCD&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Work on hard, relevant problems in an interdisciplinary and exciting research environment. The ADAPT Centre combines expertise of researchers at Trinity College Dublin, Dublin City University, University College Dublin and Dublin Institute of Technology. It brings together more than 120 researchers who have collectively won more than €100M in competitive research funding and have an international track record of bridging research and innovations to more than 140 companies. With €50M in new research funding from SFI and industry, ADAPT research and technologies will help businesses in all sectors to manage, personalise and deliver digital content more effectively.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Work in a University where excellence of research is valued. Trinity College Dublin is Ireland’s premier University and is ranked in 71st position in the top 100 world universities by the QS World University Rankings 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Work in a centre focussed on advancing your career. Whether you want to take an academic, industrial, or entrepreneurial career path, ADAPT prides itself in the support and mentoring that enables all its Students and early-stage researchers to reach their full potential. This year alone its postdoc-to-PI programme has helped three postdocs transition to be Principal Investigators on their own H2020 projects, while four others have recently won funding with ADAPT support to realise the commercialisation of their research through spin outs and licensing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Requirements:&lt;/h4&gt;
The successful candidate will have an excellent academic record (first class or II.1 primary degree) in Computer Science or a related discipline. Experience in Knowledge Engineering is a distinct advantage. The successful candidate will be highly motivated, with strong written and oral communication skills and a demonstrated proficiency in software development, with strong design and programming skills. They must be eager to work in and learn from multi-disciplinary and multi-organisation teams. They should have English language certification if English is not their first language, the requirement being: IELTS: 7.0+, TOEFL iBT: 100+, TOEFL pBT: 600+, CEF: C1+, or equivalent.
&lt;h4&gt;Application Procedure&lt;/h4&gt;
For further information and informal contact, please refer to the PhD topic details. Please apply via email to &lt;a class="moz-txt-link-abbreviated" href="mailto:vacancies@adaptcentre.ie"&gt;vacancies@adaptcentre.ie&lt;/a&gt;, referencing this advert, and including:
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A targeted cover letter (600-1000 words) expressing your suitability for a position&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A complete CV&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
There will be an interview process; a successful candidate will then be invited to apply via the TCD graduate studies admission system.</description><category>big data</category><category>data science</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2015/09/18/phd-data-science/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2015 10:54:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>PhD studentships in St Andrews</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2015/03/10/studentships-st-andrews/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The School of Computer Science has a number of fully-funded PhD scholarships available.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

I'd be interested in hearing from anyone interested in working on complex systems, complex networks, sensor networks, or situation recognition. You can find more details about what I'm interested in &lt;a title="Research" href="http://www.simondobson.org/research/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I'm particularly interested in people wanting to cross disciplines somewhat, into applications in environmental science, medicine, or the digital humanities.

The full advertisement is &lt;a href="http://www.jobs.ac.uk/job/AKR549/funded-phd-research-studentships/" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Deadline for applications &lt;strong&gt;31 March 2015&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>phd</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2015/03/10/studentships-st-andrews/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2015 11:47:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>PhD Studentships at University College Cork</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2015/03/05/phd-studentships-university-college-cork/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;There are PhD positions open at University College Cork in the area of video processing.

&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;PhD Studentships at University College Cork in Ireland&lt;/h2&gt;
Closing Date for Applications: None, positions will remain open until filled. Applications will be reviewed at as soon as they are received.

&lt;strong&gt;Project:&lt;/strong&gt; An Internet Infrastructure for Video Streaming Optimisation (iVID)

The Mobile and Internet Systems Laboratory (MISL) in the Department of Computer Science at UCC is an internationally recognised research centre focused on innovative networking research. iVID is a new research project funded by Science Foundation Ireland to investigate the use of software defined networking (SDN) techniques to optimise the delivery of streaming video. A team of 5 project researchers will work on iVID, including 3 Ph.D. students. The project will involve collaboration with AT&amp;amp;T, EMC and the University of California Riverside.

Applications are invited for fixed-term studentships (annual value of €18K, plus fees) from suitably qualified candidates who wish to undertake a PhD within the Department of Computer Science. Applicants should have a Masters degree in computer science or a closely related discipline, although applications from truly exceptional students with a bachelor's degree will be considered. Ideally, applicants will have some project experience in the areas of video streaming, software defined networks, or more generally network protocols. Applicants must have strong mathematical ability and an interest in systems programming and experimental computer science. Applicants must demonstrate good inter-personal skills, and a high standard of spoken and written English. The positions are open to applicants of any nationality.

&lt;strong&gt;How to apply:&lt;/strong&gt; Applications by email to Mary Noonan &lt;a class="moz-txt-link-abbreviated" href="mailto:m.noonan@cs.ucc.ie"&gt;m.noonan@cs.ucc.ie&lt;/a&gt; and must include "PhD Studentship iVID" in the subject line. Applications must include, in PDF format only:
&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;1300 word personal statement explaining your interest in the project and networking research;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;full CV;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;copy of transcript(s) showing names of all courses taken and grades achieved; and&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;summaries of projects (BSc/MSC), internships and relevant work experience completed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
For more information on MISL and the Department of Computer Science, please see the links below.

&lt;a class="moz-txt-link-freetext" href="http://www.cs.ucc.ie/misl/"&gt;http://www.cs.ucc.ie/misl/
&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="moz-txt-link-freetext" href="http://www.cs.ucc.ie/"&gt;http://www.cs.ucc.ie/&lt;/a&gt;</description><category>phd</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2015/03/05/phd-studentships-university-college-cork/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2015 10:51:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fully-funded PhD scholarship available</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2015/02/03/phd-cs-med/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I have a fully-funded PhD scholarship available, tenable from September 2015, to work on data science in medicine.

&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;University of St Andrews&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;School of Computer Science&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;School of Medicine&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Funded PhD studentship&lt;/strong&gt;

The Schools of Computer Science and Medicine are looking to recruit a talented student to work on improving clinical trials of tuberculosis and other conditions using computational techniques.

TB and related conditions are extremely costly in human and financial terms, and trials of new drugs and therapies are complicated by difficult environmental conditions and other factors. Improvements to the trials process will potentially translate directly into improved interventions, and so will help save lives.

We seek to apply data-driven techniques to the design, analysis, and management of such trials. These techniques might include complex networks, computational epidemiology, machine learning, Bayesian analysis, and other cutting-edge approaches to data analytics. The ideal candidate will have an interest in data science applied to medical and biological problems, and an enthusiasm for working as part of a challenging multi-disciplinary project within St Andrews' new &lt;a href="http://www.idir.st-andrews.ac.uk" target="_blank"&gt;Institute for Data-Intensive Research (IDIR)&lt;/a&gt;.

The studentship will be held jointly between the two Schools, with supervisors from Computer Science (Prof Simon Dobson, &lt;a href="https://risweb.st-andrews.ac.uk/portal/en/persons/tom-kelsey%28289c44af-c861-4f85-a604-6be4e43855f1%29.html" target="_blank"&gt;Dr Tom Kelsey&lt;/a&gt;) and Medicine (&lt;a href="https://risweb.st-andrews.ac.uk/portal/da/persons/stephen-henry-gillespie%28ce4435fa-8cee-4e25-92fe-30f18dfec159%29.html" target="_blank"&gt;Prof Stephen Gillespie&lt;/a&gt;, Dr Ruth Bowness).  We offer a stimulating and supportive environment within a small and intimate university in a beautiful setting.

The scholarship is fully funded to cover tuition fees and stipend for a registration period normally expected to be three-and-a-half years.

Informal inquiries can be made in the first instance to &lt;a href="mailto:simon.dobson@st-andrews.ac.uk"&gt;Prof Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt;. Applications will be considered until mid-March.</description><category>data science</category><category>medicine</category><category>phd</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2015/02/03/phd-cs-med/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2015 12:12:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Scholarships available to study data science in Lancaster</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2014/06/10/data-science-lancaster/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The University of Lancaster has a new MSc programme starting in Data Science, with lots of full scholarships.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

The programme is a one-year MSc that allows specialisation in computing, statistics, or environmental science.

More details &lt;a href="http://www.lancaster.ac.uk/data-science/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.

 &lt;/p&gt;</description><category>data science</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2014/06/10/data-science-lancaster/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2014 14:43:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Funded PhD positions available</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2013/12/09/funded-phd-positions/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The School of Computer Science at the University of St Andrews has around eight  fully-funded PhD positions available. I'd welcome applicants interested in sensor networks, complex systems, and data science.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

We welcome students from a wide range of countries, our only major requirements being that you're excited by the idea of research and are able to conduct a complex programme within a small, friendly, and supportive environment.

In my case, I'm interested in hearing from potential students with interests in the following areas:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Sensor networks, especially deploying sensors into the environment;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Complex system modelling, trying to model phenomena that operate on a range of scales; and&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Data science, particularly for how we collect, categorise, and work with large scientific datasets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
An early conversation by skype or email could be followed by a formal application, the details of which are available &lt;a href="http://www.jobs.ac.uk/job/AHU246/funded-phd-research-studentships/" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.</description><category>phd</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2013/12/09/funded-phd-positions/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2013 09:46:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Studentship available in Newcastle upon Tyne</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2013/03/07/studentship/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;My colleagues in Newcastle (where I did my first degree) have an MRes/PhD position available in computational behaviour analysis.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

Together with colleagues from Agriculture, the &lt;a href="http://www.ncl.ac.uk/computing/" target="_blank"&gt;School of Computing Science in Newcastle&lt;/a&gt; have recently been active in the field of computational behaviour analysis in livestock animals. They have a small grant on which we are currently doing some  pilot work related to food safety and animal wellbeing, which has now given rise to funding for an integrated MRes / PhD studentship to work in this field.

The group wants to work on a system for automatic tracking of farm pigs (indoor) and on modelling their behaviour (as individuals and in the group) with the goal of early detection of changes therein that might be linked to  certain diseases. The project involves some very strong partners from and connections to agriculture and access to farms and industry.  The topic is extremely relevant for the UK industry and has wider societal impact (food safety, animal welfare). They are looking for strong CS candidates with a background in machine learning, signal processing, or computer vision, and an interest in working in an multi-disciplinary team on a challenging and very interesting topic with substantial societal and economic relevance.

The funding covers four years of fees and maintenance. UK home  students (and EU citizens who have been residents for at least three years) are eligible for the full funding, EU students essentially for 50%. Throughout the first year the student will be enrolled into an MRes program with courses and time to get familiar with the topic, which is a fantastic opportunity for students to obtain an interdisciplinary skill-set.

More details can be found &lt;a href="http://www.ncl.ac.uk/postgraduate/funding/search/list/CS043"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Application deadline is the 5th April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>pervasive systems</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2013/03/07/studentship/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2013 16:49:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Six 600th anniversary PhD scholarships</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2012/12/20/600th-scholarships/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;As part of St Andrews' 600th anniversary, the University is funding six scholarships in computer science (and all our other Schools, for that matter).

&lt;!--more--&gt;

Details are on &lt;a href="http://blogs.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/csblog/2012/12/20/600th-anniversary-phd-scholarships/" target="_blank"&gt;our web site&lt;/a&gt;. There's no special application process, and the studentships are open to all qualified applicants. You'd be well advised to research potential research supervisors and discuss things with them ahead of applying. Most staff -- including me -- will be accepting students under this scheme.

 &lt;/p&gt;</description><category>st andrews</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2012/12/20/600th-scholarships/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2012 19:22:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>MSc/PhD positions available in wireless location systems</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2012/08/03/mscphd-wireless-location/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;UCD Dublin is looking for potential PhD students interested in wireless location systems.

&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Ph.D. and M.Sc. Studentships in WiFi Location&lt;/h2&gt;
UCD Dublin is currently potential Ph.D. and M.Sc. students in the Complex and Adaptive Systems Laboratory and the School of Computer Science and Informatics, University College Dublin (UCD), Ireland. The studentships are part of a collaborative international project to research and develop novel algorithms, solutions and applications for indoor localization based on WiFi.

The successful candidates will have obtained, or will expect to obtain, a 1st class or 2.1 Honours degree in Computer Science, Electronic Engineering, or a related discipline. For the Ph.D. position, a Masters degree or commercial experience in a relevant area is an advantage. Preference will be given to applicants with expertise in one or more of the following areas: Digital Signal Processing, Location Estimation, and Wireless Communications.

We expect that the Ph.D. positions will be funded for 4 years while the M.Sc. position will be funded for 2 years. All positions are full-time. The positions will include payment of a tax-free student stipend and fees. The anticipated starting date for the positions is 1st October 2012, or as soon as possible thereafter.

Enquiries should be sent to Dr Chris Bleakley, Complex and Adaptive Systems Laboratory (CASL), School of Computer Science and Informatics (CSI), University College Dublin (UCD), Belfield, Dublin 4, Ireland; email: &lt;a href="mailto:chris.bleakley@ucd.ie"&gt;chris.bleakley@ucd.ie&lt;/a&gt;; tel: +353 1 716 5353.

&lt;a href="http://www.csi.ucd.ie/vacancy/phd-and-msc-studentships-wifi-location"&gt;http://www.csi.ucd.ie/vacancy/phd-and-msc-studentships-wifi-location&lt;/a&gt;

[Updated 13Aug2012 with final confirmation of the grant.]</description><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2012/08/03/mscphd-wireless-location/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 Aug 2012 10:56:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>5 studentships in Computer Science and St Andrews</title><link>https://simondobson.org/2012/05/17/5-studentships/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;We have five more PhD scholarships tenable from September, for students interested in any of our areas of research. The details are available &lt;a href="http://www.jobs.ac.uk/job/AEL878/funded-phd-research-studentship/" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Please note that I'm not taking on a PhD student this year, so don't bother applying to work with me.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>st andrews</category><category>studentships</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/2012/05/17/5-studentships/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2012 10:42:57 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>