<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Dobson (Posts about university)</title><link>https://simondobson.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://simondobson.org/categories/university.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:simon.dobson@computer.org"&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2022 08:05:41 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Commuting again</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2020/11/05/commuting/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, for the first time since mid-March, I went physically back to
my University to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/blog/2020/11/05/commuting/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>covid-19</category><category>essay</category><category>humour</category><category>pandemic</category><category>teaching</category><category>university</category><category>writing</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2020/11/05/commuting/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2020 13:20:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Laureation for Professor Dana Scott</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2014/06/26/scott-laureation/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had the honour (and the great personal pleasure) of inviting the Vice-Chancellor to bestow an honorary degree upon &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dana_Scott" target="_blank"&gt;Dana Scott&lt;/a&gt;, the inventor of some of the most influential ideas in computer science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vice-Chancellor, I have the privilege to present Professor Dana Scott for the degree of Doctor of Science, &lt;i&gt;honoris causa&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vice-Chancellor, colleagues, friends, ladies and gentlemen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For millennia, people have performed calculations, sometimes changing the way we live or understand the world. Many of these calculations have involved long, complicated sequences of actions — what we now refer to as &lt;i&gt;algorithms&lt;/i&gt;. But it was only in the 1930s that researchers such as Alonzo Church, John von Neumann, Alan Turing, and others formally studied &lt;i&gt;how &lt;/i&gt;we perform calculations, which rapidly opened-up the mechanisation of such operations and led to what we now know as computer science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does it mean to describe a calculation? For Turing, it meant designing an ideal machine whose small set of simple operations could perform computation — an operational view of computing that allows machines to perform tasks previously thought to require humans. But we can also think of computation independent of mechanisation, where mathematics can be applied to studying computation, and a theory of computation becomes available for the study of mathematics, physics, and other disciplines. And when we take this view, we are making use of ideas that owe their modern existence to the work of Dana Scott.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scott was a PhD student of the logician &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alonzo_Church" target="_blank"&gt;Alonzo Church&lt;/a&gt;, whom I mentioned earlier. Working with the late &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Strachey" target="_blank"&gt;Christopher Strachey&lt;/a&gt; at Oxford, Scott developed a theory of computation that allows calculations to be analysed, studied, and compared. Scott’s insight was to view computation as a steady increase in information. His development of the mathematical structures now known as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott_domain" target="_blank"&gt;Scott domains&lt;/a&gt; provided a way of precisely describing this progression. They in turn led directly to an approach for formally describing programs and programming languages — &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denotational_semantics" target="_blank"&gt;the Scott-Strachey approach to denotational semantics&lt;/a&gt; — and indirectly both to approaches to proving programs correct, and to the development of lazy functional programming languages that today form a major strand of computer science research: one to which St Andrews is proud to be making an on-going contribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If asked, most computer scientists would agree that denotational semantics forms Scott’s most lasting contribution; they might marvel that, later this year, at the age of 81, he will be delivering a keynote lecture in Vienna at the main international conference on computational logic; and they would probably be able to tell you that he is a recipient of the &lt;a href="http://amturing.acm.org/" target="_blank"&gt;Turing Award&lt;/a&gt;, often referred to as the “Nobel Prize for Computer Science”. However, Scott in fact &lt;a href="http://amturing.acm.org/award_winners/scott_1193622.cfm" target="_blank"&gt;won the Turing Award, jointly with Michael Rabin&lt;/a&gt;, for work on automata theory that predates his work on semantics. In other words, he won the highest accolade his discipline has to offer for work not generally considered to be his most significant. As you might imagine, this is a rather unusual occurrence: in fact, the only other example I can find in the entire history of science is the award of the Nobel Prize to Albert Einstein for work other than his theory of relativity. That’s not bad company to be keeping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we think of computers, we often think of their visible manifestations: the internet, mobile phones, aircraft flight control systems, Angry Birds. But no matter how impressive, and how much they continue to change our lives for the better, these systems are possible only because of the foundational intellectual developments that let us reason about proofs, calculations, and computations, as well as simply carrying them out. Vice Chancellor, the work of Dana Scott grounded the discipline of computer science, not only in a specific piece of theory, but also in an approach and a mindset that changed how we think about computing and, through this, has had a profound influence across the whole of human endeavour. It is in recognition of these seminal contributions to science that I invite you to confer upon Professor Dana Scott the degree of Doctor of Science, &lt;i&gt;honoris causa&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo &lt;a href="http://instagram.com/p/prF477OWRs/" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Thanks to Al Dearle, Steve Linton, Lisa Dow, and Muffy Calder for comments that made this better than the first draft I did.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>dana scott</category><category>honorary degree</category><category>university</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2014/06/26/scott-laureation/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2014 08:10:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>No-cost journals</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2014/02/14/nocost-journals/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What have scientific journals ever done for us? And can we get the benefits without the access issues?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"Open access" is a big thing in scientific publishing these days. The UK research councils, who fund a large fraction of the UK's academic research, have decided that papers arising from their research have to made available to any interested reader at no charge. The argument is that publicly-funded research results are a public good, and that other researchers should not be impeded in building on results. Since science progresses by researchers building on each others' work, there is plenty of justification for this view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You would think that open access wouldn't be a problem in these days of personal web pages and Google. However, when publishing a paper in a major journal, the authors typically sign away their copyright to the journal publisher, meaning that they can't legally make the paper freely available. The publishers in turn lock the papers away, either in dead-tree form (which they then sell to university libraries at exorbitant cost) or behind paywalls requiring individual or institutional subscription. The journals who do this are often the most important and prestigious venues, places where you want your work to appear, and scientists aren't going to stop publishing in these places any time soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address open access, some journals have started charging open access fees, whereby an author can pay to have their article made open access (i.e., to appear outside the paywall). Of course, anyone funded by a UK research council basically has to pay these fees to be compliant with their funding. Effectively, though, it means that institutions typically pay twice for publication: they pay the open access fee for individual articles, but still need to subscribe to the paid-for journal to get access to other papers. There are also open access journals that charge a publication fee for each accepted paper, but these are still quite new and with some exceptions (most notably &lt;a href="http://www.plosone.org/" target="_blank"&gt;PLoS&lt;/a&gt;) still fairly low-grade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These issues got me thinking: what do the journals actually give us? And could we get the benefit using internet technology without the costs?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically journals served as the primary means of academic communication, but clearly that time has passed. Nowadays journals give us two things:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;An editor and editorial board acting as guardians of the quality of the papers accepted. As a general rule, you never publish in a journal where you don't recognise any of the names on the editorial board: you want a journal managed by people known in your field.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A brand that gives readers confidence that this journal will contain significant work that justifies the time spent reading it.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Persistent storage of articles to give confidence that they can be found, referenced, and accessed in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
Clearly (2) is a function of (1), in the sense that the brand is built by the demonstrated consistently by the editorial board. It typically takes time to develop for a new journal. As to (3), persistent storage isn't much of a problem these days, but finding a copy of a paper could well be.
&lt;p&gt;In building our now-cost journal, we therefore need to replicate (1) and (3) in order to build (2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a possible workflow. We establish the journal's web site: the &lt;em&gt;St Andrews Journal of Interesting Things&lt;/em&gt;, perhaps. Like most journals, this allows prospective authors to submit their manuscripts, which are passed to the editorial board for review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academics typically serve on editorial boards for free. They are self-organising, in the sense that the editor-in-chief (EIC) appoints a set of trusted lieutenants consisting of his friends, colleagues, and people well-known in the field of the journal. Doing this well is a major skill -- but an individual one, dependent on the selection of a good EIC. The editorial board are assigned incoming papers, which they ask their friends and colleagues to review and provide comments one. Again, the selection of reviewers is critical to the quality of papers, as the reviewers are expected to assess the work presented and to suggest changes (or reject the paper completely). Academics typically review for free, too, so you'll notice that, for a typical journal, the total cost so far has been running the web server that manages the editorial process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Papers typically go around one or two rounds of revision before being accepted and published. The problem here is that we need to show readers that the paper has passed through the quality assurance of review. Anyone can put an article on the web, but journals guarantee that the work has been looked at and approved by the authors' scientific peers. (This doesn't guarantee that journal-published work is correct, merely that it's sufficiently convincing to a suitably qualified set of reviewers. There is always a steady stream of corrections, retractions, and withdrawals as flaws are found in work post-publication.) In a paid-for journal, the guarantee comes from printing on paper: you can check whether a paper purporting to appear in a journal actually does so by checking the appropriate volume. This of course implies printing and distribution, which publishers claim is source of their need for fees. For the St Andrews Journal of Interesting Things we want to avoid this cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, this is technically straightforward in a number of ways. The complicated way is to create a machine-readable metadata file containing the paper's title, authors, abstract, journal reference, associate editor in charge, and maybe some other details. We then bind this file cryptographically to the final ("camera-ready") manuscript. The cryptography guarantees two things: that the binding was done by the journal editor, and that neither file has been changed since being bound together. Anyone downloading the file bundle can then check that the metadata and manuscript match, and therefore knows that the paper is the one "published".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The simple way is to add a header to the manuscript text and then cryptographically sign the resulting file. This is trivially accomplished using a tool like Adobe Acrobat Pro, but is less attractive than the metadata approach because the header isn't machine-readable, making it harder to index the paper.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no cost associated with either of these approaches. We can then give the signed file back to the authors and tell them to place it on any web server that Google will index. This will let anyone searching for the file to find it: that's what search engines do. If we want to be really thorough, we would keep track of where the files are stored, and/or perform regular searches to locate them (easy enough given machine-readable metadata), and maintain a journal web page listing the published papers and linking to them. (Total cost: one web page.) If we want to be &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; thorough we can mint &lt;a href="http://www.doi.org/" target="_blank"&gt;Digital Object Identifiers&lt;/a&gt; that resolve through our web server to the paper locations. (Total cost: a small database and a single CGI script on our web server.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've now recreated the publication side of the journal industry, essentially for free. This leaves the branding issue. There are two sides to establishing a brand: quality and visibility. The quality of the product, as mentioned above, relies on the selection of editorial and review teams and their willingness to serve at no cost, as is normal in academic publishing. The visibility issue is harder to crack, but could be addressed using the web, by viral marketing and appearances at conferences that editorial board members were attending, by word of mouth through the research community -- and even by advertising in the paid-for journals themselves, possibly. One great thing about the web and social media is that word &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; get out: after that, it's a matter of the quality of papers accepted and the willingness of authors to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not actually planning on setting up a new journal. The point is that 21st century research doesn't need the friction and costs imposed by journals whose main editorial services are provided free by their consumers anyway. We should be able to do away with these costs without sacrificing the quality of material that we read or the reliance we place upon it.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>publishing</category><category>science</category><category>university</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2014/02/14/nocost-journals/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2014 08:30:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Graduation address: "Every success is everybody's success"</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2013/11/30/every-success/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was honoured to be asked to give the graduation address at this year's St Andrews Day ceremony. The speech is below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chancellor, Principal, colleagues, friends, ladies and gentlemen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduations are a celebration of hard work and success. And the efforts you've all made to be sitting here today certainly deserve to be celebrated: whatever your course of study, you've shown the determination, dedication, intelligence, creativity, and drive to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But being asked to give this graduation address got me thinking about the nature of success, and I'd like to share a thought with you: that success is not something we can readily ascribe to anyone individually. Rather, it's a jigsaw that assembles itself from the actions of those people you meet and by whom you are influenced. Indeed, when you get right down to it, every success is everybody's success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see what I mean by this, think about how much had to go right for your studies to take place. You had to be born and brought up in a way that made you emotionally able to leave home and thrive on your own, possibly mastering a different language and culture, to become a rounded individual with the skills needed to take on a university such as this. This is no mean feat on the parts of yourselves and your parents, as I hope you appreciate; not to mention your earlier teachers, friends, neighbours, and all the other people who influenced you down the years. When you came to St Andrews, I'm sure you discovered that learning and research don't occur in a vacuum. Most of you will have worked as part of a team, either in a lab or a seminar, where you came together to do something that perhaps none of you could have done individually. If you think back, I'm sure you can remember plenty of things said or done that have contributed directly to your being here today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can cast the net wider. The university is clean, secure, and well-managed, thanks to the efforts of porters, cleaners, secretaries, administrators, and a host of others -- efforts that tend to be hidden away and are easily forgotten, but that contribute to your studies at least as much as the efforts of your lecturers. The lights are on, the labs and seminar rooms are warm (more or less). There are coal miners in eastern Poland whom we will never meet, and who will never know to what they contributed -- but without them the wheels would not have turned, the lights would not have burned, and none of the functions that we perform in this university would have been possible. So every success that happens here is their success too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course we should look through time as well as space. With this graduation we're coming to the end of celebrating the 600th anniversary of the University of St Andrews. Think what has happened over those six hundred years to get us here! All the discovery and learning, all the patient, careful scholarship down through the years, slowly building knowledge, slowly building the reputation of this University, and of Scotland, as a place to come to learn and to teach and to do research -- sparkling at this graduation today before ricocheting off into the future. Any successes any of us have here owe a debt to those who have come before us, who made this (frankly very unlikely) place possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there's any substance to these musings, then it's this: success isn't the singular, individual thing that we sometimes like to think it is; but nor is it an atomised, isolated thing occurring outside a particular place in space and time and the flow of humanity. The modern world tends to focus on measurement, and the corollary that anything that can't be easily measured either didn't happen at all or at least can be safely ignored. But a moment's reflection will convince you that this is nonsense: the successes we're celebrating today have been guided and driven by influences that we would struggle to identify and certainly couldn't quantify in any meaningful way, but without which we would not all be sitting here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has some quite profound implications. It means that whatever you all do from today, whatever successes you enjoy in the years to come, are of real importance, no matter how small they may appear to you. Your research project may not give rise to the next Google: but it might be read by someone, who writes a thesis, that's read by someone else, that gives another person an idea, that someone else uses to change the world for the better. We'll never know the exact details of this process -- we'll certainly never measure it or report it -- but lack of public credit doesn't equate to lack of value, and that's something that can help keep us all motivated and generous with our time and our ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So as well as celebrating your own individual successes today, I hope you'll also celebrate the contributions you've made to the successes of others through friendship, collaboration, advice, mutual support, tutoring -- or just simply being here. Every success really is everybody's success. Thank you, and enjoy the rest of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(And in keeping with this spirit, I'd like to thank &lt;a href="http://blogs.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/al/" target="_blank"&gt;Al Dearle,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/directory/person?id=sal" target="_blank"&gt;Steve Linton,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.linda-rafferty.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Linda Rafferty&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/directory/person?id=lisa" target="_blank"&gt;Lisa Dow&lt;/a&gt;, for their comments that made this speech so much better than when I first wrote it. The official press release version is on the &lt;a href="http://www.st-andrews.ac.uk/news/archive/2013/title,231150,en.php" target="_blank"&gt;university web site&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>st andrews</category><category>talk</category><category>university</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2013/11/30/every-success/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2013 09:00:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The closed cycle of MOOCs</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2013/10/18/closed-cycle/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Are the international rankings indirectly fuelling the rise of MOOCs? And is there a positive feedback cycle at work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emergence of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massive_open_online_course" target="_blank"&gt;Massively Open On-line Courseware or MOOCs&lt;/a&gt; is being hailed as a disruptive moment in education, similar to the revolution that overtook the music industry. By unbundling modules from degree programmes and the universities who deliver them, the promise is to allow more personalised, varied, accessible, and (most importantly) cheaper education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's easy to see how MOOCs benefit some students in some disciplines. Students living in remote places, from the developing world to the rural US (or rural Ireland, for that matter) can access courses from leading universities they would otherwise not be able to, or want to, attend physically. Students with disabilities, or those with significant work, family, or care commitments can more easily stitch education into their lives, freed from the constraints of structured and time-bounded degree programme. &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2013/01/mooc-student/"&gt;Modules available&lt;/a&gt; either free or at massively reduced cost will certainly broaden access and reduce the real or perceived elitism of the top institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think there are some serious caveats with the techno-utopian vision that's being propagated, not least the suitability of MOOCs for many subjects and the way that much of the innovation is more about control than about openness -- and these are topics I intend to return to. But for this post I want to focus on a narrower hypothesis: is there a positive feedback cycle in the economics of students and rankings driving at least some of the push towards MOOCs from some institutions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What got me thinking about this is the release of the &lt;a href="http://www.topuniversities.com/university-rankings/world-university-rankings/2013#sorting=rank+region=+country=+faculty=+stars=false+search=" target="_blank"&gt;latest QS World Ranking of Universities&lt;/a&gt;. These are influential sources that (I can say from personal experience) influence students' (and their parents') choices about which university to attend. This is simply a fact: one can argue that position in a research-based league table will have only a moderate influence on an undergraduate's university experience and later employability, but that's doesn't stop people considering the them important. Indeed, it is such an important factor that many universities publicly make being in the top 200, top 100, or even top 5 an institutional strategic goal that influences all their decisions. (For full disclosure, St Andrews comes comfortably in the top 100 universities in the world in this ranking, and doesn't use ranking position as an element of its strategy. It's nice for us to be highly ranked, but this is a consequence of our activities not a determiner of them.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rising up to the top of the tables is expensive, and I suspect that it gets exponentially more expensive to climb higher the higher up one is. The top-ranked institutions are amongst the richest in the world: Harvard, Stanford, MIT, and the like all have enormous economic power alongside their obvious and uncontested academic excellence. They are also major players in the MOOC space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first blush, this seems counter-intuitive. MOOCs are about cost reduction and breaking the power of traditional providers: why would the top universities be involved in this, when it seems at least possible that such a move will cannibalise their bricks-and-mortar students? It's likely they don't see this as a real threat, since they're over-subscribed by several orders of magnitude more students than they can possibly accommodate. It's also possible that they see MOOCs as a branding exercise rather than one of education, raising their profile at essentially no significant cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, a more economic driver also occurs to me, at least when one moves down out of the elite stratosphere. Many institutions want to move up the league tables, which often involves going shopping for star academics: people whose research excellence enhances the reputation of their employers. As an institution gets more highly ranked, the quality of academic they need to have any impact on their position also increases, and as star academics are generally more expensive, improving ranking involves increased expenditure at each step. Increasing staff cost is therefore a consequence of a strategic decision to climb the rankings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These stars and their research infrastructure have to be paid for, and in many systems these costs more or less trickle-down to student fees. Education inflation is running well ahead of general price inflation in the US (see for example &lt;a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-10-24/u-s-colleges-raise-tuition-4-8-outpacing-inflation.html" target="_blank"&gt;this article from 2012&lt;/a&gt;), and a large chunk of this comes from academic salaries. (Admittedly an even larger chunk comes from increased administration.)  The problem is that this inflation sets up a countervailing pressure, as students look at the costs of their education in terms of accrued student debt and contrast it against expected lifetime earnings -- and in some cases decide it's not a sufficiently valuable proposition. Physical institutions can't simply grow their numbers, since students attending a university have overhead costs: they have to be accommodated nearby at a price they can afford to pay, if nothing else. The pressure therefore builds up to reduce student costs while keeping the size of the student body roughly constant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where MOOCs might come in. Star academics have celebrity that can be leveraged by getting them to develop MOOC courses that can be sold worldwide. Even a trickle of income (from up-front registration or charges for certification) provides a revenue stream that can be used to reduce the costs for traditional students. MOOC development is sometimes seen as cost-free (since the staff are in place already), and so the revenue feels like money for nothing. But as MOOCs become more popular, institutions require more MOOCs, and more star academics to make them, and hence more revenue to pay for these individuals and their research, and so more MOOCs: a feedback loop that might actually become self-sustaining, a bubble in MOOC provision driven by a desire for increased international rank with a stable bricks-and-mortar student body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any such bubble will be an issue for universities of less exalted status, since the provision of free courses from elite institutions looks set to change how students seek out knowledge, despite the fact that not everyone is an autodidact who can learn by themselves. It's still not clear what impact MOOCs will have on education in its broadest sense, and there are certainly many positive aspects that we're interested in exploring ourselves. A self-fulfilling bubble is however not something we should be indifferent to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>moocs</category><category>teaching</category><category>university</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2013/10/18/closed-cycle/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2013 13:00:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>How to write an abstract</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2013/08/18/abstracts/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An abstract is an advertisement, not an introduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've spent much of this week working with MSc students writing their dissertations, and this has inevitably led to the part of a dissertation that often causes the most pain to write (and read, for that matter): the abstract.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the abstract of a report or paper? What it &lt;em&gt;isn't&lt;/em&gt; is an introduction or guide to the rest of the document: that, unsurprisingly, is what the introduction is for. The goal of an abstract is much simpler: it's intended to persuade the reader to read some or all of the rest of the document. It may be surprising that this is an issue, but in a world in the grip of an information explosion it's clear that readers' attention is a limiting quantity in information processing. As a reader, should you bother to read a paper? Or not? And how do you make this decision?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many new researchers, when confronted with a paper, start at the front and work forward. More experienced researchers know this is a mistake that leads to reading whole tracts of irrelevance or nonsense. (The former is worse: nonsense at least has occasional entertainment value.) This leads many people (myself included) to adopt a non-linear reading style:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Read the abstract&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;If still interested, read the conclusion&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;If &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; interested, read the introduction&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;If it's &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; interesting, read the rest of the paper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
(There are several variants, a couple of which are described &lt;a href="http://www.sciencebuddies.org/science-fair-projects/top_science-fair_how_to_read_a_scientific_paper.shtml" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.wikihow.com/Read-a-Scientific-Paper" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.) The point here is that we can filter out papers of lesser interest to reserve time and head space for the most interesting. Only if the results grab your attention do you need to spend time discovering the detail of how they were obtained -- rather than doing that work only discover that you don't care about the results being reported.
&lt;p&gt;The abstract is the key: without a decent description of what the paper is about, the discerning reader will not proceed even to the introduction, and therefore any work contained in the paper will remain unread -- and therefore be largely worthless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how does one write a decent abstract? Most experienced scientists have their own technique, and the approach does need to vary from field to field and for different paper styles: a review paper is different to a piece of primary research. The approach I've come to rely on for research in computer science and mathematics can be described succinctly as &lt;strong&gt;the five-sentence abstract&lt;/strong&gt;. I've found five sentences seems to be about optimal, structured as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="color: red"&gt;The area of the paper (1 sentence).&lt;/span&gt; The problem area to which this paper makes a contribution.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="color: orange"&gt;The issue the paper addresses (1 sentence).&lt;/span&gt; Presumably the area is not yet fully explored, and you've found a problem that needs tackling -- otherwise what's in your paper?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="color: green"&gt;What you've done, the results you've obtained (2 sentences).&lt;/span&gt; The key contribution of the paper, what you've added to practice and/or knowledge&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="color: blue"&gt;What this means (1 sentence).&lt;/span&gt; Why should anyone care?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's do an example, from a paper I've always wanted to write about finding unicorns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span style="color: red"&gt;There are lots of interesting animals out there, many of which have horns.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="color: orange"&gt;No-one has yet reported observing any one-horned horses, however.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="color: green"&gt;We describe our research survey of the horses of the West of Ireland. While we found many horses, and many other horned animals, we failed to locate any horned horses.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="color: blue"&gt;We conclude that further research is required to find unicorns, preferably in an equally pleasant holiday destination.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, perhaps not a great example. Let's try another, from a real paper:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span style="color: red"&gt;In the domain of ubiquitous computing, the ability to identify the occurrence of situations is a core function of being context-aware.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="color: orange"&gt;Given the uncertain nature of sensor information and inference rules, reasoning techniques that cater for uncertainty hold promise for enhancing the reasoning process.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="color: green"&gt;In our work, we apply the Dempster Shafer theory of evidence to infer situation occurrence with the minimal use of training data. We describe a set of evidential operations for sensor mass functions using context quality and evidence accumulation for continuous situation detection.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="color: blue"&gt;We demonstrate how our approach enables situation inference with uncertain information using a case study based on a published smart home data set.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Taken from McKeever, Ye, Coyle and Dobson. &lt;a href="http://www.simondobson.org/softcopy/ds-situation-inference-eurossc-09.pdf"&gt;Using Dempster-Shafer theory of evidence for situation inference&lt;/a&gt;. In Proceedings of the 4th European Conference on Smart Sensing and Context (EuroSSC). Volume 5741 of LNCS. Springer-Verlag. Guildford, UK. 2009.) The abstract goes from domain to challenge to approach to significance: having read it, the reader hopefully has a fairly good idea of what the paper contributes to which domain, and why this contribution is significant (in the authors' minds, at least).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shorter is often better, of course:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div title="Page 1"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span style="color: red"&gt;Wireless sensor networks are attracting increasing interest&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="color: orange"&gt;but suffer from severe challenges such as power constraints and low data reliability. Sensors are often energy-hungry and cannot operate over the long term, and the data they gather are frequently erroneous in complex ways. The two problems are linked, but existing work typically treats them independently:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="color: green"&gt;in this paper we consider both side-by-side,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="color: blue"&gt;and propose a self-organising solution for model-based data collection that reduces errors and communications in a unified fashion.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(From Fang and Dobson. &lt;a href="http://www.simondobson.org/softcopy/iwsos-faults-energy.pdf"&gt;Unifying sensor fault detection with energy conservation&lt;/a&gt;. In Proceedings of the 7th International Workshop on Self-Organising Systems (IWSOS'13). Palma de Mallorca, ES. May 2013.) In this case my student Lei messed with the sentence structure because we wanted to get across the idea that the main problem was the totality of the existing approach to the problem, which we wanted to address as a whole. The abstract still follows the basic structure, and I think is stronger for being shorter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No rule of writing is hard-and-fast, of course, and so you'll often find great abstracts that adopt a completely different approach. I don't think this matters so much as ensuring that the abstract is fit for purpose: an enticement to read further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>university</category><category>writing</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2013/08/18/abstracts/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2013 12:03:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Being a student with open courseware</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2013/01/23/mooc-student/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The move towards massively open on-line courseware (MOOCs) has the potential fundamentally to change the practice and experience of university. But what does it feel like to study on a MOOC-delivered course?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No-one in academia can have been indifferent to the influence the internet has had on their teaching and research over the past decade, but MOOCs are a significant development nonetheless. They represent an attempt to "unbundle" education from the traditional providers, reducing barriers to entry and costs to students while facilitating alternative styles of learning and attendance not always supported in existing institutions. It's impossible to generalise about how universities deliver their material, but it's fair to say that the ability to study a bespoke programme at one's own speed and from whatever location is convenient is a significant departure from the usual three-to-four-year resident degree programme. (See, for example, Salman Khan. &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/2398356.2398370" target="_blank"&gt;What college could be like&lt;/a&gt;. Communications of the ACM &lt;strong&gt;56&lt;/strong&gt;(1). January 2013.) Like most other research-led institutions, St Andrews is exploring on-line learning and MOOCs -- in our case as part of the &lt;a href="http://www.futurelearn.com" target="_blank"&gt;FutureLearn&lt;/a&gt; initiative. But planning a radical style-change in teaching doesn't really work if it's purely "from the top", as it's the experience "from the bottom", as a student, that will dictate whether an approach succeeds or fails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I signed up to take a MOOC module. We're only in Week 3 (of 12) at present, but it's worth making some early observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To avoid embarrassing the providers, I won't identify the lecturer or module. Suffice to say it's being delivered on one of the three major platforms for MOOCs; is delivered by a tenured academic at one of the world's top universities; is a science subject, not a humanity; and is not in computer science or mathematics, to avoid the risk of my subject expertise getting in the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experience of signing up is as simple and straightforward as one would expect from a modern web provider, with each module being given its own home page containing links to all the videoed lecture material, practicals, class tests, and a discussion forum. Clearly a lot of work has gone into preparing all the material: around 30 hours of video (with closed captioning) plus materials for formative and summative assessment: it's a substantial investment of time by all concerned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, this particular module is being run by the originating university as an experiment, to see how best they can deploy on-line learning. The student cohort includes both on-line students and students resident on campus for a "traditional" programme -- with the former outnumbering the latter by two orders of magnitude. Both sets are taking the same classes and assessments, but the resident students can also avail of a lecture each week "on demand" on any subject they feel needs more attention. This could be seen as a safety net in case the on-line experience is less than satisfactory, but also as a feedback loop to refine the module for next time: without this, it'd be harder to work out which parts needed more explanation, as always happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main course material is divided into units with about two hours of video material each, split into convenient sections which can be watched on-line or downloaded. The partitioning is convenient both for students and (I suspect) for the lecturer, who can record them in shorter "takes" to simplify correction and re-recording. The videos as typically either the lecturer as a "talking head" against a plain background, or a slide set onto which the lecturer writes additional notes as he talks. (Sometimes a single video piece includes both styles.) Having handwriting appear works better than might be expected: it keeps the human connection, is less mechanical and more engaging than might be the case with purely printed slides. Some sections also include in-line multiple-choice questions for students to answer to check understanding during the lecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a lecture on video has a number of advantages, not least the ability to pause and repeat arbitrarily. I found this useful for note-taking, in that I could listen to a section, pause it to write summary notes, and not miss what the lecturer said next. A more experienced student note-taker might be able to multi-task enough for this not to matter. Note-taking is important for its own sake, of course, as it activates other parts of your brain than listening alone and makes the material much more engaging and likely to stick. Repetition has been less useful, which may just be a reflection of the level of the material so far, and a non-native English-speaker would probably find it invaluable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The module assessment includes some labs, which to get the whole class involved had to occur at set times: 9pm UK time was bad enough, but of course Indian and Chinese students had it much worse! However, the lab software didn't work: I think it simply couldn't handle the demand of the student numbers, although it was hard to tell for sure from my outsider's viewpoint. The lecturer ended up dropping the entire lab component and changing the rubric, which seemed substantially easier than the same task would have been in St Andrews, where it would have raised questions about the fairness of assessment. In this case it probably reflects teething troubles, but it does highlight some of the concerns that have been raised about the standard of examination (and consequently the value of certification) from MOOC-delivered courses: does the module actually still make sense without the labs with which it was designed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remaining assessment consists of problems sets and an examination. All of these have deadlines, but with a sliding scale of lateness penalty (up to a fortnight) within which students can still submit. This seems reasonable for an on-line module, especially when one has no visibility of, or expectation about, students' personal circumstances. The marking overhead for assessment will be substantial, however, as the problem sets aren't all multiple-choice -- although they do show signs of being designed for large-scale grading. Coming from a university with small classes (less than a hundred is the norm, less than twenty not exceptional), this would require a significant change in my style of assessment -- although to be fair, no university is set-up for class sizes in the tens of thousands that could easily attend a MOOC. This remains a major academic and technical challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion forum was a particularly interesting experience. There are a number of teaching assistants as well as the lecturer monitoring the discussions, answering a guiding questions, and students get credit for their engagement in discussions. Some students were noticeably more active, offering a range of different experiences and levels of expertise. Some clearly know enormously more about the subject matter than has been taught, possibly students of this area trying to supplement their experience with modules from another -- perhaps more prestigious -- university. Others, it rapidly became clear, are actually academics doing exactly what I'm doing: attending the class for interest, but really studying the MOOC and its experience. As I said, MOOCs are not an area any institution is willing to let pass by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall the experience is broadly positive, and I'm not concerned about any of the technological challenges posed: they're simply those of any large, distributed computer system. But I think at least four questions arise about how to do this sort of learning well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it's clear that there's an immense amount of work involved at the back end of any MOOC, in terms of its design and preparation but also in terms of timetabling, support and -- especially -- assessment. Unless one is willing to accept multiple-choice questions or other approaches that can be mechanised it's hard to see how this can be avoided, and it's at a scale that few if any first-tier institutions have experience with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the feeling of a class community is notably absent, and discussion boards can't make up for face-to-face interaction and live discussion. Especially in a small institution like St Andrews, the student experience -- of a small, closely-knit class in daily close contact with lecturers, demonstrators, and the wider student body -- is a major attraction, one that is highlighted by our teaching fellows and in all our student surveys, and one that would be hard to match in a distance setting. Perhaps this is simply academic snobbery: the cost of such an experience may be prohibitive for a progressively larger fraction of potential students. On the other hand, its pedagogical advantages are unquestionable. If we simply accept the difference, we run the risk of consigning a large group of students to a study experience we &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; to be sub-standard -- and indeed have &lt;em&gt;designed&lt;/em&gt; to be such. Are there ways to provide an equivalent, if not better, experience? This has to be a major topic for future research, and has technological and sociological dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, distance interrupts the feedback loops that usually exist between a lecturer and their material, and between lecturer and class. In a local setting, feedback is generally immediate and clear: you can tell pretty much instantly if a class isn't engaged with or understanding the material, and adjust accordingly. In a distance setting, feedback is indirect and time-delayed, moderated by students' willingnesses to criticise or complain about their lecturers, which I would expect to complicate the refinement of a module that usually happens. Again, designing a better experience is probably not an insoluble problem, but it is an urgent one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there's the issue of coherence in a system in which one can make arbitrary module choices. I'm a great believer in broad curricula and plenty of options, but one often wants to get a degree in &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;, and this requires structuring either for professional or academic reasons. Without such structure, certification of what the student has learned, and how well, become a lot more difficult. But even beyond this, there's a problem of the embarrassment of choice, and of not knowing what one should study to accomplish whatever learning goal one has. This is a function often provided by advisers, counsellors and other staff within a university, who can help students understand what to study and &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2011/09/people-university/" target="_blank"&gt;why they're going to university in the first place&lt;/a&gt;. Their function is easily forgotten in distance learning, but seems to me to be vital for successful learning outcomes and eventual student satisfaction. It certainly suggests that the notion of distance learning needs to be broadened significantly beyond the content if it's to offer a real alternative to a "normal" degree: indeed, the content sometimes feels almost irrelevant, given the avalanche of material available on the web outside the MOOC universe. Curation, direction and socialisation feel like far more dominant challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I decided to conduct this experiment, I thought it would draw me into the technology of MOOCs. It didn't: the technology is well done, but unexceptional. The content is great, but again no more impressive than any number of other sources on the internet. (Admittedly a sample size of one is hardly conclusive….) The sociology, however, is another matter: there's clearly a need to study the ways in which people experience learning through computers, at a distance, and in distributed groups across which one wants to establish a cohort effect, and how the universities can leverage their expertise in this into the on-line world. It'll be interesting to see what happens next.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>moocs</category><category>strategy</category><category>teaching</category><category>university</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2013/01/23/mooc-student/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2013 08:00:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Inaugural lecture</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/11/25/inaugural/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will be giving my inaugural lecture on the topic of "The computer is the new microscope."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's traditional when appointed a full professor in the UK (strictly speaking, when appointed full prof for the first time) to give an open lecture on a topic of your choice. Because the lecture is open to anyone, they have to be very accessible (well, as accessible as the academic can make it, which often diverges from the normal meaning of "accessible"). My choice of topic follows on from a subject &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2010/04/computer-microscope/" target="_blank"&gt;I've been thinking about for a while&lt;/a&gt;, that computers change both the way we do science and the science we do, and that this needs to be more fully understood within both communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Date: 7 December, 2011
Time: 1715
Venue: Lecture theatre, Medical and Biological Science Building, University of St Andrews, North Haugh, St Andrews, Fife&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Followed by a reception in the School of Computer Science next door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[UPDATE 16Dec2011: the &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/research/publications#TheComputerIsTheNewMicroscope11"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; are now available.]&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>sensor networks</category><category>university</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/11/25/inaugural/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2011 12:49:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why do people go to university?</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/09/08/people-university/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Changes to admissions systems in the UK and Ireland simply tinker with the existing approach. They don't address the more fundamental changes in the relationship between university education, economic and social life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We're in the middle of a lot of changes in academia, with the fees increase for students in England eliciting a response in Scotland, and a &lt;a href="http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/opinion/2011/0908/1224303701553.html"&gt;report in Ireland suggesting changes to the "points" system of admissions&lt;/a&gt; to introduce more targeting. Despite the upsets these changes cause to academics -- they heighten the arbitrary and distressing discontinuity in costs between Scottish and English students in St Andrews, for example -- they're actually quite superficial in the sense of not massively changing the degrees on offer or their structure. However, these would seem to be the areas in which change could be most fruitful, in response to changing patterns of life, patterns of access to information and the like. It's hard to generate enthusiasm for this amid the problems of managing the financial structures. In other words, the fees &lt;em&gt;débâcle&lt;/em&gt; may be masking changes that we would otherwise be well advised to make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are these changes? First of all we need to understand what we believe about the lives and futures of the people who might attend university. For me this includes the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People don't know what they're passionate about.&lt;/strong&gt; Passionate enough to want to spend a substantial portion of their lives on it, that is. There's a tendency to follow an "approved" path into a stable career, and this in may in some cases lead people to do the "wrong" degree as they worry about their job prospects. But if you're going into a career in something, you have to accept that you'll spend about half your waking life on it. It makes sense to be sure you'll enjoy it. So we need to focus on allowing people to find their passions, which argues against too-early specialisation and for a broader course of study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;My first postdoc supervisor, Chris Wadsworth, told me about 20 years ago that "it takes you 10 years to decide what you're actually interested in." In your mid-20s you tend to disregard statements like this and assume you &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; what your research interests are, but on reflection he was right: it &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; take me about 10 years to work out what I wanted to spend my career researching, and it wasn't really what I was doing back then: related, yes, but definitely off to one side. I've also become interested in a whole range of other things that were of no interest to me back then, not least because most of them didn't exist. If that's true of an academic, it's just as true of an 18-year-old undergraduate. You can have an idea what you like and what interests you, but not much more than that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We can't teach enough.&lt;/strong&gt; It used to be simpler: go to university, learn all the things you'll need, then go and practice those skills with marginally upgrading for the rest of your career. I can't think of many topics like that any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This changes the emphasis of education: it's not the stuff we teach that's important, it's the ability to upskill effectively. For that you need foundations, and you need to know the important concepts, and you need to be able to figure out the details for yourself. It's not that these details aren't important -- in computing, for example, they're critical -- but they're also changing so fast that there's no way we &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; keep up. And in fact, if we &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt;, we'd be doing the students a dis-service by suggesting that this isn't a process of constant change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The jobs that people will want to do in 20 years' time don't exist now.&lt;/strong&gt; Fancy a career as a web designer? Didn't exist 20 years ago; 10 years ago it was a recognised and growing profession; lately it's become part and parcel of graphic design. The world changes &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; rapidly. &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2011/07/arts-humanities/"&gt;Even if the job you love still exists&lt;/a&gt;, there's a good chance you'll want to change to another one mid-career. Again, the ability to learn new skills becomes essential. I suspect a lot of people -- including politicians -- haven't appreciated &lt;em&gt;just how fast&lt;/em&gt; the world is changing, and that the pace of change is accelerating. You don't have to believe in &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Technological_singularity"&gt;the Sigularity&lt;/a&gt; to believe that this has profound implications for how economies and careers work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We don't know where the future value comes from.&lt;/strong&gt; In a time of increased financial stress, governments fall back on supporting courses that "obviously" support economic growth: the STEM subjects in science, engineering, technology and medicine. The only problem with this as an argument is that it's wrong. Most of the value in the digital age &lt;em&gt;hasn't&lt;/em&gt; come from these areas. The profits at Apple and Google pale into insignificance behind the aggregate profits of the companies (often much smaller) making content to add value to the devices and services these companies provide. I've argued before that &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2011/07/arts-humanities/"&gt;this value chain is best supported by humanities graduates&lt;/a&gt;, not scientists and engineers. (If you want a supporting example, consider this as a proposition: the whole argument about network neutrality is essentially an argument about whether  ISPs should be allowed to tax the producers and consumers of the content they transmit in terms of its end-user value, rather than in terms of its transmission cost. That's where the value is.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does the above have anything to suggest about changes in admissions or the structure of degrees. To me it suggests a number of things. Have broad introductory years in which students are encouraged to explore their wider interests before specialising. (The Scottish broad curriculum attempts to do this, but in sciences we don't do it particularly well.) Focus teaching on core principles and on how these affect the evolution of tools and techniques. Also focus on students learning the tools and techniques themselves, and showing how they relate back to the taught core. Generate a set of smaller degree-lets that people can take over their career with less commitment: at a distance, in the evening, in compressed blocks, over a long period -- whatever, just suitable for people to do alongside working at something else. Above all, don't assume we (either the universities or the State) can pick winners in terms of subjects. We're definitely in a post-industrial world, that means new intellectual territory and that what worked before won't always work in the future. I hope &lt;a href="https://simondobson.org/2010/04/computer-microscope/"&gt;computer science will continue to change the world&lt;/a&gt;, but I'm also completely confident that a history graduate will come up with one of the Next Big Things.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>ireland</category><category>university</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/09/08/people-university/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2011 10:56:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>On not funding the arts and humanities</title><link>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/07/05/arts-humanities/</link><dc:creator>Simon Dobson</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we don't adequately fund the arts, where will all the digital content come from?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent noises from within the UK's funding structures suggest that the future for arts and humanities education is somewhat threatened. In a time of restricted resources (the argument goes) the available funding needs to be focused on topics that make a clear, traceable contribution to the national economy. This essentially means supporting the STEM subjects -- science, technology, engineering and medicine -- at the expense of the arts and humanities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a computer scientist I might be expected to be loosely in favour of such a move: after all, it protects my discipline's funding (at least partially). But this is to mis-understand the interconnected nature of knowledge, of scholarship, and of the modern world as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need first to think about how people use their degrees. Contrary to popular belief (even amongst students), degrees don't generally lead to jobs -- and nor should they. It's true that we teach a lot of information and skills in a degree: how to program, how to analyse algorithms and understand different technologies, in the case of computer science. But this isn't the reason to get a degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we try to teach are the critical skills needed to understand the world, contribute to it and change it. Computer science is a great example of this. Three years ago there were no tablet computers and no cloud computing: the field changes radically even on the timescales of a typical degree programme. So there's not really much point in focusing on particular technologies or languages. What we teach instead is how to &lt;em&gt;learn&lt;/em&gt; new languages and technologies, and how to assess how they fit into the changing pattern of computer science. Put another way, we have to turn them into people who can learn and assimilate complex technological ideas throughout their lives, and create new ones
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Education is what survives when what has been learnt has been forgotten
&lt;p&gt;B.F. Skinner&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
This is even more true in humanities. Most people who study geography do not become geographers (or polar explorers, for that matter): they go into fields that require critical minds who can come to grips with complex ideas. But they bring to these jobs an appreciation of a complex and layered subject, an ability to deal with multiple simultaneous constraints and demands upon shared resources, the interaction of people with the natural world, and so forth. This is much more valuable than the specific knowledge they may have acquired: they have the ability to acquire specific knowledge whenever they need it, and to fit it into the wider scheme of their understanding.
&lt;p&gt;But even if we accept in part the narrower view of education as a direct feeder for the economy -- and realistically we &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to accept it at least to some extent -- reducing humanities graduates seems shortsighted. If we also accept that the future is of a digital and knowledge economy, then the technologies underlying this economy are only one part of it -- and probably only a small part. The rest, the higher-value services, come from content and applications, not directly from the technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider how much value has been created from building computers. Now consider how much value is created from selling things that &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; computers. Computer scientists didn't create much of the latter; nor did physicists, mathematicians, materials scientists or electronic engineers. Humanities people did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So even aside from the reduction in quality of life that would come from reducing the contributions of people who've studied history and literature, there's a direct economic effect in play. Without such people, there'll be no-one to create the digital content and services on which the knowledge economy depends. (It's called &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; economy, remember, not &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt; economy.) Increasing the proportion of knowledgeable, educated people is valuable &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt; for the creativity those people unleash. The fact that we perhaps can't directly trace the route from university student places to value to society doesn't make that contribution unreal: it just means we're not measuring it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we went about inventing computers and the internet we had specific goals in mind, to do with scientific analysis and communication. But it turned out that the most socially significant impacts of these technologies didn't come from these areas at all: they came from people who thought differently about the technology and came up with applications that no computer scientist would &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt; have thought of. It still amazes me that no professional computer scientist -- including me -- ever dreamed of social network sites like Facebook, even though we happily talked about concepts like "social network" and of using computers to examine the ways people interacted at least five years before it debuted. We don't have the mindset to come up with these sorts of applications: we're too close to the technology. Scientists can happily develop services for science: it needs people who are closer to the humanities to develop services for humanity.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Blog</category><category>university</category><guid>https://simondobson.org/blog/2011/07/05/arts-humanities/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2011 07:00:13 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>